<chapter id="technical-infrastructure">

<title>Infra-estrutura técnica</title>

<simplesect>

<para>Projetos de software livre dependem de tecnologia que suportem
a captura e integração seletiva de informação. Quanto mais experiente
você for para usar estas tecnologias, e em persuadir os outras a 
usá-las, mais sucesso terá o seu projeto. Isso só torna mais 
verdadeiro a medida que o projeto cresce. Um bom gerenciamento das
informações é o que garante que os projetos não quebrem sob o peso
da Lei de Brooks,<footnote><para>Do seu livro <citetitle>O Mítico 
Homem-Mês</citetitle>, 1975.  Veja <ulink
url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Mythical_Man-Month"/> e <ulink
url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brooks_Law"/>.</para></footnote>
que diz que adicionar recursos em um projeto atrasado o torna ainda
mais atrasado. Fred Brooks observou que a complexidade de um projeto
aumenta <emphasis>ao quadrado</emphasis> do númeto de participantes.
Quando apenas algumas pessoas estão envolvidas, todos podem falar
facilmente entre si, mas quando centenas de pessoas estão envolvidas,
não é mais possível para cada pessoa permanecer constantemente a par
do que todos os outros estão fazendo. Se um bom gerenciamento de
software é sobre fazer com que todos sintam-se como se estivessem
trabalhando juntos na mesma sala, a questão óbvia é: o que acontece
quando todos em uma sala lotada tentam falar de uma só vez?</para>


<para>Este problema não é novo. Em salas lotadas reais, a solução
é solução é um <firstterm>procedimento parlamentar</firstterm>:
guias formais de como ter discussões em tempo real para grupos
grandes, como assegurar que dissidências importantes não se percam
em inundações de comentários de "eu também", como formar 
subcomissões, como reconhecer quando as decisões são formadas, etc.
Uma parte importante do procedimento parlamentar é especificar como
o grupo interage com seu sistema de gerenciamento de informações.
Alguns comentários são feitos "para registros", outros não. O
registro em si é subjetivo a manipulação direta, e é entendido para
não ser uma transcrição literal do que ocorreu, mas uma 
representação do que o grupo está disposto a 
<emphasis>concordar</emphasis> do ocorrido. O registro não é 
monolítico, mas assume diferentes formas para diferentes propósitos.
Ele compreende os minutos de todas as reuniões, resumos, agendas e
suas anotações, relatório das comissões, relatório de correspondentes
ausentes, lista com ítens de ação, etc.</para>

<para>Como a Internet não é realmente uma sala, não precisamos nos
preocupar em replicar os procedimentos parlamentares que mantém 
algumas pessoas caladas enquanto outras estão falando. Mas quando 
defrontamos com técnicas de gerenciamento de informações, projetos
de código aberto bem executados são procedimentos parlamentares com
esteróides. Desde que quase toda a comunicação em projetos de código
aberto ocorrem na escrita, sistemas elaborados evoluitam para rotear
e identificar o dado corretamente; para minimizar repetições assim
como evitar falsas divergências; para armazenar e recuperar dados;
para corrigir informações ruins ou obsoletas; e para associar 
diferentes pedaços informação a medida que novas conexões são
observadas. Participantes ativos em projetos de código aberto
assumem muito destas técnicar, e irão frequentemente realizar 
tarefas manuais complexas para assegurar que a informação será
roteada corretamente. Mas o grande esforço ultimamente depende de
suporte sofisticado de softwares.

As mídias de comunicações sozinhas deveriam realizar o máximo de
roteamento das informações, identificando, e gravando, e devem
disponibilizar para as pessoas no modo mais conveniente possível.
Claro que na prática, as pessoas ainda precisam intervir em diversos
pontos no processo, e é importante que o software faça com que essas
intervenções sejam convenientes também. Mas em geral, se as pessoas
cuidarem da identificação e roteamento das informações de maneira
minuciosa já na primeira aparição no sistema, então o software
deve ser configurado para utilizar o máximo possível estes metadados.
</para>

<para>O conselho neste capítulo é intensamente prático, baseado em
experiências em um software específico e padrões de uso. Mas o ponto
não é ensinar uma coleção de técnicas particulares. Ele também 
demonstra, através de diversos pequenos exemplos, a atitude geral
que melhor encorajará o bom gerenciamento da informação em seu 
projeto. Esta atitude envolverá uma combinação de conhecimento
técnico com o conhecimento das pessoas. O conhecimento técnico é
essencial pois o software de gerenciamento de informações sempre
requer configuração, além de uma certa quantidade de manutenção e
melhorias a medida que surgem novas necessidades (por exemplo, veja
a discussão de como lidar com o crescimento do projeto em
<xref linkend="bug-filtering"/><phrase output="printed"> adiante
neste capítulo</phrase>). O conhecimento das pessoas são necessários
pois uma comunidade também requer manutenção: nem sempre é óbvio
como usar estas ferramentas como total vantagem, e em alguns casos
os projetos possui convenções conflitantes (por exemplo, veja a
discussão sobre configurar o cabeçalho <systemitem>Responder 
a</systemitem> em e-mails enviados a listas de discussão, em
<xref linkend="mailing-lists"/>). Todos os envolvidos com o projeto
precisarão ser encorajados, no momento certo e da maneira correta,
para que eles façam sua parte em manter as informações do projeto
bem organizada. Quanto mais envolvido estiver colaborador, maior a
possibilidade de que ele aprenda as técnicas mais complexas e 
especializadas.</para>

<para>O gerenciamento de informação não possui uma solução pronta.
Existem muitas variáveis. Você pode ter tudo finalmente configurado
da maneira que queria, e ter a comunidade mais participativa, e
então o crescimento do projeto fará com que algumas destas práticas
sejam impraticáveis. Ou o crescimento do projeto pode estabilizar, e
as comunidades de usuários e desenvolvedores estabeleçam uma relação
confortável com a infra-estrutura técnica, e de repente alguém vem
com uma idéia um novo serviço de gerenciamento de informação, e
logo os recém-chegados estarão perguntando por que o seu projeto
não está usando-a&mdash;por exemplo, isto está ocorrendo agora com
diversos projetos de softwares livre que antecedem a invenção do
wiki (veja <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wiki"/>). Muitas
questões merecem uma análise, envolvendo negociações entra a 
conveniência daqueles que geram informação e a conveniência daqueles
que a consomem, ou entre o tempo requerido para configurar o software
de gerenciamento de informação e o benefício que ele traz ao projeto.
</para>

<para>Cuidado com a tentação de automatizar demais, isto é, automatizar
aquilo que realmente requer uma atenção humana. A infra-estrutura
técnica é importante, mas o que faz o um projeto de software livre
funcionar é o cuidado&mdash;e a expressão inteligente deste 
cuidado&mdash;pelas pessoas envolvidas. A infra-estrutura técnica é
principalmente sobre dar as pessoas formas convenientes de fazer isso.
</para>

</simplesect>


<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="tools-needed">
<title>O Quê Um Projeto Precisa</title>

<para>A maioria dos projetos de código aberto oferecem ao menos um 
conjunto mínimo de ferramentas padrão para gerenciamento da 
informação:</para>

<variablelist>

   <varlistentry><term>Web site</term>
     <listitem>
     <para>Forma principal e centralizar de levar a informação do
           projeto ao público. O web site também pode servir como
           uma interface administrativa para outras ferramentas
           do projeto.</para>
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry><term>Listas de e-mail</term>
     <listitem>
       <para>Geralmente o forum de comunicação mais ativo no
             projeto, e o "meio de registro."</para>
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry><term>Controle de versão</term>
     <listitem>
       <para>Permite aos desenvolvedores gerenciar as mudanças de
             código convenientemente, incluindo a volta de uma versão
             anterior e uma "mudança portátil". Permite com que todos
             possam acompanhar o que está acontecendo com o código.
             </para>
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry><term>Bug tracker</term>
     <listitem>
       <para>Permite aos desenvolvedores acompanhar em que eles estão
             trabalhando, coordenar uns aos outros, e planejar 
             lançamentos. Permite a qualquer um consultar o status de
             bugs e registrar informações (ex.: reproduzir um erro)
             sobre bugs em particular. Pode ser usado para rastrear
             além de bugs, tarefas, lançamentos, novas funcionalidades,
             etc.</para>
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

<!--
   <varlistentry><term>Discussion forums</term>
     <listitem>
       <para><remark>Basically, bulletin board systems.  These are not
             as widespread as one would expect, and where they are
             found, they're not used as much as one would expect.  Why?
             Are they worth mentioning at all?</remark></para>
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
-->

   <varlistentry><term>Chat em tempo real</term>
     <listitem>
       <para>Um local para discussões rápidas e simples, e para
             troca de perguntas e respostas. Nem sempre é
             arquivado por completo.
             </para>
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

</variablelist>

<para>Cada ferramenta deste conjunto é endereçada para uma necessidade
específica, mas suas funções são inter-relacionadas, e as ferramentas
precisam ser feitas para trabalharem junto. A seguir examinaremos como
elas podem fazer isso, e mais importante, como colocar as pessoas para
utilizá-las. O web site não é discutido até o fim, pois ele atua mais
como uma cola para os outros componentes do que uma ferramenta em si.
</para>

<para>Você poderá evitar um monte de dores de cabeça para escolher
e configurar estas ferramentas ao fazer uso de sites de 
<firstterm>hospedagem enlatada</firstterm>: um servidor que oferece
áreas web previamente empacotadas e modeladas com todas as ferramentas
de acompanhamento necessárias para manter um projeto de software livre.
Veja <xref linkend="canned-hosting"/><phrase output="printed"> adiante
neste capítulo</phrase> para uma discussão das vantagens e desvantagens
da hospedagem enlatada.</para>

</sect1>


<!-- ========================== SECTION =========================== -->
<sect1 id="mailing-lists">
<title>Listas de E-mail</title>

<para>Listas de e-mail são o pão com mantega das comunicações do
projeto. Se um usuário é exposto a qualquer fórum além das páginas
web, é bem provável que seja uma das listas de e-mail do projeto.
Mas antes que eles experimentes a lista em si, eles irão se deparar
com a interface da lista de e-mail&mdash;isto é, o mecanismo pelo 
qual eles se juntarão ("increver a") a lista. Isso nos leva a Regra
no. 1 de listas de e-mail:</para>

<blockquote>
   <para><emphasis>Não tente gerenciar listas de e-mail 
   manualmente&mdash;use um software de gerenciamento de 
   lista.</emphasis></para>
</blockquote>

<para>Será tentador descartar esta possibilidade. Configurar um
software de gerenciamento de lista de e-mail pode parecer um pouco
exagerado no início. Gerenciar listas pequenas e com pouco tráfego
manualmente parecerá muito fácil: você só precisa configurar um
endereço de inscrição que encaminhe as mensagens para você, e quando
alguém envia um e-mail, você adiciona (ou remove) o endereço e-mail 
em algum arquivo texto que contém todos os endereços da lista. O
que poderia ser mais simples que isso?</para>

<para>A pegadinha é que um bom gerenciamento da lista de 
e-mail&mdash;que é o que as pessoas esperam&mdash;não é nem um pouco
simples. Não se trata apenas de adicionar ou remover usuários quando
eles pedem. Trata-se também de moderar para evitar spam, oferecer um
e-mail com resumos ou mensagem a mensagem, fornecer a lista padrão e
informações do projeto através de auto-resposta, e várias outras
coisas. Uma monitoração humana do endereço de inscrição pode fornecer
apenas um mínimo de funcionalidade, e ainda assim não tão confiável
e rápido quanto pode fazer um software.</para>

<para>Um software moderno de gerenciamento de listas oferece no 
mínimo as seguintes funcionalidades:</para>

<variablelist>

  <varlistentry><term>Inscrição por e-mail e através da web</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Quando um usuário se inscreve a uma lista, ele pode
            <emphasis>imediatamente</emphasis> receber uma mensagem
            de boas vindas, dizendo que ele foi inscrito, como 
            interagir com o software da lista de e-mail, e (mais
            importante) como cancelar a inscrição. Esta resposta
            automática pode ser customizada para conter informações
            específicas do projeto, tais como o web site, 
            localização do FAQ, etc.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Inscrição em modo digerido (digest) ou
                      mensagem a mensagem</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>No modo digerido, o inscrito recebe um e-mail por dia, 
            contento toda a atividade da lista naquele dia. Para 
            pessoas que estão acompanhando vagamente a lista, sem
            participar, este modo é geralmente mais adequado, pois
            permite a eles olharem todos os assuntos de uma só vez
            e evitar a distração de e-mails chegando em horários 
            aleatórios.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Funcionalidades de moderação</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>"Moderar" é verificar os envios e assegurar que eles
            a)&nbsp;não&nbsp;sejam spam, e 
            b)&nbsp;estejam&nbsp;dentro do tópico, antes que eles
            sejam enviados para toda a lista. A moderação envolve
            necessariamente humanos, mas o software pode ajudar
            bastante para torná-la mais fácil. Haverá mais conteúdo
            sobre moderação adiante.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Interface administrativa</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Entre outras coisas, ela permite que o administrador acesse
            e remova endereços obsoletos facilmente. Isso pode tornar-se
            urgente quando um endereço destinatário passa a enviar
            respostas automáticas com "Eu não utilizo mais este e-mail"
            de volta para a lista para todas as outras mensagens. (Alguns
            softwares conseguem detectar este comportamente e remover
            a pessoa automaticamente.)</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Manipulação de cabeçalho</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Muitas pessoas possuem filtros sofisticados e regras de
            resposta configuradas em seus clientes de e-mail. Os 
            softwares de listas de e-mail podem adicionar e manipular
            alguns cabeçalhos padrões para que essas pessoas possam
            obter alguma vantagem disso (mais detalhes a seguir).
            </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Arquivamento</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Todos os enviados para uma lista gerenciada são armazenados
            e disponibilizados na web; alternativamente, alguns 
            softwares de listas de e-mail oferecem interfaces especiais
            para conectar uma ferramenta externa de arquivamento como
            o MHonArc
            (<ulink url="http://www.mhonarc.org/"/>). Como 
             <xref
            linkend="using-archives"/><phrase output="printed">
            discute no <xref linkend="communications"/></phrase>,
            o arquivamento é crucial.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

</variablelist>

<para>O ponto de tudo isto é meramente para enfatizar que o 
gerenciamento de listas de e-mail é um problema complexo o qual foi
pensado bastante, e resolvido em sua maioria. Você certamente não 
precisa se tornar um especialista nisso. Mas você deve estar a par
que sempre há espaço para aprender mais, e que o gerenciamento da
lista irá ocupar a sua atenção de tempos em tempos no curso da
execução de um projeto de software livre. A seguir nós examinaremos
um pouco dos problemas mais comum na configuração das listas de
e-mail.</para>

<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="spam-prevention">
<title>Prevenção de Spam</title>

<para>No intervalo em que esta sentença é publicada, o tamanho do
problema de spam provavelmente terá sua gravidade dobrada&mdash; ou
ao menos estará neste camninho. Há não muito tempo atrás era possível
que alguém abrisse uma lista de e-mails sem precisar tomar nenhuma
medida de prevenção. Os e-mails de spam ainda iriam aparecer, com
com tão pouca frequência que era um problema de nível bem baixo.
Este tempo se foi para sempre. Hoje, uma lista de e-mail que não
toma medidas de prevenção de spam será rapidamente submersa por
lixos de e-mail, ao ponto de ficar inutilizável. A prevenção de
spam é obrigatória.</para>

<para>Dividimos a prevenção de spam em duas categorias: previnindo
que envios de spam apareçam na sua lista de e-amils, e previnindo
a sua lista de e-mails de ser a fonte de novos endereços de e-mails
para spammers. A primeira é a mais importante, e iremos examiná-la 
primeiro.</para>

<sect3 id="spam-filtering">
<title>Filtrando os envios</title>

<para>Existem três técnicas básicas de previnir envios de spam, e a
maior parte de software de listas de e-mail oferece todas elas. Elas
são melhores se usadas em conjunto:</para>

<orderedlist>

  <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Permita apenas que os inscritos
            enviem e-mails para lista.</emphasis></para>

            <para>Isso é muito efetivo efetivo, e envolve apenas um
            pequeno esforço administrativo, pois geralmente é apenas 
            uma questão de configuração no software de gerenciamento
            da lista de e-mails. Mas perceba que os envios que não são
            aprovados automaticamente não podem ser simplesmente 
            descartados. Ao invés disso, eles devem passar por uma
            moderação, por duas razões. Primeiro, você quer que os
            não inscritos possam enviar e-mails. Uma pessoa com uma 
            questão ou uma sugestão não precisa se inscrever na lista
            apenas para deixar uma única mensagem. Segundo, mesmo os
            inscritos poder de vez em quando enviar mensagens de um
            endereço diferente que não está inscrito. Endereços de
            e-mail não são métodos confiáveis de se identificar as 
            pessoas, e não deveriam ser usados para tal fim.</para>
            </listitem>

  <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Filtre os envios através de
            um software de filtro de spams.</emphasis></para>

            <para>Se o software de lista de e-mail permitir (a 
            maioria permite), você pode filtrar as mensagens com um
            software de filtro de spams. O filtro de spam automático
            não é perfeito, e nunca será, pois existe uma guerra
            sem fim entre spammers e escritores de filtros. Contanto,
            pode ser ótimo em reduzir a quantidade de spam que chegam
            através da fila de moderação, e como maior o tamanho da
            fila, mais tempo uma pessoa levará para examiná-la, 
            qualquer quantidade de filtragem automática é benéfica.
            </para>

            <para>Não há espaço aqui para instruções detalhadas de
            configuraraçã dos filtros de spam. Você terá de consultar
            a documentação do seu software de lista de e-mails para 
            isso (veja  <xref
            linkend="mailing-list-software"/><phrase
            output="printed"> adiante neste capítulo</phrase>).
            Os softwares de listas geramente vem embutido com 
            funcionalidades de prevenção de spam, mas você pode 
            querer colocar filtros de terceiros. Eu tive boas 
            experiências com esses dois:
            SpamAssassin
            (<ulink url="http://spamassassin.apache.org/"/>)
            e SpamProbe
            (<ulink url="http://spamprobe.sourceforge.net/"/>). 

            Este não é um comentário a respeito de diversos outros 
            filtros de spam existentes por aí, alguns dos quais são
            aparentemente muito bons. Eu apenas usei esses dois e
            fiquei satisfeito com eles.</para>

  </listitem>

  <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Moderação.</emphasis></para>
            <para>Para e-mais que não são automaticamente autorizados
            por não ser de um inscrito, e que passou pelos softwares
            de filtro de spam, caso haja algum, o último estágio é a
            <firstterm>moderação</firstterm>: o e-mail é direcionado
            para um endereço especial, onde uma pessoa o examina e
            o confirma ou o rejeita.</para>

            <para>Confirmar um envio pode ser uma das duas formas:
            você pode aceitar a mensagem apenas desta vez, ou você
            pode dizer ao software da lista para permitir este e
            todas as mensagens futuras provenientes do mesmo 
            remetente. Você quase sempre irá preferir a última forma,
            com objetivo de reduzir o fardo da moderação futura. 
            Detalhes de como confirmar variam de sistema para 
            sistema, mas geralmente é uma questão de responder a um
            endereço especial com o comando "accept" (significando
            a confirmação apenas desta mensagem) ou "allow",
            (permitindo a mensagem atual e futuras).</para>
            
            <para>A rejeição é geralmente feita simplesmente 
            ignorando o e-mail de moderação. Se o software de lista 
            nunca receber a confirmação de que não é uma mensagem
            válida, então ele não irá repassar a mensagem para a 
            lista, o que simplesmente excluir o e-mail de moderação
            surte o efeito desejado. Algumas vezes você também tem a
            opção de responder com os comandos "reject" ou "deny", 
            para desaprovar automaticamente e-mails futuros deste
            remetente sem precisar passar novamente pela moderação.
            Raramente há um sentido em fazer isso, pois a moderação
            trata na maioria de prevenção de spam, e spammers não
            costumam realizar envios do mesmo endereço mais de uma
            vez.</para>
            </listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>Certifique-se de usar a moderação <emphasis>apenas</emphasis> 
para filtrar spams e mensagens que estão claramente fora do escopo,
tais como quando alguém envia uma mensagem acidentalmente para a
lista errada. O sistema de moreração geralmente fornece uma forma
de se responder diretamente ao remetente, mas não use este método 
para responder questões que realmente pertencem a lista em si, mesmo
se você souber a resposta de cabeça. Fazer isso privaria a comunidade
do projeto de uma visão apurada dos tipos de questões que as pessoas
estão fazendo, e irá privá-las de uma chance de responder as questões
elas mesmas e/ou ver a resposta dos demais. A moderação da lista é
estritamente sobre manter a lista livre de e-mails de lixo e fora
do tópico, e nada mais.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="address-hiding">
<title>Camuflando endereços em arquivos da lista</title>

<para>Para evitar que suas listas de e-mail sejam uma fonte de
endereços para spammers, uma técnica comum é camuflar os endereços
das pessoas nos arquivos, substituindo por exemplo</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para><literal>jrandom@somedomain.com</literal></para>
    </blockquote>

<para>por</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para><literal>jrandom_AT_somedomain.com</literal></para>
    </blockquote>

<para>ou</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para><literal>jrandomNOSPAM@somedomain.com</literal></para>
    </blockquote>

<para>ou alguma codificação similar e óbvia (para humanos). Como os
caçadores de e-mails para spam geralmente trabalham rastreando páginas
da internet&mdash;incluindo os arquivos online se suas listas de 
e-mail&mdash;e procurando por sequências que contenham "@", camuflar
os endereços é uma forma de deixar os endereços de e-mail das pessoas 
invisível ou sem utilidade para os spammers. Claro que isto não faz 
nada para evitar que spams sejam enviados da própria lista de e-mail, 
mas evita o aumento do número de spams enviados diretamente para os 
e-mails pessoais dos usuários da lista.</para>

<para>A camuflagem de endereços pode ser controversa. Algumas pessoas
gostam bastante e ficarão surpresas se seus arquivos não fizerem isso
automaticamente. Outras pessoas acham muito incoveniente (pois elas
também devem traduzí-los antes de o usarem). Algumas vezes as pessoas
asseguram que não tem efeito, uma vez que os caçadores podem em teoria
compensar qualquer padrão de camuflagem consistente. Entretanto, note
que há uma evidência empírica que a camuflagem de endereços
<emphasis>é</emphasis> efetiva, veja <ulink
url="http://www.cdt.org/speech/spam/030319spamreport.shtml"/>.</para>

<para>Idealmente, o software de gerenciamento da lista deixará a 
escolha a cada inscrito, tanto por um cabeçalho especial com um
Sim/Não ou então nas preferências da conta daquele inscrito. Contanto,
eu não conheço um software que oferece uma opção por inscrito ou por
mensagem em relação a isso, deixando uma decisão a ser tomada pelo
administrador para todos (assumindo que o arquivador oferece esta
funcionalidade, o que nem sempre é o caso). Eu fico levemente 
inclinado em direção a ligar a opção de camuflagem. Algumas pessoas
são muito cuidadosas e evitam colocar seus endereços de e-mail em
uma página web ou qualquer outra local que um caçador de e-mails para
spam possa vê-lo, e eles ficarão desapontados ao ter todo o trabalho
jogado fora por um arquivo de lista de e-mails; enquanto isso, a 
incoveniência que a camuflagem e e-mails impõe aos usuários de
arquivos são bem leves, pois é fácil transformar um e-mail camuflado
em um e-mail válido se você precisar contatar diretamente a pessoa.
Mas tenha em mente que, no final, ainda é uma corrida de armamentos:
no momento que estiver lendo isto, os caçadores podem muito bem ter
evoluído ao ponto que eles possam reconhecer as formas mais comuns
de camuflagem, e nós teremos de pensar em alguma outra coisa.</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="header-management">
<title>Gerenciamento de Identificação e de Cabeçalho</title>

<para>Os assinantes de listas geralmente querem deixar os e-mails da 
lista em uma pasta específica do projeto, separando-os dos demais
e-mails. O software de e-mail pode fazer isto automaticamente examinando
os <firstterm>cabeçalhos</firstterm> dos e-mails. Os cabeçalhos são 
campos especiais no topo do e-mail que identifica o remetente, 
destinatário, assunto, data, e várias outras informações sobre a 
mensagem. Certos cabeçalhos são bem conhecidos e obrigatótios 
efetivamente:</para>

<screen>
De: ...
Para: ...
Assunto: ...
Data: ...
</screen>

<para>outros são opcionais, mas ainda assim padrões. Por exemplo,
e-mails não requerem estritamente ter o cabeçalho</para>

<screen>
Responder a: sender@email.address.here
</screen>

<para>mas a maioria o faz, porque isso dá aos destinatários uma
forma infalível de se chegar ao autor (isto é especialmente útil
quando o autor teve que enviar de um endereço diferente ao qual
as respostas deveriam ser direcionadas).</para>

<para>Alguns softwares de leitura de e-mail ofecerem uma interface
amigavel para arquivamento de e-mails baseado em padrões no cabeçalho
Assunto. Isso leva as pessoas a solicitarem que a lista de e-mail
adicione automaticamente um prefixo em todos os Assuntos, e então
eles poderão configurar os leitores para buscar por aquele prefixo
e automaticamente arquivar a mensagem na pasta correta. A idéia é
que o autor original escreveria:</para>

<screen>
Assunto: Construindo o release 2.5.
</screen>

<para>mas o e-mail apareceria na lista desta forma:</para>

<screen>
Assunto: [discuss@lists.example.org] Construindo o release 2.5.
</screen>

<para>Apesar da maioria de software de gerenciamento de listas 
oferecer uma opção para isso, eu sou fortemente contra este opção
habilitada. O problema que ela resolve pode facilmente ser 
resolvido de uma maneira menos importuna, e o preço de se perder boa 
parte do campo de Assunto é extremamente alto. Usuários experientes
de listas de e-mail normalmente olham os assuntos de e-mails que
chegaram no dia para decidir quais ler e/ou responder. Prefixar o
nome da lista no assunto pode empurrar o Assunto para a direita
na tela, deixando-o invisível. Isso ofusca a informação que as
pessoas dependem para decidir quais e-mails serão abertos, reduzindo
assim a funcionalidade geral da lista para todo mundo.</para>

<para>Ao invés de adulterar o cabeçalho Assunto, ensine aos seus
usuários a usarem a vantagem de outros cabeçalhos padrões, começando
com o "Para", que deve informar o nome da lista:</para>

<screen>
Para: &lt;discuss@lists.example.org&gt;
</screen>

<para>Qualquer leitor de e-mail que pode filtrar o Assunto deve ser
capaz de filtrar o Para facilmente.</para>

<para>Existem outro cabeçalhos opcionais mas padrões para listas de
e-mail. Filtrar por eles é ainda mais confiável que usar os cabeçalhos
"Para" ou "Cc"; como esses cabeçalhos são colocados em cada mensagem
pelo próprio software de gerenciamento da lista, alguns usuários 
podem estar contando com a presença deles:</para>

<screen>
list-help: &lt;mailto:discuss-help@lists.example.org&gt;
list-unsubscribe: &lt;mailto:discuss-unsubscribe@lists.example.org&gt;
list-post: &lt;mailto:discuss@lists.example.org&gt;
Delivered-To: mailing list discuss@lists.example.org
Mailing-List: contact discuss-help@lists.example.org; run by ezmlm
</screen>

<para>Eles são auto-explicativos na sua maioria. Veja <ulink
url="http://www.nisto.com/listspec/list-manager-intro.html"/> para 
maiores esclarecimentos, ou se você precisa de uma especificação 
formal e realmente detalhada, veja
<ulink url="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc2369.html"/>.
</para>

<para>Perceba em quanto esses cabeçalhos complicam caso você tenha
uma lista de e-mail com o nome de "list", e que você tenha os
endereços administrativos "list-help" e "list-subscribe", para
inscrições, e "list-owner", para contatar os administradores da lista.
Dependendo do software de gerenciamento da lista que você usa, esses
e/ou vários outros endereços administrativos poderiam estar 
encrencados; a documentação terá os detalhes. Normalmente uma 
explicação completa de todos estes endereços especiais é enviado para
cada novo usuário como parte de um e-mail automático de "boas vindas"
na inscrição. Provavelmente você terá uma cópia deste e-mail de boas
vindas. Se não tiver, peça uma cópia a alguém, para saber o que os
seus usuários estão vendo quando eles assinam a lista. Mantenha a 
cópia por perto para poder responder questões sobre a lista de e-mails,
ou melhor ainda, coloque-a em uma página web em algum lugar. Desta
forma quando alguém perder a própria cópia das instruções e perguntar
"Como eu cancelo a inscrição nesta lista?", você apenas envia a ela
a URL.</para>

<para>Alguns softwares de lista de e-mail oferecem a opção de anexar
as instruções de cancelamento ao final de todas as mensagens. Se 
esta opção estiver disponível, habilite-a. Ele coloca apenas algumas
linhas extras por mensagem, em um local inofensivo, e te ajuda a
ganhar tempo, diminuindo o número de pessoas que enviam mensagens para 
você&mdash;ou pior, enviam para lista!&mdash;peguntando sobre como
cancelam a inscrição.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="reply-to">
<title>O Longo Debate do Responder a</title>

<para>Anteriormente em  <xref linkend="avoid-private-discussions"/>, eu
enfatizei a importância de certificar-se de que as discussões fiquem nos
forums públicos, e falei sobre a necessidade de algumas medidas ativas
para evitar que as conversas passem para um ambiente com discussão 
privada; além disso, este capítulo tratou da configuração de softwares
de comunicação do projeto para fazer o máximo de trabalho possível
para você. Por isso, se o software de gerenciamento de lista oferece
uma maneira de manter as discussões na lista automaticamente, você
certamente pensará que deixar esta opção ligada é a uma escolha óbvia.
</para>

<para>Bem, não é bem assim. A tal opção existe, mas ela possui algumas
desvantagens graves. A questão de usá-la ou não é uma das discussões
mais fervorosas sobre gerenciamento de listas de e-mail.&mdash;na
verdade, não é uma controvérsia que iria ao noticiário do horário 
nobre na sua cidade, mas ele pode vir a tona de tempos em tempos
em projetos de software livre. A seguir, descreverei esta opção,
elucidando os argumentos dos dois lados, e farei a melhor recomendação
que puder.</para>

<para>A opção em si é bem simples: o software da lista de e-mails pode,
se você quiser, colocar automaticamente o cabeçalho "Responder a" em
todas as mensagens para redirecionar as respostas para a lista de 
e-mail. Isto é, não importa o que o remetente original coloque no
cabeçalho "Responder a" (ou mesmo se ele não incluir nenhum), quando
os assinantes da lista virem a mensagem, o cabeçalho irá conter o
endereço da lista:</para>

<screen>
Reply-to: discuss@lists.example.org
</screen>

<para>A primeira vista, isto parece ser algo bom. Por que 
virtualmente todo leitor de e-mail reconhece o cabeçalho "Responder a",
então quando alguém responder a mensagem, a resposta irá diretamente
para toda a lista automaticamente, e não apenas ao remetente da
mensagem original. Claro que quem responde ainda pode mudar manualmente
para onde vai a mensagem, mas o que é importante aqui é que as 
respostas serão direcionadas a lista <emphasis>por padrão</emphasis>.
É um exemplo perfeito de utilizar a tecnologia para encorajar a
colaboração.</para>

<para>Infelizmente, existem algumas desvantagens. A primeira é
conhecida como o problema <firstterm>Não consigo encontrar o
caminho de volta pra casa</firstterm>: Algumas vezes, o remetente
original irá colocar o seu endereço de e-mail "real" no campo
"Responder a", pois por uma razão ou outra ele envia e-mails de
um endereço diferente do qual ele usa para recebê-los. Pessoas 
que sempre leem e enviam do mesmo local não tem este problema,
e podem até ficar surpresos que isso possa existir. Mas para aqueles
que possuem configurações de e-mail diferenciadas, ou que não 
possuem controle para alterar o endereço de envio (talvez 
porque enviem do trabalho e não possuem nenhuma influência no
departamento de TI), usando o "Responder a" pode ser a única
forma que eles tem de assegurar que as respostas cheguem até
eles. Quando tal pessoa envia mensagem para a lista de e-mails
o qual ela não está inscrivta, sua configuração de "Responder a"
torna-se uma informação essencial. Se o software da lista o
sobrescreve, pode ser que ele nunca veja as respostas para
sua mensagem.</para>

<para>A segunda desvantagem tem a ver com as expectativas, e na
minha opinião é o argumento mais forte contra a alteração do 
"Responder a". Usuários de e-mails mais experientes estão acostumados
a dois métodos básicos de resposta: <firstterm>responder a 
todos</firstterm> e <firstterm>responder ao autor</firstterm>.
Todos os softwares modernos de leitura de e-mail possuem formas
diferenciadas para estas duas ações. O usuários sabem que para 
responder a todos (isto é, incluindo a lista), eles precisam
escolher "Responder a todos", e para responder somente ao autor, eles
precisam escolher "Responder ao autor". Embora você queira encorajar
as pessoas a responder para a lista sempre que possível, existem
certas circunstâncias onde uma resposta privada é a prerrogativa do 
autor&mdah;por exemplo, eles podem querer dizer algo confidencial 
para o autor da mensagem original, algo que seria inapropriado para
para a lista pública.</para>

<para>Agora considere o que acontece quando a lista sobreescreveu o
"Reponder a" original do rementente. Quem responder irá acionar a
opção "responder ao autor", com a expectativa de estar enviando uma
mensagem privada de volta ao autor original. Como este é o 
comportamento experado, ele pode nem mesmo se importar em olhar
cuidadosamente para o endereço do destinatários na nova mensagem. 
Ele compõe sua mensagem confidencial e privada, da qual talvez diga
algo embaraçoso sobre alguém da lista, e envia o e-mail. 
Inexperadamente, alguns minutos depois a mensagem aparece 
<emphasis>na lista de e-mails!</emphasis> É verdade que na teoria
ele deveria olhar atentamente ao campo de destinatário, e não deveria
aceitar qualquer coisa sobre o cabeçalho "responder a". Mas os autores
quase sempre colocam o "Responder a" para seu endereço pessoal (ou
então, o software de e-mails configura isso para eles), e muitos 
usuários antigos de e-mail vem a esperar por isso. Na verdade, quando
alguém propositalmente configura o "responde a" para algum outro 
endereço, ele geralmente cita isso no corpo da mensagem, para que as
pessoas não fiquem surpreendidas com o que acontece quando elas 
responderem a nebsagem.</para>

<para>Devido a possibilidades de consequências sérias por este 
comportamento inexperado, minha preferência pessoal é conifigurar o
software para nunca todas no cabeçalho "responder a". Esta é uma área
onde usar a tecnologia para encorajar a colaboração possui ao meu 
ver, efeitos colaterais altamente perigosos. Entretanto, existem 
fortes argumentos do outro lado desta discussão. Independente de qual
você escolha, sempre haverão pessoas perguntando porque você não 
utilizou a outra maneira. Como isto não é algo que você irá querer
como tópico perincipal de discussão na sua lista de e-mail, pode
ser interessante ter uma responta pronta para isso, uma do tipo que
irá frear a discussão ao invés de encorajá-la. Certifique-se que você
<emphasis>não</emphasis> insista que a sua decisão, independende de
qual seja, é obviamente a única e a mais sensata (mesmo que você
realmente ache isto). Ao invè disso, diga que isto é um debate antigo,
e que há bons argumentos dos dois lados, e nenhuma escolha irá
satisfazer a todos os usuários, e que você procurou tomar a melhor 
decisão que você pode. Educadamente peça que o assunto não seja 
levado adianta a menos que alguém tenha algo genuinamente novo a
dizer, e então fique fora da discussão e espere que ele morra de
morte natural.</para>

<para>Alguém pode sugerir em votar em uma maneira ou na outra. Você
pode fazer isso se quiser, mas eu pessoalmente não acho que contar
votos é uma solução adequada neste caso. A penalidade para quem
for surpreendido por este comportamento é tão grande (enviar 
acidentalmente um e-mail para uma lista pública), e a inconveniência
para todos os outros é razoavelmente pequena (ocasionalmente ter que
lembrar alguém a responder para toda a lista ao invés de a você
somente), que não é claro que a maioria, mesmo que eles sejam a 
maioria, deveriam ser capazes de colocar a minoria em risco.</para>

<para>Eu não enderecei todos os aspectos deste problema aqui, apenas
os que parecem ser de extrema importância. Para uma discussão completa,
verifique estes dois documentos ortodoxos, os quais são sempre citados
quando as pessoas entram neste debate:

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
     <para><emphasis role="bold">Leave Reply-to alone (Deixe o Responder a em paz)</emphasis>,
     <emphasis>por Chip Rosenthal</emphasis></para>
     <para><ulink
        url="http://www.unicom.com/pw/reply-to-harmful.html"/></para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para><emphasis role="bold">Set Reply-to to list (Configure o Responder a para lista)</emphasis>,
     <emphasis>por Simon Hill</emphasis></para>
     <para><ulink
        url="http://www.metasystema.net/essays/reply-to.mhtml"/></para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</para>

<para>Apesar a leve preferência indicada acima, eu não acho que haja 
uma resposta "certa" para esta questão, e participo com felicidade em
muitas listas que <emphasis>realmente</emphasis> configuram o "responder 
a". A coisa mais importante que você pode fazer é configurar uma das
formas logo no início, e procurar não se envolver em futuros debates 
depois disso.</para>

<sect3 id="reply-fantasies">
<title>Duas fantasias</title>

<para>Algum dia, alguém terá a idéia brilante de implementar o botão
<firstterm>responder a lista</firstterm> no leitor de e-mails. Isto
utilizarias um dos cabeçalhos de lista customizados mencionados 
anteriormente para identificar o endereço da lista de e-mails, e 
então responde diretamente e apenas para a lista, deixando de lado
todos os outros e-mails de destinatários, pois a maioria está inscrita
de qualquer forma. Eventualmente, outros leitores de e-mail irão
adotar a característica, e todo esta discussão irá embora. (Na verdade,
o leitor de e-mail <ulink url="http://www.mutt.org/">Mutt</ulink>
oferece esta funcionalidade.<footnote><para>Logo depois que este livro
apareceu, <ulink url="http://www.michaelbernstein.com/"
>Michael Bernstein</ulink> me escreveu para dizer: "Existem outros
clientes de e-mail que implementam a função de responder a lista além
do Mytt. Por exemplo, o Evolution tem esta função como um atalho de
teclado, mas não um botão (Ctrl+L)."</para></footnote>)</para>

<para>Uma outra solução ainda melhor seria a configuração para cada
usuário quanto a alteração do "Responder a". Aqueles que quiserem
configurar a alteração automática da lista (tanto das próprias 
mensagens de e-mail quanto dos demais) poderia solicitar isso, e
aqueles que não quiserem a alteração, não mexem em nada. No entanto,
eu não conheço um software de gerenciamento de lista que oferece
isto no nível de perfil de inscritos. No momento, parece que estamos
presos a uma configuração global.<footnote><para>Desde que escrevi
isso, eu descobri que existe ao menos um sistema de gerenciamento
de lista que oferece isto: 
<ulink url="http://siesta.unixbeard.net/">Siesta</ulink>.
Veja também este artigo sobre ele:
<ulink url="http://www.perl.com/pub/a/2004/02/05/siesta.html"
/></para></footnote></para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="archiving">
<title>Arquivamento</title>

<para>The technical details of setting up mailing list archiving are
specific to the software that's running the list, and are beyond the
scope of this book.  When choosing or configuring an archiver,
consider these qualities:</para>

<variablelist>

  <varlistentry><term>Prompt updating</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>People will often want to refer to an archived post made
            within the last hour or two.  If possible, the archiver
            should archive each post instantaneously, so that by the
            time a post appears on the mailing list, it's already
            present in the archives.  If that option isn't available,
            then at least try to set the archiver to update itself
            every hour or so.  (By default, some archivers run their
            update processes once per night, but in practice that's
            far too much lag time for an active mailing list.)</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Referential stability</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Once a message is archived at a particular URL, it should
            remain accessible at that exact same URL forever, or as
            close to forever as possible.  Even if the archives are
            rebuilt, restored from backup, or otherwise fixed, any
            URLs that have already been made publicly available
            should remain the same.  Stable references make it
            possible for Internet search engines to index the
            archives, which is a major boon to users looking for
            answers.  Stable references are also important because
            mailing list posts and threads are often linked to from
            the bug tracker (see
            <xref
            linkend="bug-tracker"/>)<phrase output="printed">
            later in this chapter</phrase> or
            from other project documents.</para>

      <para>Ideally, mailing list software would include a message's
            archive URL, or at least the message-specific portion of
            the URL, in a header when it distributes the message to
            recipients.  That way people who have a copy of the
            message would be able to know its archive location
            without having to actually visit the archives, which would
            be helpful because any operation that involves one's web
            browser is automatically time-consuming.  Whether any
            mailing list software actually offers this feature, I don't
            know; unfortunately, the ones I have used do not.
            However, it's something to look for (or, if you write
            mailing list software, it's a feature to consider
            implementing, please).</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Backups</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>It should be reasonably obvious how to back up the
            archives, and the restoration recipe should not be too
            difficult.  In other words, don't treat your archiver as a
            black box.  You (or someone in your project) should know
            where it's storing the messages, and how to regenerate the
            actual archive pages from the message store if it should
            ever become necessary.  Those archives are precious
            data&mdash;a project that loses them loses a good part of
            its collective memory.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Thread support</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>It should be possible to go from any individual message to
            the <firstterm>thread</firstterm> (group of related
            messages) that that original message is part of.  Each
            thread should have its own URL too, separate from the URLs
            of the individual messages in the thread.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Searchability</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>An archiver that doesn't support searching&mdash;on the
            bodies of messages, as well as on authors and
            subjects&mdash;is close to useless.  Note that some archivers 
            support searching by simply farming the work out to an
            external search engine such as <ulink
            url="http://www.google.com/">Google</ulink>.  This is
            acceptable, but direct search support is usually more
            fine-tuned, because it allows the searcher to specify that
            the match must appear in a subject line versus the body,
            for example.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

</variablelist>

<para>The above is just a technical checklist to help you evaluate and
set up an archiver.  Getting people to
actually <emphasis>use</emphasis> the archiver to the project's
advantage is discussed in later chapters, in particular
<xref linkend="using-archives"/>.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="mailing-list-software">
<title>Software</title>

<para>Here are some open source tools for doing list management and
archiving.  If the site where you're hosting your project already has
a default setup, then you may not ever have to decide on a tool at
all.  But if you must install one yourself, these are some
possibilities.  The ones I have actually used are Mailman, Ezmlm,
MHonArc, and Hypermail, but that doesn't mean the others aren't good
too (and of course, there are probably other tools out there that I
just didn't happen to find, so don't take this as a complete
list).</para>

<para>Mailing list management software:</para>

<itemizedlist>
 <listitem>
   <para><emphasis role="bold">Mailman</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
         url="http://www.list.org/"/></para>
   <para>(Has built-in archiver, and hooks for plugging in
         external archivers.)</para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
   <para><emphasis role="bold">SmartList</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
         url="http://www.procmail.org/"/></para>
   <para>(Meant to be used with the Procmail mail processing system.)</para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
   <para><emphasis role="bold">Ecartis</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
         url="http://www.ecartis.org/"/></para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
   <para><emphasis role="bold">ListProc</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
         url="http://listproc.sourceforge.net/"/></para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
   <para><emphasis role="bold">Ezmlm</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
         url="http://cr.yp.to/ezmlm.html"/></para>
   <para>(Designed to work with the <ulink
         url="http://cr.yp.to/qmail.html">Qmail</ulink> mail
         delivery system.)</para> 
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
   <para><emphasis role="bold">Dada</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
         url="http://mojo.skazat.com/"/></para>
   <para>(Despite the web site's bizarre attempts to hide the fact,
         this is free software, released under the GNU General
         Public License.  It also has a built-in archiver.)</para>
 </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Mailing list archiving software:</para>

<itemizedlist>
 <listitem>
   <para><emphasis role="bold">MHonArc</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
         url="http://www.mhonarc.org/"/></para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
   <para><emphasis role="bold">Hypermail</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
         url="http://www.hypermail.org/"/></para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
   <para><emphasis role="bold">Lurker</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
         url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/lurker/"/></para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
   <para><emphasis role="bold">Procmail</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
         url="http://www.procmail.org/"/></para>
   <para>(Companion software to SmartList, this is a general mail
         processing system that can, apparently, be configured as an
         archiver.)</para>
 </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

</sect1>


<!-- ========================== SECTION =========================== -->
<sect1 id="vc">
<title>Version Control</title>

<para>A <firstterm>version control system</firstterm> (or
<firstterm>revision control system</firstterm>) is a combination of
technologies and practices for tracking and controlling changes to a
project's files, in particular to source code, documentation, and web
pages.  If you have never used version control before, the first thing
you should do is go find someone who has, and get them to join your
project.  These days, everyone will expect at least your project's
source code to be under version control, and probably will not take
the project seriously if it doesn't use version control with at least
minimal competence.</para>

<para>The reason version control is so universal is that it helps with
virtually every aspect of running a project: inter-developer
communications, release management, bug management, code stability and
experimental development efforts, and attribution and authorization of
changes by particular developers.  The version control system provides
a central coordinating force among all of these areas.  The core of
version control is <firstterm>change management</firstterm>:
identifying each discrete change made to the project's files,
annotating each change with metadata like the change's date and
author, and then replaying these facts to whoever asks, in whatever
way they ask.  It is a communications mechanism where a change is the
basic unit of information.</para>

<para>This section does not discuss all aspects of using a version
control system.  It's so all-encompassing that it must be addressed
topically throughout the book.  Here, we will concentrate on choosing
and setting up a version control system in a way that will foster
cooperative development down the road.</para>

<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-vocabulary">
<title>Version Control Vocabulary</title>

<para>This book cannot teach you how to use version control if you've
never used it before, but it would be impossible to discuss the
subject without a few key terms.  These terms are useful independently
of any particular version control system: they are the basic nouns and
verbs of networked collaboration, and will be used generically
throughout the rest of this book.  Even if there were no version
control systems in the world, the problem of change management would
remain, and these words give us a language for talking about that
problem concisely.

<variablelist>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-commit">
  <term><firstterm>commit</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>To make a change to the project; more formally, to
  store a change in the version control database in such a way that it
  can be incorporated into future releases of the project.  "Commit"
  can be used as a verb or a noun.  As a noun, it is essentially
  synonymous with "change".  For example: "I just committed a fix for
  the server crash bug people have been reporting on Mac OS X.  Jay,
  could you please review the commit and check that I'm not misusing
  the allocator there?"</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-log-message">
  <term><firstterm>log&nbsp;message</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>A bit of commentary attached to each commit,
  describing the nature and purpose of the commit.  Log messages are
  among the most important documents in any project: they are the
  bridge between the highly technical language of individual code
  changes and the more user-oriented language of features, bugfixes,
  and project progress.  Later in this section, we'll look at ways to
  distribute log messages to the appropriate audiences; also, <xref
  linkend="codifying-tradition"/><phrase output="printed"> in
  <xref linkend="communications"/></phrase> discusses ways to
  encourage contributors to write concise and useful log
  messages.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-update">
  <term><firstterm>update</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>To ask that others' changes (commits) be
  incorporated into your local copy of the project; that is, to bring
  your copy "up-to-date".  This is a very common operation; most
  developers update their code several times a day, so that they know
  they're running roughly the same thing the other developers are
  running, and so that if they see a bug, they can be pretty sure it
  hasn't been fixed already.  For example: "Hey, I noticed the
  indexing code is always dropping the last byte.  Is this a new bug?"
  "Yes, but it was fixed last week&mdash;try updating, it should go
  away."</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-repository">
  <term><firstterm>repository</firstterm></term> <listitem><para>A
  database in which changes are stored.  Some version control systems
  are centralized: there is a single, master repository, which stores
  all changes to the project.  Others are decentralized: each
  developer has his own repository, and changes can be swapped back
  and forth between repositories arbitrarily.  The version control
  system keeps track of dependencies between changes, and when it's
  time to make a release, a particular set of changes is approved for
  that release.  The question of whether centralized or decentralized
  is better is one of the enduring holy wars of software development;
  try not to fall into the trap of arguing about it on your project
  lists.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-checkout">
  <term><firstterm>checkout</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>The process of obtaining a copy of the project from
  a repository.  A checkout usually produces a directory tree called a
  "working copy" (see below), from which changes may be committed back
  to the original repository.  In some decentralized version control
  systems, each working copy is itself a repository, and changes can
  be pushed out to (or pulled into) any repository that's willing
  to accept them.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-working-copy">
  <term><firstterm>working copy</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>A developer's private directory tree containing the
  project's source code files, and possibly its web pages or other
  documents.  A working copy also contains a little bit of metadata
  managed by the version control system, telling the working copy what
  repository it comes from, what "revisions" (see below) of the files
  are present, etc.  Generally, each developer has his own working
  copy, in which he makes and tests changes, and from which he
  commits.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-revision">
  <term><firstterm>revision</firstterm>,
        <firstterm>change</firstterm>,
        <firstterm>changeset</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>A "revision" is usually one specific incarnation of
  a particular file or directory.  For example, if the project starts
  out with revision 6 of file F, and then someone commits a change to
  F, this produces revision 7 of F.  Some systems also use
  "revision", "change", or "changeset" to refer to a set of changes
  committed together as one conceptual unit.</para> 

  <para>These terms occasionally have distinct technical meanings in
  different version control systems, but the general idea is always
  the same: they give a way to speak precisely about exact points in
  time in the history of a file or a set of files (say, immediately
  before and after a bug is fixed).  For example: "Oh yes, she fixed
  that in revision 10" or "She fixed that in revision 10 of
  foo.c."</para>

  <para>When one talks about a file or collection of files without
  specifying a particular revision, it is generally assumed that one
  means the most recent revision(s) available.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

  <sidebar id="version-vs-revision">
  <title>"Version" Versus "Revision"</title>
  <para>The word <firstterm>version</firstterm> is sometimes used as a
  synonym for "revision", but I will not use it that way in this
  book, because it is too easily confused with "version" in the sense
  of a version of a piece of software&mdash;that is, the release or
  edition number, as in "Version 1.0".  However, since the phrase
  "version control" is already standard, I will continue to use it as
  a synonym for "revision control" and "change control".</para>
  </sidebar>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-diff">
  <term><firstterm>diff</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>A textual representation of a change.  A diff shows
  which lines were changed and how, plus a few lines of surrounding
  context on either side.  A developer who is already familiar with
  some code can usually read a diff against that code and understand
  what the change did, and even spot bugs.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-tag">
  <term><firstterm>tag</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>A label for a particular collection of files at
  specified revisions.  Tags are usually used to preserve
  interesting snapshots of the project.  For example, a tag is usually
  made for each public release, so that one can obtain, directly from
  the version control system, the exact set of files/revisions
  comprising that release.  Common tag names are things like
  <literal>Release_1_0</literal>, <literal>Delivery_00456</literal>,
  etc.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-branch">
  <term><firstterm>branch</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>A copy of the project, under version control but
  isolated, so that changes made to the branch don't affect the rest
  of the project, and vice versa, except when changes are
  deliberately "merged" from one side to the other (see below).
  Branches are also known as "lines of development".  Even when a
  project has no explicit branches, development is still considered
  to be happening on the "main branch", also known as the "main line"
  or "<firstterm>trunk</firstterm>".</para>

  <para>Branches offer a way to isolate different lines of development
  from each other.  For example, a branch can be used for experimental
  development that would be too destabilizing for the main trunk.  Or
  conversely, a branch can be used as a place to stabilize a new
  release.  During the release process, regular development would
  continue uninterrupted in the main branch of the repository;
  meanwhile, on the release branch, no changes are allowed except
  those approved by the release managers.  This way, making a release
  needn't interfere with ongoing development work.  See <xref
  linkend="branches"/><phrase output="printed"> later in this
  chapter</phrase> for a more detailed discussion of
  branching.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-merge">
  <term><firstterm>merge (a.k.a. port)</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>To move a change from one branch to another.  This
  includes merging from the main trunk to some other branch, or vice
  versa.  In fact, those are the most common kinds of merges; it is
  rare to port a change between two non-main branches.  See <xref
  linkend="vc-singularity"/> for more about this kind of
  merging.</para>

  <para>"Merge" has a second, related meaning: it is what the version
  control system does when it sees that two people have changed the
  same file but in non-overlapping ways.  Since the two changes do not
  interfere with each other, when one of the people updates their copy
  of the file (already containing their own changes), the other
  person's changes will be automatically merged in.  This is very
  common, especially on projects where multiple people are hacking on
  the same code.  When two different changes <emphasis>do</emphasis>
  overlap, the result is a "conflict"; see below.</para>
  </listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-conflict">
  <term><firstterm>conflict</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>What happens when two people try to make different
  changes to the same place in the code.  All version control systems
  automatically detect conflicts, and notify at least one of the
  humans involved that their changes conflict with someone else's.  It
  is then up to that human to <firstterm>resolve</firstterm> the
  conflict, and to communicate that resolution to the version control
  system.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-lock">
  <term><firstterm>lock</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>A way to declare an exclusive intent to change a
  particular file or directory.  For example, "I can't commit any
  changes to the web pages right now.  It seems Alfred has them all
  locked while he fixes their background images."  Not all version
  control systems even offer the ability to lock, and of those that
  do, not all require the locking feature to be used.  This is because
  parallel, simultaneous development is the norm, and locking people
  out of files is (usually) contrary to this ideal.</para>

  <para>Version control systems that require locking to make commits
  are said to use the <firstterm>lock-modify-unlock</firstterm> model.
  Those that do not are said to use the
  <firstterm>copy-modify-merge</firstterm> model.  An excellent
  in-depth explanation and comparison of the two models may be found
  at <ulink
  url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/svnbook-1.0/ch02s02.html"/>.  In
  general, the copy-modify-merge model is better for open source
  development, and all the version control systems discussed in this
  book support that model.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</para>

</sect2>


<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-choosing">
<title>Choosing a Version Control System</title>

<para>As of this writing, the two most popular version control systems
in the free software world are <firstterm>Concurrent Versions
System</firstterm> (<firstterm>CVS</firstterm>,
<ulink url="http://www.cvshome.org/"/>)
and <firstterm>Subversion</firstterm> (<firstterm>SVN</firstterm>,
<ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org/"/>).</para>

<para>CVS has been around for a long time.  Most experienced
developers are already familiar with it, it does more or less what you
need, and since it's been popular for a long time, you probably won't
end up in any long debates about whether or not it was the right
choice.  CVS has some disadvantages, however.  It doesn't provide an
easy way to refer to multi-file changes; it doesn't allow you to
rename or copy files under version control (so if you need to
reorganize your code tree after starting the project, it can be a real
pain); it has poor merging support; it doesn't handle large files or
binary files very well; and some operations are slow when large
numbers of files are involved.</para>

<para>None of CVS's flaws is fatal, and it is still quite popular.
However, in the last few years the more recent Subversion has been
gaining ground, especially in newer
projects.<footnote><para>See <ulink url="http://cia.vc/stats/vcs"/> and
<ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org/svn-dav-securityspace-survey.html"/>
for evidence of this growth.</para></footnote>.  If you're starting a
new project, I recommend Subversion.</para>

<para>On the other hand, since I'm involved in the Subversion project,
my objectivity might reasonably be questioned.  And in the last few
years a number of new open-source version control systems have
appeared.  <xref linkend="vc-systems"/> lists all the ones I know of,
in rough order of popularity.  As the list makes clear, deciding on a
version control system could easily become a lifelong research
project.  Possibly you will be spared the decision because it will be
made for you by your hosting site.  But if you must choose, consult
with your other developers, ask around to see what people have
experience with, then pick one and run with it.  Any stable,
production-ready version control system will do; you don't have to
worry too much about making a drastically wrong decision.  If you
simply can't make up your mind, then go with Subversion.  It's fairly
easy to learn, and is likely to remain a standard for at least a few
years.</para>

</sect2>


<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-using">
<title>Using the Version Control System</title>

<para>The recommendations in this section are not targeted toward a
particular version control system, and should be simple to implement
in any of them.  Consult your specific system's documentation for
details.</para>

<sect3 id="version-everything">
<title>Version everything</title>

<para>Keep not only your project's source code under version control,
but also its web pages, documentation, FAQ, design notes, and anything
else that people might want to edit.  Keep them right next to the
source code, in the same repository tree.  Any piece of information
worth writing down is worth versioning&mdash;that is, any piece of
information that could change.  Things that don't change should be
archived, not versioned.  For example, an email, once posted, does not
change; therefore, versioning it wouldn't make sense (unless it becomes
part of some larger, evolving document).</para>

<para>The reason versioning everything together in one place is
important is so people only have to learn one mechanism for submitting
changes.  Often a contributor will start out making edits to the web
pages or documentation, and move to small code contributions later,
for example.  When the project uses the same system for all kinds of
submissions, people only have to learn the ropes once.  Versioning
everything together also means that new features can be committed
together with their documentation updates, that branching the code
will branch the documentation too, etc.</para>

<para>Don't keep <firstterm>generated files</firstterm> under version
control.  They are not truly editable data, since they are produced
programmatically from other files.  For example, some build systems
create <filename>configure</filename> based on the template
<filename>configure.in</filename>.  To make a change to the
<filename>configure</filename>, one would edit
<filename>configure.in</filename> and then regenerate; thus, only the
template <filename>configure.in</filename> is an "editable file."
Just version the templates&mdash;if you version the result files as
well, people will inevitably forget to regenerate when they commit a
change to a template, and the resulting inconsistencies will cause no
end of confusion.<footnote><para>For a different opinion on the
question of versioning <filename>configure</filename> files, see
Alexey Makhotkin's post "<citetitle>configure.in and version
control</citetitle>" at
<ulink url="http://versioncontrolblog.com/2007/01/08/configurein-and-version-control/"/>.</para></footnote></para>

<para>The rule that all editable data should be kept under version
control has one unfortunate exception: the bug tracker.  Bug databases
hold plenty of editable data, but for technical reasons generally
cannot store that data in the main version control system.  (Some
trackers have primitive versioning features of their own, however,
independent of the project's main repository.)</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="vc-browsing">
<title>Browsability</title>

<para>The project's repository should be browsable on the Web.  This
means not only the ability to see the latest revisions of the
project's files, but to go back in time and look at earlier revisions,
view the differences between revisions, read log messages for selected
changes, etc.</para>

<para>Browsability is important because it is a lightweight portal to
project data.  If the repository cannot be viewed through a web
browser, then someone wanting to inspect a particular file (say, to
see if a certain bugfix had made it into the code) would first have to
install version control client software locally, which could turn
their simple query from a two-minute task into a half-hour or longer
task.</para>

<para>Browsability also implies canonical URLs for viewing specific
revisions of files, and for viewing the latest revision at any given
time.  This can be very useful in technical discussions or when
pointing people to documentation.  For example, instead of saying "For
tips on debugging the server, see the www/hacking.html file in your
working copy," one can say "For tips on debugging the server, see
<emphasis>http://subversion.apache.org/docs/community-guide/</emphasis>,"
giving a URL that always points to the latest revision of
the <filename>hacking.html</filename> file.  The URL is better because
it is completely unambiguous, and avoids the question of whether the
addressee has an up-to-date working copy.</para>

<para>Some version control systems come with built-in
repository-browsing mechanisms, while others rely on third-party tools
to do it.  Three such tools are <firstterm>ViewCVS</firstterm> (<ulink
url="http://viewcvs.sourceforge.net/"/>),
<firstterm>CVSWeb</firstterm> (<ulink
url="http://www.freebsd.org/projects/cvsweb.html"/>), and
<firstterm>WebSVN</firstterm> (<ulink
url="http://websvn.tigris.org/"/>).  The first works with both CVS and
Subversion, the second with CVS only, and the third with Subversion
only.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="commit-emails">
<title>Commit emails</title>

<para>Every commit to the repository should generate an email showing
who made the change, when they made it, what files and directories
changed, and how they changed.  The email should go to a special
mailing list devoted to commit emails, separate from the mailing lists
to which humans post.  Developers and other interested parties should
be encouraged to subscribe to the commits list, as it is the most
effective way to keep up with what's happening in the project at the
code level.  Aside from the obvious technical benefits of peer review
(see <xref linkend="code-review"/>), commit emails help create a
sense of community, because they establish a shared environment in
which people can react to events (commits) that they know are visible
to others as well.</para>

<para>The specifics of setting up commit emails will vary depending on
your version control system, but usually there's a script or other
packaged facility for doing it.  If you're having trouble finding it,
try looking for documentation on <firstterm>hooks</firstterm>,
specifically a <firstterm>post-commit hook</firstterm>, also called
the <firstterm>loginfo hook</firstterm> in CVS.  Post-commit hooks are
a general means of launching automated tasks in response to commits.
The hook is triggered by an individual commit, is fed all the
information about that commit, and is then free to use that
information to do anything&mdash;for example, to send out an
email.</para>

<para>With pre-packaged commit email systems, you may want to
modify some of the default behaviors:</para>

<orderedlist>

  <listitem>
  <para>Some commit mailers don't include the actual diffs in the
  email, but instead provide a URL to view the change on the web using
  the repository browsing system.  While it's good to provide the URL,
  so the change can be referred to later, it is also
  <emphasis>very</emphasis> important that the commit email include
  the diffs themselves.  Reading email is already part of people's
  routine, so if the content of the change is visible right there in
  the commit email, developers will review the commit on the spot,
  without leaving their mail reader.  If they have to click on a URL to
  review the change, most won't do it, because that requires a new
  action instead of a continuation of what they were already doing.
  Furthermore, if the reviewer wants to ask something about the
  change, it's vastly easier to hit reply-with-text and simply
  annotate the quoted diff than it is to visit a web page and
  laboriously cut-and-paste parts of the diff from web browser to
  email client.</para>

  <para>(Of course, if the diff is huge, such as when a large body of
  new code has been added to the repository, then it makes sense to
  omit the diff and offer only the URL.  Most commit mailers can do
  this kind of limiting automatically.  If yours can't, then it's
  still better to include diffs, and live with the occasional huge
  email, than to leave the diffs off entirely.  Convenient reviewing
  and commenting is a cornerstone of cooperative development, much
  too important to do without.)</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>The commit emails should set their Reply-to header
  to the regular development list, not the commit email list.  That
  is, when someone reviews a commit and writes a response, their
  response should be automatically directed toward the human
  development list, where technical issues are normally discussed.
  There are a few reasons for this.  First, you want to keep all
  technical discussion on one list, because that's where people expect
  it to happen, and because that way there's only one archive to
  search.  Second, there might be interested parties not subscribed to
  the commit email list.  Third, the commit email list advertises
  itself as a service for watching commits, not for watching commits
  <emphasis>and</emphasis> occasional technical discussions.  Those who
  subscribed to the commit email list did not sign up for anything but
  commit emails; sending them other material via that list would
  violate an implicit contract.  Fourth, people often write programs
  that read the commit email list and process the results (for
  display on a web page, for example).  Those programs are prepared to
  handle consistently-formatted commit emails, but not inconsistent
  human-written mails.</para>

  <para>Note that this advice to set Reply-to does not contradict the
  recommendations in
  <xref linkend="reply-to"/><phrase output="printed"> earlier in
  this chapter</phrase>.  It's
  always okay for the <emphasis>sender</emphasis> of a message to set
  Reply-to.  In this case, the sender is the version control system
  itself, and it sets Reply-to in order to indicate that the
  appropriate place for replies is the development mailing list, not
  the commit list.</para>

  </listitem>

</orderedlist>

<sidebar id="cia">
<title>CIA: Another Change Publication Mechanism</title>

<para>Commit emails are not the only way to propagate change news.
Recently, another mechanism called CIA (<ulink
url="http://cia.navi.cx/"/>) has been developed.  CIA is a real-time
commit statistics aggregator and distributor.  The most popular use of
CIA is to send commit notifications to IRC channels, so that people
logged into those channels see the commits happening in real time.
Though of somewhat less technical utility than commit emails, since
observers might or might not be around when a commit notice pops up in
IRC, this technique is of immense <emphasis>social</emphasis> utility.
People get the sense of being part of something alive and active, and
feel that they can see progress being made right before their
eyes.</para>

<para>The way it works is that you invoke the CIA notifier program
from your post-commit hook.  The notifier formats the commit
information into an XML message, and sends to a central server
(typically <literal>cia.navi.cx</literal>).  That server then
distributes the commit information to other forums.</para>

<para>CIA can also be configured to send out <ulink
url="http://www.xml.com/pub/a/2002/12/18/dive-into-xml.html">RSS</ulink>
feeds.  See the documentation at <ulink url="http://cia.navi.cx/"/>
for details.</para>

<para>To see an example of CIA in action, point your IRC
client at <literal>irc.freenode.net</literal>, channel
<literal>#commits</literal>.</para>

</sidebar>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="branches">
<title>Use branches to avoid bottlenecks</title>

<para>Non-expert version control users are sometimes a bit afraid of
branching and merging.  This is probably a side effect of CVS's
popularity: CVS's interface for branching and merging is somewhat
counterintuitive, so many people have learned to avoid those
operations entirely.</para>

<para>If you are among those people, resolve right now to conquer any
fears you may have and take the time to learn how to do branching and
merging.  They are not difficult operations, once you get used to
them, and they become increasingly important as a project acquires
more developers.</para>

<para>Branches are valuable because they turn a scarce
resource&mdash;working room in the project's code&mdash;into an
abundant one.  Normally, all developers work together in the same
sandbox, constructing the same castle.  When someone wants to add a
new drawbridge, but can't convince everyone else that it would be an
improvement, branching makes it possible for her to go to an isolated
corner and try it out.  If the effort succeeds, she can invite the
other developers to examine the result.  If everyone agrees that the
result is good, they can tell the version control system to move
("merge") the drawbridge from the branch castle over to the main
castle.</para>

<para>It's easy to see how this ability helps collaborative
development.  People need the freedom to try new things without
feeling like they're interfering with others' work.  Equally
importantly, there are times when code needs to be isolated from the
usual development churn, in order to get a bug fixed or a release
stabilized (see <xref linkend="stabilizing-a-release"/> and
<xref linkend="release-lines"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="development-cycle"/></phrase>) without worrying
about tracking a moving target.</para>

<para>Use branches liberally, and encourage others to use them.  But
also make sure that a given branch is only active for exactly as long
as needed.  Every active branch is a slight drain on the community's
attention.  Even those who are not working in a branch still maintain
a peripheral awareness of what's going on in it.  Such awareness is
desirable, of course, and commit emails should be sent out for branch
commits just as for any other commit.  But branches should not become
a mechanism for dividing the development community.  With rare
exceptions, the eventual goal of most branches should be to merge
their changes back into the main line and disappear.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="vc-singularity">
<title>Singularity of information</title>

<para>Merging has an important corollary: never commit the same change
twice.  That is, a given change should enter the version control
system exactly once.  The revision (or set of revisions) in which the
change entered is its unique identifier from then on.  If it needs to
be applied to branches other than the one on which it entered, then it
should be merged from its original entry point to those other
destinations&mdash;as opposed to committing a textually identical
change, which would have the same effect in the code, but would make
accurate bookkeeping and release management impossible.</para>

<para>The practical effects of this advice differ from one version
control system to another.  In some systems, merges are special
events, fundamentally distinct from commits, and carry their own
metadata with them.  In others, the results of merges are committed
the same way other changes are committed, so the primary means of
distinguishing a "merge commit" from a "new change commit" is in the
log message.  In a merge's log message, don't repeat the log message
of the original change.  Instead, just indicate that this is a merge,
and give the identifying revision of the original change, with at most
a one-sentence summary of its effect.  If someone wants to see the
full log message, she should consult the original revision.</para>

<para>The reason it's important to avoid repeating the log message is
that log messages are sometimes edited after they've been committed.
If a change's log message were repeated at each merge destination,
then even if someone edited the original message, she'd still leave
all the repeats uncorrected&mdash;which would only cause confusion
down the road.</para>

<para>The same principle applies to reverting a change.  If a change
is withdrawn from the code, then the log message for the reversion
should merely state that some specific revision(s) is being reverted,
<emphasis>not</emphasis> describe the actual code change that results
from the reversion, since the semantics of the change can be derived
by reading the original log message and change.  Of course, the
reversion's log message should also state the reason why the change is
being reverted, but it should not duplicate anything from the original
change's log message.  If possible, go back and edit the original
change's log message to point out that it was reverted.</para>

<para>All of the above implies that you should use a consistent syntax
for referring to revisions.  This is helpful not only in log messages,
but in emails, the bug tracker, and elsewhere.  If you're using
CVS, I suggest "<literal>path/to/file/in/project/tree:REV</literal>",
where REV is a CVS revision number such as "1.76".  If you're using
Subversion, the standard syntax for revision 1729 is "r1729" (file
paths are not needed because Subversion uses global revision numbers).
In other systems, there is usually a standard syntax for expressing
the changeset name.  Whatever the appropriate syntax is for your
system, encourage people to use it when referring to changes.
Consistent expression of change names makes project bookkeeping much
easier (as we will see in <xref linkend="communications"/> and
<xref linkend="development-cycle"/>), and since a lot of the
bookkeeping will be done by volunteers, it needs to be as easy as
possible.</para>

<para>See also
<xref
linkend="releases-and-daily-development"/><phrase
output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="development-cycle"/></phrase>.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="vc-authz">
<title>Authorization</title>

<para>Most version control systems offer a feature whereby certain
people can be allowed or disallowed from committing in specific
sub-areas of the repository.  Following the principle that when handed
a hammer, people start looking around for nails, many projects use
this feature with abandon, carefully granting people access to just
those areas where they have been approved to commit, and making sure
they can't commit anywhere else.  (See
<xref linkend="committers"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="managing-volunteers"/></phrase> for how projects
decide who can commit where.)</para>

<para>There is probably little harm done by exercising such tight
control, but a more relaxed policy is fine too.  Some projects simply
use an honor system: when a person is granted commit access, even for
a sub-area of the repository, what they actually receive is a password
that allows them to commit anywhere in the project.  They're just
asked to keep their commits in their area.  Remember that there is no
real risk here: in an active project, all commits are reviewed anyway.
If someone commits where they're not supposed to, others will
notice it and say something.  If a change needs to be undone, that's
simple enough&mdash;everything's under version control anyway, so
just revert.</para>

<para>There are several advantages to the relaxed approach.  First, as
developers expand into other areas (which they usually will if they
stay with the project), there is no administrative overhead to
granting them wider privileges.  Once the decision is made, the person
can just start committing in the new area right away.</para>

<para>Second, expansion can be done in a more fine-grained manner.
Generally, a committer in area X who wants to expand to area Y will
start posting patches against Y and asking for review.  If someone who
already has commit access to area Y sees such a patch and approves of
it, they can just tell the submitter to commit the change directly
(mentioning the reviewer/approver's name in the log message, of
course).  That way, the commit will come from the person who actually
wrote the change, which is preferable from both an information
management standpoint and from a crediting standpoint.</para>

<para>Last, and perhaps most important, using the honor system
encourages an atmosphere of trust and mutual respect.  Giving someone
commit access to a subdomain is a statement about their technical
preparedness&mdash;it says: "We see you have expertise to make commits
in a certain domain, so go for it."  But imposing strict authorization
controls says: "Not only are we asserting a limit on your expertise,
we're also a bit suspicious about
your <emphasis>intentions</emphasis>."  That's not the sort of
statement you want to make if you can avoid it.  Bringing someone into
the project as a committer is an opportunity to initiate them into a
circle of mutual trust.  A good way to do that is to give them more
power than they're supposed to use, then inform them that it's up to
them to stay within the stated limits.</para>

<para>The Subversion project has operated on the honor system way for
more than four years, with 33 full and 43 partial committers as of
this writing.  The only distinction the system actually enforces is
between committers and non-committers; further subdivisions are
maintained solely by humans.  Yet we've never had a problem with
someone deliberately committing outside their domain.  Once or twice
there's been an innocent misunderstanding about the extent of
someone's commit privileges, but it's always been resolved quickly and
amiably.</para>

<para>Obviously, in situations where self-policing is impractical, you
must rely on hard authorization controls.  But such situations are
rare.  Even when there are millions of lines of code and hundreds or
thousands of developers, a commit to any given code module should
still be reviewed by those who work on that module, and they can
recognize if someone committed there who wasn't supposed to.  If
regular commit review <emphasis>isn't</emphasis> happening, then the
project has bigger problems to deal with than the authorization system
anyway.</para>

<para>In summary, don't spend too much time fiddling with the version
control authorization system, unless you have a specific reason to.  It
usually won't bring much tangible benefit, and there are advantages to
relying on human controls instead.</para>

<para>None of this should be taken to mean that the restrictions
themselves are unimportant, of course.  It would be bad for a project
to encourage people to commit in areas where they're not qualified.
Furthermore, in many projects, full (unrestricted) commit access has a
special status: it implies voting rights on project-wide questions.
This political aspect of commit access is discussed more in <xref
linkend="electorate"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="social-infrastructure"/></phrase>.</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1>


<!-- ========================== SECTION =========================== -->
<sect1 id="bug-tracker">
<title>Bug Tracker</title>

<para>Bug tracking is a broad topic; various aspects of it are
discussed throughout this book.  Here I'll try to concentrate mainly
on setup and technical considerations, but to get to those, we have to
start with a policy question: exactly what kind of information should
be kept in a bug tracker?</para>

<para>The term <firstterm>bug tracker</firstterm> is misleading.  Bug
tracking systems are also frequently used to track new feature
requests, one-time tasks, unsolicited patches&mdash;really anything
that has distinct beginning and end states, with optional transition
states in between, and that accrues information over its lifetime.
For this reason, bug trackers are also called <firstterm>issue
trackers</firstterm>, <firstterm>defect trackers</firstterm>,
<firstterm>artifact trackers</firstterm>, <firstterm>request
trackers</firstterm>, <firstterm>trouble ticket systems</firstterm>,
etc.  See <xref linkend="bug-trackers"/> for a list of software.
</para>

<para>In this book, I'll continue to use "bug tracker" for the
software that does the tracking, because that's what most people call
it, but will use <firstterm>issue</firstterm> to refer to a single
item in the bug tracker's database.  This allows us to distinguish
between the behavior or misbehavior that the user encountered (that is,
the bug itself), and the tracker's <emphasis>record</emphasis> of the
bug's discovery, diagnosis, and eventual resolution.  Keep in mind
that although most issues are about actual bugs, issues can be used to
track other kinds of tasks too.</para>

<para>The classic issue life cycle looks like this:

<orderedlist>
  <listitem><para>Someone files the issue.  They provide a summary, an
            initial description (including a reproduction recipe, if
            applicable; see
            <xref
            linkend="users-to-volunteers"/><phrase
            output="printed"> in
            <xref linkend="managing-volunteers"/></phrase> for
            how to encourage good bug reports), and whatever other
            information the tracker asks for.  The person who files
            the issue may be totally unknown to the project&mdash;bug
            reports and feature requests are as likely to come from
            the user community as from the developers.</para>

            <para>Once filed, the issue is in what's called an
            <firstterm>open</firstterm> state.  Because no action has
            been taken yet, some trackers also label it as
            <firstterm>unverified</firstterm> and/or
            <firstterm>unstarted</firstterm>.  It is not assigned to
            anyone; or, in some systems, it is assigned to a fake
            user to represent the lack of real assignation.  At this
            point, it is in a holding area: the issue has been
            recorded, but not yet integrated into the project's
            consciousness.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>Others read the issue, add comments to it, and
            perhaps ask the original filer for clarification on some
            points.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>The bug gets <firstterm>reproduced</firstterm>.
            This may be the most important moment in its
            life cycle.  Although the bug is not actually fixed yet,
            the fact that someone besides the original filer was able
            to make it happen proves that it is genuine, and, no less
            importantly, confirms to the original filer that they've
            contributed to the project by reporting a real bug.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>The bug gets <firstterm>diagnosed</firstterm>: its
            cause is identified, and if possible, the effort required
            to fix it is estimated.  Make sure these things get
            recorded in the issue; if the person who diagnosed the
            bug suddenly has to step away from the project for a
            while (as can often happen with volunteer developers),
            someone else should be able to pick up where she left
            off.</para>

            <para>In this stage, or sometimes the previous one, a
            developer may "take ownership" of the issue and
            <firstterm>assign</firstterm> it to herself (<xref
            linkend="delegation-assignment"/><phrase
            output="printed"> in
            <xref linkend="managing-volunteers"/></phrase>
            examines the assignment process in more detail).  The issue's
            <firstterm>priority</firstterm> may also be set at this
            stage.  For example, if it is so severe that it should
            delay the next release, that fact needs to be identified
            early, and the tracker should have some way of noting
            it.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>The issue gets scheduled for resolution.
            Scheduling doesn't necessarily mean naming a date by which
            it will be fixed.  Sometimes it just means deciding which
            future release (not necessarily the next one) the bug
            should be fixed by, or deciding that it need not block any
            particular release.  Scheduling may also be dispensed
            with, if the bug is quick to fix.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>The bug gets fixed (or the task completed, or
            the patch applied, or whatever).  The change or set of
            changes that fixed it should be recorded in a comment in
            the issue, after which the issue is
            <firstterm>closed</firstterm> and/or marked as
            <firstterm>resolved</firstterm>.</para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>

</para>

<para>There are some common variations on this life cycle.  Sometimes
an issue is closed very soon after being filed, because it turns out
not to be a bug at all, but rather a misunderstanding on the part of
the user.  As a project acquires more users, more and more such
invalid issues will come in, and developers will close them with
increasingly short-tempered responses.  Try to guard against the
latter tendency.  It does no one any good, as the individual user in
each case is not responsible for all the previous invalid issues; the
statistical trend is visible only from the developers' point of view,
not the user's.  (In
<xref linkend="bug-filtering"/><phrase output="printed"> later
in this chapter,</phrase> we'll look at
techniques for reducing the number of invalid issues.)  Also, if
different users are experiencing the same misunderstanding over and
over, it might mean that that aspect of the software needs to be
redesigned.  This sort of pattern is easiest to notice when there is
an issue manager monitoring the bug database; see
<xref linkend="issue-manager"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="managing-volunteers"/></phrase>.</para>

<para>Another common life cycle variation is for the issue to be closed
as a <firstterm>duplicate</firstterm> soon after Step 1.  A duplicate
is when someone files an issue that's already known to the project.
Duplicates are not confined to open issues: it's possible for a bug to
come back after having been fixed (this is known as a
<firstterm>regression</firstterm>), in which case the preferred course
is usually to reopen the original issue and close any new reports as
duplicates of the original one.  The bug tracking system should keep
track of this relationship bidirectionally, so that reproduction
information in the duplicates is available to the original issue, and
vice versa.</para>

<para>A third variation is for the developers to close the issue,
thinking they have fixed it, only to have the original reporter reject
the fix and reopen it.  This is usually because the developers simply
don't have access to the environment necessary to reproduce the bug,
or because they didn't test the fix using the exact same reproduction
recipe as the reporter.</para>

<para>Aside from these variations, there may be other small details of
the life cycle that vary depending on the tracking software.  But the
basic shape is the same, and while the life cycle itself is not
specific to open source software, it has implications for how open
source projects use their bug trackers.</para>

<para>As Step 1 implies, the tracker is as much a public face of the
project as the mailing lists or web pages.  Anyone may file an issue,
anyone may look at an issue, and anyone may browse the list of currently
open issues.  It follows that you never know how many people are
waiting to see progress on a given issue.  While the size and skill of
the development community constrains the rate at which issues can be
resolved, the project should at least try to acknowledge each issue the
moment it appears.  Even if the issue lingers for a while, a response
encourages the reporter to stay involved, because she feels that a
human has registered what she has done (remember that filing an
issue usually involves more effort than, say, posting an email).
Furthermore, once an issue is seen by a developer, it enters the
project's consciousness, in the sense that that developer can be on
the lookout for other instances of the issue, can talk about it with
other developers, etc.</para>

<para>The need for timely reactions implies two things:

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>The tracker must be connected to a mailing list, such that
    every change to an issue, including its initial filing, causes a
    mail to go out describing what happened.  This mailing list
    is usually different from the regular development list, since not
    all developers may want to receive automated bug mails, but (just
    as with commit mails) the Reply-to header should be set to the
    development mailing list.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>The form for filing issues should capture the reporter's
    email address, so she can be contacted for more information.
    (However, it should not <emphasis>require</emphasis> the
    reporter's email address, as some people prefer to report issues
    anonymously.  See
    <xref linkend="anonymity"/><phrase output="printed"> later
    in this chapter</phrase> for more on the importance of
    anonymity.)</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</para>

<sect2 id="bug-tracker-mailing-list-interaction">
<title>Interaction with Mailing Lists</title>

<para>Make sure the bug tracker doesn't turn into a discussion forum.
Although it is important to maintain a human presence in the bug
tracker, it is not fundamentally suited to real-time discussion.
Think of it rather as an archiver, a way to organize facts and
references to other discussions, primarily those that take place on
mailing lists.</para>

<para>There are two reasons to make this distinction.  First, the bug
tracker is more cumbersome to use than the mailing lists (or than
real-time chat forums, for that matter).  This is not because bug
trackers have bad user interface design, it's just that their
interfaces were designed for capturing and presenting discrete states,
not free-flowing discussions.  Second, not everyone who should be
involved in discussing a given issue is necessarily watching the bug
tracker.  Part of good issue management (see
<xref linkend="share-management"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="managing-volunteers"/></phrase>) is to make sure
each issue is brought to the right peoples' attention, rather than
requiring every developer to monitor all issues.  In
<xref linkend="bug-tracker-usage"/><phrase output="printed"> in <xref linkend="communications"/>,</phrase> we'll look at ways to make
sure people don't accidentally siphon discussions out of appropriate
forums and into the bug tracker.</para>

<para>Some bug trackers can monitor mailing lists and automatically
log all emails that are about a known issue.  Typically they do this
by recognizing the issue's identifying number in the subject line of
the mail, as part of a special string; developers learn to include
these strings in their mails to attract the tracker's notice.  The bug
tracker may either save the entire email, or (even better) just record
a link to the mail in the regular mailing list archive.  Either way,
this is a very useful feature; if your tracker has it, make sure
both to turn it on and to remind people to take advantage of
it.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="bug-filtering">
<title>Pre-Filtering the Bug Tracker</title>

<para>Most issue databases eventually suffer from the same problem: a
crushing load of duplicate or invalid issues filed by well-meaning but
inexperienced or ill-informed users.  The first step in combatting
this trend is usually to put a prominent notice on the front page of
the bug tracker, explaining how to tell if a bug is really a bug, how
to search to see if it's already been filed, and finally, how to
effectively report it if one still thinks it's a new bug.</para>

<para>This will reduce the noise level for a while, but as the number
of users increases, the problem will eventually come back.  No
individual user can be blamed for it.  Each one is just trying to
contribute to the project's well-being, and even if their first bug
report isn't helpful, you still want to encourage them to stay
involved and file better issues in the future.  In the meantime,
though, the project needs to keep the issue database as free of junk
as possible.</para>

<para>The two things that will do the most to prevent this problem
are: making sure there are people watching the bug tracker who have
enough knowledge to close issues as invalid or duplicates the moment
they come in, and requiring (or strongly encouraging) users to confirm
their bugs with other people before filing them in the tracker.</para>

<para>The first technique seems to be used universally.  Even projects
with huge issue databases (say, the Debian bug tracker at
<ulink url="http://bugs.debian.org/"/>, which contained 315,929 issues
as of this writing) still arrange things so that
<emphasis>someone</emphasis> sees each issue that comes in.  It may be
a different person depending on the category of the issue.  For
example, the Debian project is a collection of software packages, so
Debian automatically routes each issue to the appropriate package
maintainers.  Of course, users can sometimes misidentify an issue's
category, with the result that the issue is sent to the wrong person
initially, who may then have to reroute it.  However, the important
thing is that the burden is still shared&mdash;whether the user
guesses right or wrong when filing, issue watching is still
distributed more or less evenly among the developers, so each issue is
able to receive a timely response.</para>

<para>The second technique is less widespread, probably because it's
harder to automate.  The essential idea is that every new issue gets
"buddied" into the database.  When a user thinks he's found a problem,
he is asked to describe it on one of the mailing lists, or in an IRC
channel, and get confirmation from someone that it is indeed a bug.
Bringing in that second pair of eyes early can prevent a lot of
spurious reports.  Sometimes the second party is able to identify that
the behavior is not a bug, or is fixed in recent releases.  Or she may
be familiar with the symptoms from a previous issue, and can prevent a
duplicate filing by pointing the user to the older issue.  Often it's
enough just to ask the user "Did you search the bug tracker to see if
it's already been reported?"  Many people simply don't think of that,
yet are happy to do the search once they know someone's
<emphasis>expecting</emphasis> them to.</para>

<para>The buddy system can really keep the issue database clean, but
it has some disadvantages too.  Many people will file solo anyway,
either through not seeing, or through disregarding, the instructions
to find a buddy for new issues.  Thus it is still necessary for
volunteers to watch the issue database.  Furthermore, because most new
reporters don't understand how difficult the task of maintaining the
issue database is, it's not fair to chide them too harshly for
ignoring the guidelines.  Thus the volunteers must be vigilant, and
yet exercise restraint in how they bounce unbuddied issues back to
their reporters.  The goal is to train each reporter to use the
buddying system in the future, so that there is an ever-growing pool
of people who understand the issue-filtering system.  On seeing an
unbuddied issue, the ideal steps are:</para>

<orderedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>Immediately respond to the issue, politely thanking the user
          for filing, but pointing them to the buddying guidelines
          (which should, of course, be prominently posted on the web
          site).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>If the issue is clearly valid and not a duplicate, approve it
          anyway, and start it down the normal life cycle.  After all,
          the reporter's now been informed about buddying, so there's
          no point wasting the work done so far by closing a valid
          issue.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Otherwise, if the issue is not clearly valid, close it, but
          ask the reporter to reopen it if they get confirmation from
          a buddy.   When they do, they should put a reference to the
          confirmation thread (e.g., a URL into the mailing list
          archives).</para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>Remember that although this system will improve the signal/noise
ratio in the issue database over time, it will never completely stop
the misfilings.  The only way to prevent misfilings entirely is to
close off the bug tracker to everyone but developers&mdash;a cure that
is almost always worse than the disease.  It's better to accept that
cleaning out invalid issues will always be part of the project's
routine maintenance, and to try to get as many people as possible to
help.</para>

<para>See also
<xref linkend="issue-manager"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="managing-volunteers"/></phrase>.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ========================== SECTION =========================== -->
<sect1 id="irc">
<title>IRC / Real-Time Chat Systems</title>

<para>Many projects offer real-time chat rooms using <firstterm>Internet
Relay Chat</firstterm> (<firstterm>IRC</firstterm>), forums where users
and developers can ask each other questions and get instant responses.
While you <emphasis>can</emphasis> run an IRC server from your own
web site, it is generally not worth the hassle.  Instead, do what
everyone else does: run your IRC channels at Freenode
(<ulink url="http://freenode.net/"/>).  Freenode gives you the control
you need to administer your project's IRC
channels,<footnote><para>There is no requirement or expectation that
you donate to Freenode, but if you or your project can afford it,
please consider a contribution.  They are a tax-exempt charity in the
U.S., and they perform a valuable service.</para></footnote> while
sparing you the not-insignificant trouble of maintaining an IRC server
yourself.</para>

<para>The first thing to do is choose a channel name.  The most
obvious choice is the name of your project&mdash;if that's available
at Freenode, then use it.  If not, try to choose something as close to
your project's name, and as easy to remember, as possible.  Advertise
the channel's availabity from your project's web site, so a visitor
with a quick question will see it right away.  For example, this
appears in a prominently placed box at the top of Subversion's home
page:</para>

  <blockquote>
    <para><emphasis>If you're using Subversion, we recommend that you
    join the</emphasis> <literal>users@subversion.tigris.org</literal>
    <emphasis>mailing list, and read the <ulink
    url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/">Subversion Book</ulink> and
    <ulink
    url="http://subversion.tigris.org/faq.html">FAQ</ulink>.
    You can also ask questions on IRC at</emphasis>
    <literal>irc.freenode.net</literal>
    <emphasis>channel</emphasis>&nbsp;<literal>#svn</literal>.</para>
  </blockquote>

<para>Some projects have multiple channels, one per subtopic.  For
example, one channel for installation problems, another for usage
questions, another for development chat, etc. (<xref
linkend="growth"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="communications"/></phrase> discusses and how to
divide into multiple channels).  When your project is young, there
should only be one channel, with everyone talking together.  Later, as
the user-to-developer ratio increases, separate channels may become
necessary.</para>

<para>How will people know all the available channels, let alone which
channel to talk in?  And when they talk, how will they know what the
local conventions are?</para>

<para>The answer is to tell them by setting the <firstterm>channel
topic</firstterm>.<footnote><para>To set a channel topic, use the
<literal>/topic</literal> command.  All commands in IRC start with
"<literal>/</literal>".  See <ulink url="http://www.irchelp.org/"/> if
you're not familiar with IRC usage and administration; in particular,
<ulink url="http://www.irchelp.org/irchelp/irctutorial.html"/> is an
excellent tutorial.</para></footnote>  The channel topic is a brief
message each user sees when they first enter the channel.  It gives
quick guidance to newcomers, and pointers to further information.  For
example:</para>

<screen>
You are now talking on #svn

Topic for #svn is Forum for Subversion user questions, see also
http://subversion.tigris.org/. || Development discussion happens in
#svn-dev. || Please don't paste long transcripts here, instead use
a pastebin site like http://pastebin.ca/. || NEWS: Subversion 1.1.0
is released, see http://svn110.notlong.com/ for details.
</screen>

<para>That's terse, but it tells newcomers what they need to know.  It
says exactly what the channel is for, gives the project home page (in
case someone wanders into the channel without having first been to the
project web site), mentions a related channel, and gives some guidance
about pasting.</para>

<sidebar id="paste-sites">
<title>Paste Sites</title>

<para>An IRC channel is a shared space: everyone can see what everyone
else is saying.  Normally, this is a good thing, as it allows people
to jump into a conversation when they think they have something to
contribute, and allows spectators to learn by watching.  But it
becomes problematic when someone has to provide a large quantity of
information at once, such as a debugging session transcript, because
pasting too many lines of output into the channel will disrupt other
conversations.</para>

<para>The solution is to use one of the
<firstterm>pastebin</firstterm> or <firstterm>pastebot</firstterm>
sites.  When requesting a large amount of data from someone, ask them
not to paste it into the channel, but instead to go to (for example)
<ulink url="http://pastebin.ca/"/>, paste their data into the form
there, and tell the resulting new URL to the IRC channel.  Anyone can
then visit the URL and view the data.</para>

<para>There are a number of free paste sites available now, too many
for a comprehensive list, but here are some of the ones I've seen used:
<ulink url="http://www.nomorepasting.com/"/>,
<ulink url="http://pastebin.ca/"/>,
<ulink url="http://nopaste.php.cd/"/>
<ulink url="http://rafb.net/paste/"/>
<ulink url="http://sourcepost.sytes.net/"/>,
<ulink url="http://extraball.sunsite.dk/notepad.php"/>,
and
<ulink url="http://www.pastebin.com/"/>.</para>

</sidebar>

<sect2 id="bots">
<title>Bots</title>

<para>Many technically-oriented IRC channels have a non-human member,
a so-called <firstterm>bot</firstterm>, that is capable of storing and
regurgitating information in response to specific commands.
Typically, the bot is addressed just like any other member of the
channel, that is, the commands are delivered by "speaking to" the bot.
For example:</para>

<screen>
&lt;kfogel&gt; ayita: learn diff-cmd = http://subversion.tigris.org/faq.html#diff-cmd
&lt;ayita&gt;  Thanks!
</screen>

<para>That told the bot (who is logged into the channel as ayita) to
remember a certain URL as the answer to the query "diff-cmd".  Now we
can address ayita, asking the bot to tell another user about
diff-cmd:</para>

<screen>
&lt;kfogel&gt; ayita: tell jrandom about diff-cmd
&lt;ayita&gt;  jrandom: http://subversion.tigris.org/faq.html#diff-cmd
</screen>

<para>The same thing can be accomplished via a convenient shorthand:</para>

<screen>
&lt;kfogel&gt; !a jrandom diff-cmd
&lt;ayita&gt;  jrandom: http://subversion.tigris.org/faq.html#diff-cmd
</screen>

<para>The exact command set and behaviors differ from bot to bot.  The
above example is with <literal>ayita</literal>
(<ulink url="http://hix.nu/svn-public/alexis/trunk/"/>), of which
there is usually an instance running in <literal>#svn</literal> at
freenode.  Other bots include Dancer
(<ulink url="http://dancer.sourceforge.net/"/>) and Supybot
(<ulink url="http://supybot.com/"/>).  Note that no special server
privileges are required to run a bot.  A bot is a client program;
anyone can set one up and direct it to listen to a particular
server/channel.</para>

<para>If your channel tends to get the same questions over and over,
I highly recommend setting up a bot.  Only a small percentage of
channel users will acquire the expertise needed to manipulate the bot,
but those users will answer a disproportionately high percentage of
questions, because the bot enables them to respond so much more
efficiently.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="irc-archiving">
<title>Archiving IRC</title>

<para>Although it is possible to archive everything that happens in an
IRC channel, it's not necessarily expected.  IRC conversations may be
nominally public, but many people think of them as informal,
semi-private conversations.  Users may be careless with grammar, and
often express opinions (for example, about other software or other
programmers) that they wouldn't want preserved forever in an online
archive.</para>

<para>Of course, there will sometimes be <emphasis>excerpts</emphasis>
that should be preserved, and that's fine.  Most IRC clients can log a
conversation to a file at the user's request, or failing that, one can
always just cut and paste the conversation from IRC into a more
permanent forum (most often the bug tracker).  But indiscriminate
logging may make some users uneasy.  If you do archive everything,
make sure you state so clearly in the channel topic, and give a URL to
the archive.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ========================== SECTION =========================== -->
<sect1 id="wikis">
<title>Wikis</title>

<para>A <firstterm>wiki</firstterm> is a web site that allows any
visitor to edit or extend its content; the term "wiki" (from a
Hawaiian word meaning "quick" or "super-fast") is also used to refer
to the software that enables such editing.  Wikis were invented in
1995, but their popularity has really started to take off since 2000
or 2001, boosted partly by the success of Wikipedia (<ulink
url="http://www.wikipedia.org/"/>), a wiki-based free-content
encyclopedia.  Think of a wiki as falling somewhere between IRC and
web pages: wikis don't happen in realtime, so people get a chance to
ponder and polish their contributions, but they are also very easy to
add to, involving less interface overhead than editing a regular web
page.</para>

<para>Wikis are not yet standard equipment for open source projects,
but they probably will be soon.  As they are relatively new
technology, and people are still experimenting with different ways of
using them, I will just offer a few words of caution here&mdash;at
this stage, it's easier to analyze misuses of wikis than to analyze
their successes.</para>

<para>If you decide to run a wiki, put a lot of effort into having a
clear page organization and pleasing visual layout, so that visitors
(i.e., potential editors) will instinctively know how to fit in their
contributions.  Equally important, post those standards on the wiki
itself, so people have somewhere to go for guidance.  Too often, wiki
administrators fall victim to the fantasy that because hordes of
visitors are individually adding high quality content to the site,
the sum of all these contributions must therefore also be of high
quality.  That's not how web sites work.  Each individual page or
paragraph may be good when considered by itself, but it will not be
good if embedded in a disorganized or confusing whole.  Too often,
wikis suffer from:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
     <para><emphasis role="bold">Lack of navigational principles.</emphasis>
     A well-organized web site makes visitors feel like they know
     where they are at any time.  For example, if the pages are
     well-designed, people can intuitively tell the difference
     between a "table of contents" region and a "content" region.
     Contributors to a wiki will respect such differences too, but
     only if the differences are present to begin with.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para><emphasis role="bold">Duplication of information.</emphasis>
     Wikis frequently end up with different pages saying similar
     things, because the individual contributors did not notice the
     duplications.  This can be partly a consequence of the lack of
     navigational principles noted above, in that people may not find
     the duplicate content if it is not where they expect it to
     be.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para><emphasis role="bold">Inconsistent target audience.</emphasis>
     To some degree this problem is inevitable when there are so many
     authors, but it can be lessened if there are written guidelines
     about how to create new content.  It also helps to aggressively
     edit new contributions at the beginning, as an example, so that
     the standards start to sink in.</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>The common solution to all these problems is the same: have
editorial standards, and demonstrate them not only by posting them,
but by editing pages to adhere to them.  In general, wikis will
amplify any failings in their original material, since contributors
imitate whatever patterns they see in front of them.  Don't just
set up the wiki and hope everything falls into place.  You must also
prime it with well-written content, so people have a template to
follow.</para>

<para>The shining example of a well-run wiki is Wikipedia, though this
may be partly 
because the content (encyclopedia entries) is naturally well-suited to
the wiki format.  But if you examine Wikipedia closely, you'll see
that its administrators laid a <emphasis>very</emphasis> thorough
foundation for cooperation.  There is extensive documentation on how
to write new entries, how to maintain an appropriate point of view,
what sorts of edits to make, what edits to avoid, a dispute resolution
process for contested edits (involving several stages, including
eventual arbitration), and so forth.  They also have authorization
controls, so that if a page is the target of repeated inappropriate
edits, they can lock it down until the problem is resolved.  In other
words, they didn't just throw some templates onto a web site and hope
for the best.  Wikipedia works because its founders thought carefully
about how to get thousands of strangers to tailor their writing to a
common vision.  While you may not need the same level of preparedness
to run a wiki for a free software project, the spirit is worth
emulating.</para>

<para>For more information about wikis, see
<ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wiki"/>.  Also, the first
wiki remains alive and well, and contains a lot of discussion about
running wikis: see <ulink
url="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?WelcomeVisitors"/>, 
<ulink url="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?WhyWikiWorks"/>, and
<ulink url="http://www.c2.com/cgi/wiki?WhyWikiWorksNot"/> for
various points of view.</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="web-site">
<title>Web Site</title>

<para>There is not much to say about setting up the project web site
from a technical point of view: setting up a web server and writing
web pages are fairly simple tasks, and most of the important things to
say about layout and arrangement were covered in the previous chapter.
The web site's main function is to present a clear and welcoming
overview of the project, and to bind together the other tools (the
version control system, bug tracker, etc.).  If you don't have the
expertise to set up a web server yourself, it's usually not hard to
find someone who does and is willing to help out.  Nonetheless, to
save time and effort, people often prefer to use one of the canned
hosting sites.</para>

<sect2 id="canned-hosting">
<title>Canned Hosting</title>

<para>There are two main advantages to using a canned site.  The first
is server capacity and bandwidth: their servers are beefy boxes sitting
on really fat pipes.  No matter how successful your project gets,
you're not going to run out of disk space or swamp the network
connection.  The second advantage is simplicity.  They have already
chosen a bug tracker, a version control system, a mailing list manager,
an archiver, and everything else you need to run a site.  They've
configured the tools, and are taking care of backups for all the data
stored in the tools.  You don't need to make many decisions.  All you
have to do is fill in a form, press a button, and suddenly you've got
a project web site.</para>

<para>These are pretty significant benefits.  The disadvantage, of
course, is that you must accept <emphasis>their</emphasis> choices and
configurations, even if something different would be better for your
project.  Usually canned sites are adjustable within certain narrow
parameters, but you will never get the fine-grained control you would
have if you set up the site yourself and had full administrative
access to the server.</para>

<para>A perfect example of this is the handling of generated files.
Certain project web pages may be generated files&mdash;for example,
there are systems for keeping FAQ data in an easy-to-edit master
format, from which HTML, PDF, and other presentation formats can be
generated.  As explained in
<xref linkend="version-everything"/><phrase output="printed">
earlier in this chapter</phrase>,
you wouldn't want to version the generated formats, only the master
file.  But when your web site is hosted on someone else's server, it
may be impossible to set up a custom hook to regenerate the online
HTML version of the FAQ whenever the master file is changed.  The only
workaround is to version the generated formats too, so that they show
up on the web site.</para>

<para>There can be larger consequences as well.  You may not have as
much control over presentation as you would wish.  Some of the canned
hosting sites allow you to customize your web pages, but the site's
default layout usually ends up showing through in various awkward
ways.  For example, some projects that host themselves at SourceForge
have completely customized home pages, but still point developers to
their "SourceForge page" for more information.  The SourceForge page
is what would be the project's home page, had the project not used a
custom home page.  The SourceForge page has links to the bug tracker,
the CVS repository, downloads, etc.  Unfortunately, a SourceForge page
also contains a great deal of extraneous noise.  The top is a banner
ad, often an animated image.  The left side is a vertical arrangement
of links of little relevance to someone interested in the project.
The right side is often another advertisement.  Only the center of the
page is devoted to truly project-specific material, and even that is
arranged in a confusing way that often makes visitors unsure of what
to click on next.</para>

<para>Behind every individual aspect of SourceForge's design, there is
no doubt a good reason&mdash;good from SourceForge's point of view,
such as the advertisements.  But from an individual project's point of
view, the result can be a less-than-ideal web page.  I don't mean to
pick on SourceForge; similar concerns apply to many of the canned
hosting sites.  The point is that there's a tradeoff.  You get relief
from the technical burdens of running a project site, but only at the
price of accepting someone else's way of running it.</para>

<para>Only you can decide whether canned hosting is best for your
project.  If you choose a canned site, leave open the option of
switching to your own servers later, by using a custom domain name for
the project's "home address".  You can forward the URL to the canned
site, or have a fully customized home page at the public URL and hand
users off to the canned site for sophisticated functionality.  Just
make sure to arrange things such that if you later decide to use a
different hosting solution, the project's address doesn't need to
change.</para>

<sect3 id="canned-hosting-choosing">
<title>Choosing a canned hosting site</title>

<para>The largest and most well-known hosting site is <ulink
url="http://www.sourceforge.net/">SourceForge</ulink>.  Two other
sites providing the same or similar services are <ulink
url="http://savannah.gnu.org/">savannah.gnu.org</ulink> and <ulink
url="http://www.berlios.de/">BerliOS.de</ulink>.  A few organizations,
such as the <ulink url="http://www.apache.org/">Apache Software
Foundation</ulink> and <ulink
url="http://www.tigris.org/">Tigris.org</ulink><footnote><para>Disclaimer:
I am employed by <ulink
url="http://www.collab.net/">CollabNet</ulink>, which sponsors
Tigris.org, and I use Tigris regularly.</para></footnote>, give free
hosting to open source projects that fit well with their missions and
their community of existing projects.</para>

<para>Haggen So did a thorough evaluation of various canned hosting
sites, as part of the research for his Ph.D. thesis,
<citetitle>Construction of an Evaluation Model for Free/Open Source
Project Hosting (FOSPHost) sites</citetitle>.  The results are at
<ulink url="http://www.ibiblio.org/fosphost/"/>, and see especially
the very readable comparison chart at <ulink
url="http://www.ibiblio.org/fosphost/exhost.htm"/>.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="anonymity">
<title>Anonymity and involvement</title>

<para>A problem that is not strictly limited to the canned sites, but
is most often found there, is the abuse of user login functionality.
The functionality itself is simple enough: the site allows each
visitor to register herself with a username and password.  From
then on it keeps a profile for that user, and project administrators
can assign the user certain permissions, for example, the right to
commit to the repository.</para>

<para>This can be extremely useful, and in fact it's one of the prime
advantages of canned hosting.  The problem is that sometimes user
login ends up being required for tasks that ought to be permitted to
unregistered visitors, specifically the ability to file issues in the
bug tracker, and to comment on existing issues.  By requiring a
logged-in username for such actions, the project raises the
involvement bar for what should be quick, convenient tasks.  Of
course, one wants to be able to contact someone who's entered data
into the issue tracker, but having a field where she can enter her
email address (if she wants to) is sufficient.  If a new user spots a
bug and wants to report it, she'll only be annoyed at having to fill
out an account creation form before she can enter the bug into the
tracker.  She may simply decide not to file the bug at all.</para>

<para>The advantages of user management generally outweigh the
disadvantages.  But if you can choose which actions can be done
anonymously, make sure not only that <emphasis>all</emphasis>
read-only actions are permitted to non-logged-in visitors, but also
some data entry actions, especially in the bug tracker and, if you
have them, wiki pages.</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1>


<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->


</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->

