<chapter id="social-infrastructure">

<title>Social and Political Infrastructure</title>

<simplesect>

<para>The first questions people usually ask about free software are
"How does it work?  What keeps a project running?  Who makes the
decisions?"  I'm always dissatisfied with bland responses about
meritocracy, the spirit of cooperation, code speaking for itself, etc.
The fact is, the question is not easy to answer.  Meritocracy,
cooperation, and running code are all part of it, but they do little
to explain how projects actually run on a day-to-day basis, and say
nothing about how conflicts are resolved.</para>

<para>This chapter tries to show the structural underpinnings
successful projects have in common.  I mean "successful" not just in
terms of technical quality, but also operational health and
survivability.  Operational health is the project's ongoing ability to
incorporate new code contributions and new developers, and to be
responsive to incoming bug reports.  Survivability is the project's
ability to exist independently of any individual participant or
sponsor&mdash;think of it as the likelihood that the project would
continue even if all of its founding members were to move on to other
things.  Technical success is not hard to achieve, but without a
robust developer base and social foundation, a project may be unable
to handle the growth that initial success brings, or the departure of
charismatic individuals.</para>

<para>There are various ways to achieve this kind of success.  Some
involve a formal governance structure, by which debates are resolved,
new developers are invited in (and sometimes out), new features
planned, and so on.  Others involve less formal structure, but more
conscious self-restraint, to produce an atmosphere of fairness that
people can rely on as a <foreignphrase>de facto</foreignphrase> form
of governance.  Both ways lead to the same result: a sense of
institutional permanence, supported by habits and procedures that are
well understood by everyone who participates.  These features are even
more important in self-organizing systems than in centrally-controlled
ones, because in self-organizing systems, everyone is conscious that a
few bad apples can spoil the whole barrel, at least for a while.</para>

<sect1 id="forkability">
<title>Forkability</title>

<para>The indispensable ingredient that binds developers together on a
free software project, and makes them willing to compromise when
necessary, is the code's <firstterm>forkability</firstterm>: the
ability of anyone to take a copy of the source code and use it to
start a competing project, known as a <firstterm>fork</firstterm>.
The paradoxical thing is that the <emphasis>possibility</emphasis> of
forks is usually a much greater force in free software projects than
actual forks, which are very rare.  Because a fork is bad for everyone
(for reasons examined in detail in
<xref linkend="forks"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="managing-volunteers"/></phrase>), the more serious
the threat of a fork becomes, the more willing people are to
compromise to avoid it.</para>

<para>Forks, or rather the potential for forks, are the reason there
are no true dictators in free software projects.  This may seem like a
surprising claim, considering how common it is to hear someone called
the "dictator" or "tyrant" in a given open source project.  But this
kind of tyranny is special, quite different from the conventional
understanding of the word.  Imagine a king whose subjects could copy
his entire kingdom at any time and move to the copy to rule as they
see fit.  Would not such a king govern very differently from one whose
subjects were bound to stay under his rule no matter what he
did?</para>

<para>This is why even projects that are not formally organized as
democracies are, in practice, democracies when it comes to important
decisions.  Replicability implies forkability; forkability implies
consensus.  It may well be that everyone is willing to defer to one
leader (the most famous example being Linus Torvalds in Linux kernel
development), but this is because they <emphasis>choose</emphasis> to
do so, in an entirely non-cynical and non-sinister way.  The dictator
has no magical hold over the project.  A key property of all open
source licenses is that they do not give one party more power than any
other in deciding how the code can be changed or used.  If the dictator
were to suddenly start making bad decisions, there would be
restlessness, followed eventually by revolt and a fork.  Except, of
course, things rarely get that far, because the dictator compromises
first.</para>

<para>But just because forkability puts an upper limit on how much
power anyone can exert in a project doesn't mean there aren't
important differences in how projects are governed.  You don't want
every decision to come down to the last-resort question of who is
considering a fork.  That would get tiresome very quickly, and sap
energy away from real work.  The next two sections examine different
ways to organize projects such that most decisions go smoothly.  These
two examples are somewhat idealized extremes; many projects fall
somewhere along a continuum between them.</para>

</sect1>

</simplesect>

<!-- For link compatibility with a previous misspelling. -->
<simplesect id="benevolant-dictator"></simplesect>
<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="benevolent-dictator">
<title>Benevolent Dictators</title>

<para>The <firstterm>benevolent dictator</firstterm> model is exactly
what it sounds like: final decision-making authority rests with one
person, who, by virtue of personality and experience, is expected
to use it wisely.</para>

<para>Although "benevolent dictator" (or <firstterm>BD</firstterm>)is
the standard term for this role, it would be better to think of it as
"community-approved arbitrator" or "judge".  Generally, benevolent
dictators do not actually make all the decisions, or even most of the
decisions.  It's unlikely that one person could have enough expertise
to make consistently good decisions across all areas of the project,
and anyway, quality developers won't stay around unless they have some
influence on the project's direction.  Therefore, benevolent dictators
commonly do not dictate much.  Instead, they let things work
themselves out through discussion and experimentation whenever
possible.  They participate in those discussions themselves, but as
regular developers, often deferring to an area maintainer who has more
expertise.  Only when it is clear that no consensus can be reached,
and that most of the group <emphasis>wants</emphasis> someone to guide
the decision so that development can move on, do they put their foot
down and say "This is the way it's going to be."  Reluctance to make
decisions by fiat is a trait shared by virtually all successful
benevolent dictators; it is one of the reasons they manage to keep the
role.</para>

<!-- For link compatibility with a previous misspelling. -->
<simplesect id="benevolant-dictator-qualifications"></simplesect>
<sect2 id="benevolent-dictator-qualifications">
<title>Who Can Be a Good Benevolent Dictator?</title>

<para>Being a BD requires a combination of traits.  It needs, first of
all, a well-honed sensitivity to one's own influence in the project,
which in turn brings self-restraint.  In the early stages of a
discussion, one should not express opinions and conclusions with so
much certainty that others feel like it's pointless to dissent.
People must be free to air ideas, even stupid ideas.  It is inevitable
that the BD will post a stupid idea from time to time too, of course,
and therefore the role also requires an ability to recognize and
acknowledge when one has made a bad decision&mdash;though this is
simply a trait that <emphasis>any</emphasis> good developer should
have, especially if she stays with the project a long time.  But the
difference is that the BD can afford to slip from time to time without
worrying about long-term damage to her credibility.  Developers with
less seniority may not feel so secure, so the BD should phrase
critiques or contrary decisions with some sensitivity for how much
weight her words carry, both technically and psychologically.</para>

<para>The BD does <emphasis>not</emphasis> need to have the sharpest
technical skills of anyone in the project.  She must be skilled enough
to work on the code herself, and to understand and comment on any
change under consideration, but that's all.  The BD position is
neither acquired nor held by virtue of intimidating coding skills.
What <emphasis>is</emphasis> important is experience and overall
design sense&mdash;not necessarily the ability to produce good
design on demand, but the ability to recognize good design, whatever
its source.</para>

<para>It is common for the benevolent dictator to be a founder of the
project, but this is more a correlation than a cause.  The sorts of
qualities that make one able to successfully start a
project&mdash;technical competence, ability to persuade other people
to join, etc.&mdash;are exactly the qualities any BD would need.  And
of course, founders start out with a sort of automatic seniority,
which can often be enough to make benevolent dictatorship appear the
path of least resistance for all concerned.</para>

<para>Remember that the potential to fork goes both ways.  A BD can
fork a project just as easily as anyone else, and some have
occasionally done so, when they felt that the direction they wanted to
take the project was different from where the majority of other
developers wanted to go.  Because of forkability, it does not matter
whether the benevolent dictator has root (system administrator
privileges) on the project's main servers or not.  People sometimes
talk of server control as though it were the ultimate source of power
in a project, but in fact it is irrelevant.  The ability to add or
remove people's commit passwords on one particular server affects only
the copy of the project that resides on that server.  Prolonged abuse
of that power, whether by the BD or someone else, would simply lead to
development moving to a different server.</para>

</sect2>

<para>Whether your project should have a benevolent dictator, or would
run better with some less centralized system, largely depends on who
is available to fill the role.  As a general rule, if it's simply
obvious to everyone who should be the BD, then that's the way to go.
But if no candidate for BD is immediately obvious, then the project
should probably use a decentralized decision-making process, as
described in the next section.</para>

</sect1>


<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="consensus-democracy">
<title>Consensus-based Democracy</title>

<para>As projects get older, they tend to move away from the
benevolent dictatorship model and toward more openly democratic
systems.  This is not necessarily out of dissatisfaction with a
particular BD.  It's simply that group-based governance is more
"evolutionarily stable", to borrow a biological metaphor.  Whenever a
benevolent dictator steps down, or attempts to spread decision-making
responsibility more evenly, it is an opportunity for the group to
settle on a new, non-dictatorial system&mdash;establish a
constitution, as it were.  The group may not take this opportunity the
first time, or the second, but eventually they will; once they do,
the decision is unlikely ever to be reversed.  Common sense explains
why: if a group of N people were to vest one person with special
power, it would mean that N&nbsp;-&nbsp;1 people were each agreeing to
decrease their individual influence.  People usually don't want to do
that.  Even if they did, the resulting dictatorship would still be
conditional: the group anointed the BD, clearly the group could depose
the BD.  Therefore, once a project has moved from leadership by a
charismatic individual to a more formal, group-based system, it rarely
moves back.</para>

<para>The details of how these systems work vary widely, but there are
two common elements: one, the group works by consensus most of the
time; two, there is a formal voting mechanism to fall back on when
consensus cannot be reached.</para>

<para><firstterm>Consensus</firstterm> merely means an agreement that
everyone is willing to live with.  It is not an ambiguous state: a
group has reached consensus on a given question when someone proposes
that consensus has been reached, and no one contradicts the assertion.
The person proposing consensus should, of course, state specifically
what the consensus is, and what actions would be taken in consequence
of it, if they're not obvious.</para>

<para>Most conversation in a project is on technical topics, such as
the right way to fix a certain bug, whether or not to add a feature,
how strictly to document interfaces, etc.  Consensus-based governance
works well because it blends seamlessly with the technical discussion
itself.  By the end of a discussion, there is often general agreement
on what course to take.  Someone will usually make a concluding post,
which is simultaneously a summary of what has been decided and an
implicit proposal of consensus.  This provides a last chance for
someone else to say "Wait, I didn't agree to that.  We need to hash
this out some more."</para>

<para>For small, uncontroversial decisions, the proposal of consensus
is implicit.  For example, when a developer spontaneously commits a
bugfix, the commit itself is a proposal of consensus: "I assume we all
agree that this bug needs to be fixed, and that this is the way to fix
it."  Of course, the developer does not actually say that; she just
commits the fix, and the others in the project do not bother to state
their agreement, because silence is consent.  If someone commits a
change that turns out <emphasis>not</emphasis> to have consensus, the
result is simply for the project to discuss the change as though it
had not already been committed.  The reason this works is the topic of
the next section.</para>

<sect2 id="version-control-relaxation">
<title>Version Control Means You Can Relax</title>

<para>The fact that the project's source code is kept under version
control means that most decisions can be easily unmade.  The most
common way this happens is that someone commits a change mistakenly
thinking everyone would be happy with it, only to be met with
objections after the fact.  It is typical for such objections to start
out with an obligatory apology for having missed out on prior
discussion, though this may be omitted if the objector finds no record
of such a discussion in the mailing list archives.  Either way, there
is no reason for the tone of the discussion to be different after the
change has been committed than before.  Any change can be reverted, at
least until dependent changes are introduced (i.e., new code that
would break if the original change were suddenly removed).  The
version control system gives the project a way to undo the effects of
bad or hasty judgement.  This, in turn, frees people to trust their
instincts about how much feedback is necessary before doing
something.</para>

<para>This also means that the process of establishing consensus need
not be very formal.  Most projects handle it by feel.  Minor changes
can go in with no discussion, or with minimal discussion followed by a
few nods of agreement.  For more significant changes, especially ones
with the potential to destabilize a lot of code, people should wait a
day or two before assuming there is consensus, the rationale being
that no one should be marginalized in an important conversation simply
because he didn't check email frequently enough.</para>

<para>Thus, when someone is confident he knows what needs to be done,
he should just go ahead and do it.  This applies not only to software
fixes, but to web site updates, documentation changes, and anything
else unlikely to be controversial.  Usually there will be only a few
instances where an action needs to be undone, and these can be handled on
a case-by-case basis.  Of course, one shouldn't encourage people to be
headstrong.  There is still a psychological difference between a
decision under discussion and one that has already taken effect, even
if it is technically reversible.  People always feel that momentum is
allied to action, and will be slightly more reluctant to revert a
change than to prevent it in the first place.  If a developer abuses
this fact by committing potentially controversial changes too quickly,
however, people can and should complain, and hold that developer to a
stricter standard until things improve.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="voting">
<title>When Consensus Cannot Be Reached, Vote</title>

<para>Inevitably, some debates just won't consense.  When all other
means of breaking a deadlock fail, the solution is to vote.  But
before a vote can be taken, there must be a clear set of choices on
the ballot.  Here, again, the normal process of technical discussion
blends serendipitously with the project's decision-making procedures.
The kinds of questions that come to a vote often involve complex,
multifaceted issues.  In any such complex discussion, there are
usually one or two people playing the role of <firstterm>honest
broker</firstterm>: posting periodic summaries of the various
arguments and keeping track of where the core points of disagreement
(and agreement) lie.  These summaries help everyone measure how much
progress has been made, and remind everyone of what issues remain to
be addressed.  Those same summaries can serve as prototypes for a
ballot sheet, should a vote become necessary.  If the honest brokers
have been doing their job well, they will be able to credibly call for
a vote when the time comes, and the group will be willing to use a
ballot sheet based on their summary of the issues.  The brokers
themselves may be participants in the debate; it is not necessary for
them to remain above the fray, as long as they can understand and
fairly represent others' views, and not let their partisan sentiments
prevent them from summarizing the state of the debate in a neutral
fashion.</para>

<para>The actual content of the ballot is usually not controversial.
By the time matters reach a vote, the disagreement has usually boiled
down to a few key issues, with recognizable labels and brief
descriptions.  Occasionally a developer will object to the form of the
ballot itself.  Sometimes his concern is legitimate, for example,
that an important choice was left off or not described accurately.
But other times a developer may be merely trying to stave off the
inevitable, perhaps knowing that the vote probably won't go his way.
See <xref linkend="difficult-people"/><phrase output="printed">
in <xref linkend="communications"/></phrase> for how to deal with
this sort of obstructionism.</para>

<para>Remember to specify the voting system, as there are many
different kinds, and people might make wrong assumptions about which
procedure is being used.  A good choice in most cases is
<firstterm>approval voting</firstterm>, whereby each voter can vote
for as many of the choices on the ballot as he likes.  Approval
voting is simple to explain and to count, and unlike some other
methods, it only involves one round of voting.  See <ulink
url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voting_system#List_of_systems"/> for
more details about approval voting and other voting systems, but try
to avoid getting into a long debate about which voting system to use
(because, of course, you will then find yourself in a debate about
which voting system to use to decide the voting system!).  One reason
approval voting is a good choice is that it's very hard for anyone to
object to&mdash;it's about as fair as a voting system can be.</para>

<para>Finally, conduct votes in public.  There is no need for secrecy
or anonymity in a vote on matters that have been debated publicly
anyway.  Have each participant post her votes to the project mailing
list, so that any observer can tally and check the results for
herself, and so that everything is recorded in the archives.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="when-to-vote">
<title>When To Vote</title>

<para>The hardest thing about voting is determining when to do it.  In
general, taking a vote should be very rare&mdash;a last resort for
when all other options have failed.  Don't think of voting as a great
way to resolve debates.  It isn't.  It ends discussion, and thereby
ends creative thinking about the problem.  As long as discussion
continues, there is the possibility that someone will come up with a
new solution everyone likes.  This happens surprisingly often: a
lively debate can produce a new way of thinking about the problem, and
lead to a proposal that eventually satisfies everyone.  Even when no
new proposal arises, it's still usually better to broker a compromise
than to hold a vote.  After a compromise, everyone is a little bit
unhappy, whereas after a vote, some people are unhappy while others
are happy.  From a political standpoint, the former situation is
preferable: at least each person can feel he extracted a price for his
unhappiness.  He may be dissatisfied, but so is everyone else.</para>

<para>Voting's main advantage is that it finally settles a question so
everyone can move on.  But it settles it by a head count, instead of
by rational dialogue leading everyone to the same conclusion.  The
more experienced people are with open source projects, the less eager
I find them to be to settle questions by vote.  Instead they will try
to explore previously unconsidered solutions, or compromise more
severely than they'd originally planned.  Various techniques are
available to prevent a premature vote.  The most obvious is simply to
say "I don't think we're ready for a vote yet," and explain why not.
Another is to ask for an informal (non-binding) show of hands.  If the
response clearly tends toward one side or another, this will make some
people suddenly more willing to compromise, obviating the need for a
formal vote.  But the most effective way is simply to offer a new
solution, or a new viewpoint on an old suggestion, so that people
re-engage with the issues instead of merely repeating the same
arguments.</para>

<para>In certain rare cases, everyone may agree that all the
compromise solutions are worse than any of the non-compromise ones.
When that happens, voting is less objectionable, both because it is
more likely to lead to a superior solution and because people will not
be overly unhappy no matter how it turns out.  Even then, the vote
should not be rushed.  The discussion leading up to a vote is what
educates the electorate, so stopping that discussion early can lower
the quality of the result.</para>

<para>(Note that this advice to be reluctant to call votes does not
apply to the change-inclusion voting described in
<xref linkend="stabilizing-a-release"/><phrase output="printed">
in <xref linkend="development-cycle"/></phrase>.  There, voting
is more of a communications mechanism, a means of registering one's
involvement in the change review process so that everyone can tell how
much review a given change has received.)</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="electorate">
<title>Who Votes?</title>

<para>Having a voting system raises the question of electorate: who
gets to vote?  This has the potential to be a sensitive issue, because
it forces the project to officially recognize some people as being
more involved, or as having better judgement, than others.</para>

<para>The best solution is to simply take an existing distinction,
commit access, and attach voting privileges to it.  In projects that
offer both full and partial commit access, the question of whether
partial committers can vote largely depends on the process by which
partial commit access is granted.  If the project hands it out
liberally, for example as a way of maintaining many third-party
contributed tools in the repository, then it should be made clear that
partial commit access is really just about committing, not voting.
The reverse implication naturally holds as well: since full committers
<emphasis>will</emphasis> have voting privileges, they must be chosen
not only as programmers, but as members of the electorate.  If someone
shows disruptive or obstructionist tendencies on the mailing list, the
group should be very cautious about making him a committer, even if
the person is technically skilled.</para>

<para>The voting system itself should be used to choose new
committers, both full and partial.  But here is one of the rare
instances where secrecy is appropriate.  You can't have votes about
potential committers posted to a public mailing list, because the
candidate's feelings (and reputation) could be hurt.  Instead, the
usual way is that an existing committer posts to a private mailing
list consisting only of the other committers, proposing that someone
be granted commit access.  The other committers speak their minds
freely, knowing the discussion is private.  Often there will be no
disagreement, and therefore no vote necessary.  After waiting a few
days to make sure every committer has had a chance to respond, the
proposer mails the candidate and offers him commit access.  If there
is disagreement, discussion ensues as for any other question, possibly
resulting in a vote.  For this process to be open and frank, the mere
fact that the discussion is taking place at all should be secret.  If
the person under consideration knew it was going on, and then were
never offered commit access, he could conclude that he had lost
the vote, and would likely feel hurt.  Of course, if someone
explicitly asks for commit access, then there is no choice but to
consider the proposal and explicitly accept or reject him.  If the
latter, then it should be done as politely as possible, with a clear
explanation: "We liked your patches, but haven't seen enough of them
yet," or "We appreciate all your patches, but they required
considerable adjustments before they could be applied, so we don't
feel comfortable giving you commit access yet.  We hope that this will
change over time, though."  Remember, what you're saying could come as
a blow, depending on the person's level of confidence.  Try to see it
from their point of view as you write the mail.</para>

<para>Because adding a new committer is more consequential than most
other one-time decisions, some projects have special requirements for
the vote.  For example, they may require that the proposal receive at
least <emphasis>n</emphasis> positive votes and no negative votes, or
that a supermajority vote in favor.  The exact parameters are not
important; the main idea is to get the group to be careful about
adding new committers.  Similar, or even stricter, special requirements
can apply to votes to <emphasis>remove</emphasis> a committer, though
hopefully that will never be necessary.  See <xref
linkend="committers"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="managing-volunteers"/></phrase> for more on the
non-voting aspects of adding and removing committers.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="polls">
<title>Polls Versus Votes</title>

<para>For certain kinds of votes, it may be useful to expand the
electorate. For example, if the developers simply can't figure out
whether a given interface choice matches the way people actually use
the software, one solution is to ask to all the subscribers of the
project's mailing lists to vote.  These are really
<firstterm>polls</firstterm> rather than votes, but the developers may
choose to treat the result as binding.  As with any poll, be sure to
make it clear to the participants that there's a write-in option: if
someone thinks of a better option not offered in the poll questions,
her response may turn out to be the most important result of the
poll.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="veto">
<title>Vetoes</title>

<para>Some projects allow a special kind of vote known as a
<firstterm>veto</firstterm>.  A veto is a way for a developer to put a
halt to a hasty or ill-considered change, at least long enough for
everyone to discuss it more.  Think of a veto as somewhere between a
very strong objection and a filibuster.  Its exact meaning varies from
one project to another.  Some projects make it very difficult to
override a veto; others allow them to be overridden by regular
majority vote, perhaps after an enforced delay for more discussion.
Any veto should be accompanied by a thorough explanation; a veto
without such an explanation should be considered invalid on
arrival.</para>

<para>With vetoes comes the problem of veto abuse.  Sometimes
developers are too eager to raise the stakes by casting a veto, when
really all that was called for was more discussion.  You can prevent
veto abuse by being very reluctant to use vetoes yourself, and by
gently calling it out when someone else uses her veto too often.  If
necessary, you can also remind the group that vetoes are binding for
only as long as the group agrees they are&mdash;after all, if a
clear majority of developers wants X, then X is going to happen one
way or another.  Either the vetoing developer will back down, or the
group will decide to weaken the meaning of a veto.</para>

<para>You may see people write "-1" to express a veto.  This usage
comes from the Apache Software Foundation, which has a highly
structured voting and veto process, described at <ulink
url="http://www.apache.org/foundation/voting.html"/>.  The Apache
standards have spread to other projects, and you will see their
conventions used to varying degrees in a lot of places in the open
source world.  Technically, "-1" does not always indicate a formal
veto even according to the Apache standards, but informally it is
usually taken to mean a veto, or at least a very strong
objection.</para>

<para>Like votes, vetoes can apply retroactively.  It's not okay to
object to a veto on the grounds that the change in question has
already been committed, or the action taken (unless it's something
irrevocable, like putting out a press release).  On the other hand, a
veto that arrives weeks or months late isn't likely to be taken very
seriously, nor should it be.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="written-rules">
<title>Writing It All Down</title>

<para>At some point, the number of conventions and agreements floating
around in your project may become so great that you need to record it
somewhere.  In order to give such a document legitimacy, make it clear
that it is based on mailing list discussions and on agreements already
in effect.  As you compose it, refer to the relevant threads in the
mailing list archives, and whenever there's a point you're not sure
about, ask again.  The document should not contain any surprises: it
is not the source of the agreements, it is merely a description of
them.  Of course, if it is successful, people will start citing it as
a source of authority in itself, but that just means it reflects the
overall will of the group accurately.</para>

<para>This is the document alluded to in <xref
linkend="developer-guidelines"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="getting-started"/></phrase>.  Naturally, when the
project is very young, you will have to lay down guidelines without
the benefit of a long project history to draw on.  But as the
development community matures, you can adjust the language to reflect
the way things actually turn out.</para>

<para>Don't try to be comprehensive.  No document can capture
everything people need to know about participating in a project.  Many
of the conventions a project evolves remain forever unspoken, never
mentioned explicitly, yet adhered to by all.  Other things are simply
too obvious to be mentioned, and would only distract from important
but non-obvious material.  For example, there's no point writing
guidelines like "Be polite and respectful to others on the mailing
lists, and don't start flame wars," or "Write clean, readable bug-free
code."  Of course these things are desirable, but since there's no
conceivable universe in which they might <emphasis>not</emphasis> be
desirable, they are not worth mentioning.  If people are being rude on
the mailing list, or writing buggy code, they're not going to stop
just because the project guidelines said to.  Such situations need to
be dealt with as they arise, not by blanket admonitions to be good.
On the other hand, if the project has specific guidelines about
<emphasis>how</emphasis> to write good code, such as rules about
documenting every API in a certain format, then those guidelines
should be written down as completely as possible.</para>

<para>A good way to determine what to include is to base the document
on the questions that newcomers ask most often, and on the complaints
experienced developers make most often.  This doesn't necessarily mean
it should turn into a FAQ sheet&mdash;it probably needs a more
coherent narrative structure than FAQs can offer.  But it should
follow the same reality-based principle of addressing the issues that
actually arise, rather than those you anticipate might arise.</para>

<para>If the project is a benevolent dictatorship, or has officers
endowed with special powers (president, chair, whatever), then the
document is also a good opportunity to codify succession procedures.
Sometimes this can be as simple as naming specific people as
replacements in case the BD suddenly leaves the project for any
reason.  Generally, if there is a BD, only the BD can get away with
naming a successor.  If there are elected officers, then the
nomination and election procedure that was used to choose them in the
first place should be described in the document.  If there was no
procedure originally, then get consensus on a procedure on the mailing
lists <emphasis>before</emphasis> writing about it.  People can
sometimes be touchy about hierarchical structures, so the subject
needs to be approached with sensitivity.</para>

<para>Perhaps the most important thing is to make it clear that the
rules can be reconsidered.  If the conventions described in the
document start to hamper the project, remind everyone that it is
supposed to be a living reflection of the group's intentions, not a
source of frustration and blockage.  If someone makes a habit of
inappropriately asking for rules to be reconsidered every time the
rules get in her way, you don't always need to debate it with
her&mdash;sometimes silence is the best tactic.  If other people
agree with the complaints, they'll chime in, and it will be obvious
that something needs to change.  If no one else agrees, then the
person won't get much response, and the rules will stay as they
are.</para>

<para>Two good examples of project guidelines are the Subversion
<filename>hacking.html</filename> file, at <ulink
url="http://subversion.apache.org/docs/community-guide/"/>, and the Apache
Software Foundation governance documents, at <ulink
url="http://www.apache.org/foundation/how-it-works.html"/> and <ulink
url="http://www.apache.org/foundation/voting.html"/>.  The ASF is
really a collection of software projects, legally organized as a
nonprofit corporation, so its documents tend to describe governance
procedures more than development conventions.  They're still worth
reading, though, because they represent the accumulated experience of
a lot of open source projects.</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
