<preface id="pfs-ch-0">
<title>Preface</title>
  
<simplesect>
    
<para>At cocktail parties, people no longer give me blank looks when I
tell them I write free software.  "Oh, yes, Open Source &mdash; like
Linux and all that stuff?" they say.  I nod eagerly in agreement.  The
terms Free Software and Open Source are largely interchangeable,
though the latter seems to be in wider use among non-programmers.
"Yes, exactly!  That's what we work on," I say.  </para>

<para> Over the last couple of decades, Free Software has gone from
being an obscure, mostly unfunded sideline in the software development
world, to a [todo]... but, although people now know what it
<emphasis>is</emphasis>, they don't know how it works.  The most
common questions are: "But how do you get paid?" and "Who makes the
decisions in these projects?".  </para> </simplesect>


<!-- ======================== SECTION 1 ============================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-ch-0-sect-1">
<title>Who Should Read This Book?</title>

<para> Describe target audience(s).  Describe assumed background here,
or in a separate section?  ("Assumed background" as in, the reader
knows what the term "source code" means, even if doesn't write code,
etc.)  Also: explain that to an experienced free software programmer,
much of this book will seem obvious, trite, and boring.  Point out how
wide the gap is and how you don't need the bridge if you're already on
the other side.</para>

</sect1>


<!-- ======================== SECTION 2 ============================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-ch-0-sect-2">
<title>Terminology</title>

<para> Explain very briefly how the two terms FS and OSS are
synonymous, though different in emphasis; talk about how people got
confused by "free", mention the open source consortium.  Point out
that the term "open source" gives the useful contrasting term "closed
source", which is much more descriptive than "non-free".  But this
initial mention of FS/OSS terminology should be very short, only a
paragraph or so.  Leave the rest for the History section in Chapter 1,
<xref linkend="pfs-ch-1-sect-1"/>.  </para>

<para> Anamoly: "closed-source" is almost always hyphenated, "open
source" is not.  Dunno why this is, but at least it should be
acknowledged.  Also, note how "commercial" is <emphasis>not</emphasis>
being used as an antonym for "free / open source" here: plenty of free
software projects are commercial in intent.  The important difference
is proprietary vs non-proprietary, not commercial vs
non-commercial. </para>

<para> Explain very briefly the difference between source code and
executable code, and why it matters.  Or should we just assume that
background?
</para>

<para> Define "patch", even give an example.  That concept is too
important to leave till later, and many people who know what source
code is may still not know what a patch is.
</para>

<para> Anything else?  </para>

</sect1>


<!-- ======================== SECTION 3 ============================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-ch-0-sect-3">
<title>Conventions Used in This Book</title>

<para> todo </para>

<sect2 id="pfs-ch-0-sect-3.1">
<title>Typographic Conventions</title>
<para> todo </para>
</sect2>

</sect1>

</preface>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
