<chapter id="pfs-ch-6">

<title>Daily Development, Packaging and Releasing <!-- [ 15-25 pp] --> </title>

<simplesect>

<para> todo chapter introduction </para>

        <para>a) 
        b) 
        c)</para>



</simplesect>


<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-ch-6-sect-1">
<title>Cycles</title>

<para><remark>Common development cycle patterns in free
software.</remark></para>


<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->

<sect2 id="pfs-ch-6-sect-1.1">
<title>Version Numbering</title>

<para><remark>talk about how to do release numbers right, refer here from the
      "Announcing" in Chapter 2</remark></para>

</sect2>

<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="pfs-ch-6-sect-1.2">
<title>Packaging for Distribution</title>

<para><remark>Talk about the importance of adhering to the standards.
Describe and reference them.  Use cvs2svn as an example of how *not*
to do it.  Importance of tight link between release numbering and
tarball unpackment result name.  Importance of certain standard
all-caps files in the top-level of the project, which will also serve
as canonical reference targets from web pages.  Therefore it's
important that either the version control system have a browse mode,
or that the live web site be a checked out tree.  Note this in section
3 on version control.</remark></para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-ch-6-sect-2">
<title>Integrating Process With Tools</title>

<para><remark>How to tie in with the revision control system and the
bug tracker, so that they become integral parts of distributed
development.</remark></para>

</sect1>


<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-ch-6-sect-3">
<title>Testing, Automated and Otherwise</title>

<para><remark>Regression testing: choosing the right level of
formality.  Coordinating results from human volunteers.</remark></para>

</sect1>


<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-ch-6-sect-4">
<title>Stabilizing and Releasing</title>

<para><remark>Stabilization and release preparation (i.e., avoiding the last
minute feature rush); making sure the process terminates in a finite
amount of time.  Point out how that releases may actually be harder in
open source projects than in proprietary ones.</remark></para>

</sect1>


<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-ch-6-sect-5">
<title>Maintaining Multiple Release Lines</title>

<para><remark>Whether and how to maintain multiple release lines.  Make sure
this gets tied in bidirectionally with revision control discussion
(branches, arch vs cvs-style, for example).  Also, stress importance
of training people to use the issue tracker well.  Be patient, be
verbose, repeat yourself -- it will feel stupid, but it <emphasis>will
pay off</emphasis>.</remark></para>

</sect1>


</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->

