<chapter id="pfs-ch-9">

<title>Reconcilable and Irreconcilable Differences <!-- [ 15-20 pp] --> </title>

<simplesect>

<para> todo chapter introduction </para>

</simplesect>


<!-- ======================== SECTION 1 ============================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-politics">
<title> Politics </title>

<para> Arguments happen.  Politics are inevitable.  How to deal with
this, especially in communities where people like to think that
they're immune to politics, or that if everyone would just look at the
technical issues objectively "...they'd see that I'm right!" :-)
</para>

</sect1>


<!-- ======================== SECTION 2 ============================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-forks">
<title> Forks </title>

<para> How to recognize when a fork is inevitable, how to prevent it
when is isn't.  Handling forks both amicable and hostile.  </para>

<para><remark>(In explaining why there is no definitive answer to the
question of "which fork is the true fork", use the obvious
evolutionary analogy.  Point out how people will colloquially talk of
how fork F came out of project P, rather than the reverse, but this is
in effect a declaration of how that speaker feels about it.  When a
large enough percentage of observers agree, then it starts to become
objectively true.  It is fundamentally a matter of perception: that
is, it's not the case that there's an objective truth here, but we are
only imperfectly able to perceive it.  Rather, the perceptions
<emphasis>are</emphasis> the objective truth, since ultimately a
project (or a ofork) is an entity that exists only in people's minds
anyway.)</remark></para>

<para><remark>Paragraph lifted from Chapter 4, may eventually have a
place here:</remark></para>

<para><remark>People tend not to use the threat of a fork as an
extremist debating technique &mdash; "Do things my way or I'll fork
the project!" &mdash; because everyone is aware that a fork which
fails to attract developers away from the original project is unlikely
to survive long.  All observers, not just developers but users and
operating system packagers too, will make their own judgement about
which side to choose.  Anyone who would contemplate initiating a fork
knows this, and would therefore want to appear extremely reluctant to
fork, so that if they finally do it, they can credibly claim it was
the only route left.  Whether they were actually reluctant or not
doesn't matter, since fake reluctance has much the same outward effect
as real reluctance.</remark></para>

</sect1>


<!-- ======================== SECTION 3 ============================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-case-studies">
<title> Case Studies </title>

<para> todo </para>

<screen> Should these really be their own section?

        [ Case study #1: The GDB maintainership structure debate. ]
        [ Case study #2: FSF Emacs / XEmacs fork (?maybe?) ]
</screen>

</sect1>

</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->

