<preface id="pfs-ch-0">
<title>Preface</title>
  
<simplesect>
    
<para>At cocktail parties, people no longer give me blank looks when I
tell them I write free software.  "Oh, yes, Open Source &mdash; like
Linux and all that stuff?" they say.  I nod eagerly in agreement.  The
terms <emphasis>free software</emphasis> and <emphasis>open
source</emphasis> are largely interchangeable, though the latter seems
to be in wider use among non-programmers.  "Yes, exactly!  That's what
we work on," I say.  </para>

<remark>(Is &lt;emphasis&gt; the right thing for the terms
above?  I didn't want to use &lt;firstterm&gt; because the terms
aren't actually defined here, just mentioned.)</remark>

<para>Over the last couple of decades, Free Software has gone from
being an obscure, mostly unfunded sideline in the software development
world, to a [todo]... but, although people now know what it
<emphasis>is</emphasis>, they don't know how it works.  The most
common questions are: "But how do you get paid?" and "Who makes the
decisions in these projects?".</para>

</simplesect>


<!-- ======================== SECTION 1 ============================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-ch-0-sect-1">
<title>Who Should Read This Book?</title>

<para>Describe target audience(s), and assumed reader background.  (As
in, the reader should know what the terms "source code" and "commit"
mean, even if doesn't write code, etc.)  Also: explain that to an
experienced free software programmer, much of this book will seem
obvious, trite, and boring.  Point out how wide the gap is and how you
don't need the bridge if you're already on the other side.</para>

</sect1>


<!-- ======================== SECTION 2 ============================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-ch-0-sect-2">
<title>Terminology</title>

<remark>(I looked at moving Terminology into Chapter 1, as you
suggested.  The problem is that it would need to come early, since
both terms are used in the remainder of the chapter, but I'm pretty
happy with the way Chapter 1 currently begins, and it doesn't have a
really good place for an early terminology detour.  So for now the
terminology is here.  Not sure what the best solution is...  I'm
leaning toward leaving it here, but making it as brief as possible,
and including pointers to later sections where further detail is
warranted.)</remark>

<para> Explain very briefly how the two terms FS and OSS are
synonymous, though different in emphasis; talk about how people got
confused by "free", mention the open source consortium.  Point out
that the term "open source" gives the useful contrasting term "closed
source", which is much more descriptive than "non-free".  But this
initial mention of FS/OSS terminology should be very short, only a
paragraph or so.  Leave the rest for the History section in Chapter 1,
<xref linkend="pfs-ch-1-sect-1"/>.  </para>

<para> Anamoly: "closed-source" is almost always hyphenated, "open
source" is not.  Dunno why this is, but at least it should be
acknowledged.  Also, note how "commercial" is <emphasis>not</emphasis>
being used as an antonym for "free / open source" here: plenty of free
software projects are commercial in intent.  The important difference
is proprietary vs non-proprietary, not commercial vs
non-commercial. </para>

<para> Explain very briefly the difference between source code and
executable code, and why it matters.  Or should we just assume that
background?
</para>

<para> Anything else?  </para>

</sect1>


<!-- ======================== SECTION 3 ============================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-ch-0-sect-3">
<title>Conventions Used in This Book</title>

<remark>(O'Reilly probably has boilerplate for this
section.)</remark>

<sect2 id="pfs-ch-0-sect-3.1">
<title>Typographic Conventions</title>
<para> todo </para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="pfs-ch-0-sect-3.2">
<title>Sourcing Conventions</title>
<para> Might want to note why a URL is sometimes given and sometimes
not.  Basically, it's a matter of convenience.  When offering a quote,
for example, it's best to give the actual web page.  But a mention of
a project may or may not call for a URL, depending on the context.
The general principle is that if the obvious Google search would
quickly lead to the item in question, then there's no point giving the
URL, unless it would be very easy &amp; unobtrusive to do so.</para>
</sect2>

</sect1>

</preface>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
