<chapter id="pfs-ch-4">

<title>Technical Infrastructure <!-- [ 10-20 pp ] --></title>

<simplesect>

<para> todo chapter introduction </para>

<para>(Remember to note the temptations/perils of over-automation,
that is, attempts to automate things that really require human
attention.  Technical infrastructure is important, but what makes a
free software project work is the care -- and intelligent application
of that care -- by the humans involved.  One good example is the
FAQ-o-Matic disaster.  Search for other examples of over-automation,
for example, in use of bug tracking systems.)</para>

</simplesect>


<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-ch-4-sect-1">
<title> What a Project Needs </title>

<para> Project web site, source code repository, mailing lists, bug
tracker, IRC, and other communications forums. </para>

</sect1>


<!-- ========================== SECTION =========================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-ch-4-sect-2">
<title>Packaging for Distribution</title>

<para><remark>(Talk about the importance of adhering to the standards.
Describe and reference them.  Use cvs2svn as an example of how *not*
to do it.)</remark></para>

</sect1>


<!-- ========================== SECTION =========================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-ch-4-sect-3">
<title>Version Control</title>

<remark>(Talk about the importance of doing it, describe it as a
communications medium, list the choices, point out that CVS is the
safe choice right now.  Talk about commit emails, setting
reply-to.)</remark>


</sect1>


<!-- ========================== SECTION =========================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-ch-4-sect-4">
<title>Bug Tracker</title>

<para>todo</para>


</sect1>
<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="pfs-ch-4-sect-5">
<title> What's Out There For Free? </title>

<para>Describe various sites that provide some of these services for
free, such as SourceForge, Savannah, Freenode, etc.  Evaluate
pros/cons of each, compare with roll-your-own solutions. </para>

<para><remark>A *perfect* example of one disadvantage of using a
canned site: the handling of generated files.  You don't want them in
version control, because they're generated.  On the other hand, you
can't make arbitrary scripts run on the server, because you don't own
the server.  Use the SVN FAQ as a cautionary tale.</remark></para>

<para><remark>(Mention the survey by Haggen So, at
http://www.ibiblio.org/fosphost/ and
http://www.ibiblio.org/fosphost/exhost.htm.  It's pretty amazing!)
</remark></para>

</sect1>


</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->

