<chapter id="legal">

<title>Licenses, Copyrights, and Patents</title>

<simplesect>

<para>The license you select probably won't have a major impact on the
adoption of your project, as long as the license is open source.
Users generally choose software based on quality and features, not on
the details of the license.  Nevertheless, you still need a basic
understanding of free software licensing issues, both to ensure that
the project's license is compatible with its goals, and to be able to
discuss licensing decisions with other people.  Please note, however,
that I am not a lawyer, and that nothing in this chapter should be
construed as formal legal advice.  For that, you'll need to hire a
lawyer or be one.</para>

</simplesect>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="licenses-terminology">
<title>Terminology</title>

<para>In any discussion of open source licensing, the first thing that
becomes apparent is that there seem to be many different words for the
same thing: <firstterm>free&nbsp;software</firstterm>,
<firstterm>open&nbsp;source</firstterm>,
<firstterm>FOSS</firstterm>, <firstterm>F/OSS</firstterm>, and
<firstterm>FLOSS</firstterm>.  Let's start by sorting those
out, along with a few other terms.</para>

<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><firstterm>free software</firstterm></term>
    <listitem><para>Software that can be freely shared and modified,
              including in source code form.  The term was first
              coined by Richard Stallman, who codified it in the GNU
              General Public License (GPL), and who founded the Free
              Software Foundation (<ulink url="http://www.fsf.org/"/>)
              to promote the concept.</para>

              <para>Although "free software" covers almost exactly the
              same range of software as "open source", the FSF, among
              others, prefers the former term because it emphasizes
              the idea of freedom, and the concept of
              freely redistributable software as primarily a social
              movement rather than a technical one.  The FSF
              acknowledges that the term is ambiguous&mdash;it could
              mean "free" as in "zero-cost", instead of "free" as in
              "freedom"&mdash;but feels that it's still the best term,
              all things considered, and that the other possibilities
              in English have their own ambiguities.  (Throughout this
              book, "free" is used in the "freedom" sense, not the
              "zero-cost" sense.)</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term><firstterm>open source software</firstterm></term>

    <listitem><para>Free software under another name.  But the
              different name reflects an important philosophical
              difference: "open source" was coined by the Open Source
              Initiative (<ulink url="http://www.opensource.org/"/>)
              as a deliberate alternative to "free software," in order
              to make such software a more palatable choice for
              corporations, by presenting it as a development
              methodology rather than a political movement.  They may
              also have wanted to overcome another stigma: that
              anything "free" must be low quality.</para>

              <para>While any license that is free is also open
              source, and vice versa (with a few minor exceptions),
              people tend to pick one term and stick with it.  In
              general, those who prefer "free software" are more
              likely to have a philosophical or moral stance on the
              issue, while those who prefer "open source" either don't
              view it as a matter of freedom, or are not interested in
              advertising the fact that they do.  See
              <xref linkend="free-vs-open-source"/><phrase
              output="printed"> in
              <xref linkend="introduction"/></phrase> for a more
              detailed history of this schism.</para>

              <para>The Free Software Foundation has an
              excellent&mdash;utterly unobjective, but nuanced and
              quite fair&mdash;exegesis of the two terms, at <ulink
   url="http://www.fsf.org/licensing/essays/free-software-for-freedom.html"/>.
              The Open Source Initiative's take on it is spread across
              two pages: <ulink
   url="http://www.opensource.org/advocacy/case_for_hackers.php#marketing"/>
              and <ulink
   url="http://www.opensource.org/advocacy/free-notfree.php"/>.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term><firstterm>FOSS</firstterm>,
                      <firstterm>F/OSS</firstterm>,
                      <firstterm>FLOSS</firstterm></term>

    <listitem><para>Where there are two of anything, there will soon
              be three, and that is exactly what is happening with
              terms for free software.  The academic world, perhaps
              wanting precision and inclusiveness over elegance, seems
              to have settled on FOSS, or sometimes F/OSS, standing
              for "Free / Open Source Software".  Another variant
              gaining momentum is FLOSS, which
              stands for "Free / Libre Open Source Software"
              (<foreignphrase>libre</foreignphrase> is familiar in
              many languages and does not suffer from the ambiguities
              of "free"; see
              <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FLOSS"/> for
              more).</para>

              <para>All these terms mean essentially the same thing:
              software that can be modified and redistributed by
              everyone, sometimes&mdash;but not always&mdash;with the
              requirement that derivative works be freely
              redistributable under the same terms.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term><firstterm>DFSG-compliant</firstterm></term>
    <listitem><para>Compliant with the Debian Free Software Guidelines
              (<ulink
              url="http://www.debian.org/social_contract#guidelines"/>).
              This is a widely-used test for whether a given license
              is truly open source
              (free, <foreignphrase>libre</foreignphrase>, etc.).  The
              Debian Project's mission is to maintain an entirely free
              operating system, such that someone installing it need
              never doubt that she has the right to modify and
              redistribute any or all of the system.  The Debian Free
              Software Guidelines are the requirements that a software
              package's license must meet in order to be included in
              Debian.  Because the Debian Project spent a good deal of
              time thinking about how to construct such a test, the
              guidelines they came up with have proven very robust
              (see <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DFSG"/>),
              and as far as I'm aware, no serious objection to them has
              been raised either by the Free Software Foundation or
              the Open Source Initiative.  If you know that a given
              license is DFSG-compliant, you know that it guarantees
              all the important freedoms (such as forkability even
              against the original author's wishes) required to
              sustain the dynamics of an open source project.  All of
              the licenses discussed in this chapter are
              DFSG-compliant.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term><firstterm>OSI-approved</firstterm></term>
    <listitem><para>Approved by the Open Source Initiative.  This is
              another widely-used test of whether a license permits
              all the necessary freedoms.  The OSI's definition of
              open source software is based on the Debian Free
              Software Guidelines, and any license that meets one
              definition almost always meets the other.  There have
              been a few exceptions over the years, but only involving
              niche licenses and none of any relevance here.  Unlike
              the Debian Project, the OSI maintains a list of all
              licenses it has ever approved, at
              <ulink url="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/"/>, so
              that being "OSI-approved" is an unambiguous state: a
              license either is or isn't on the list.</para>

              <para>The Free Software Foundation also maintains a list
              of licenses at <ulink
              url="http://www.fsf.org/licensing/licenses/license-list.html"/>.
              The FSF categorizes licenses not only by whether they
              are free, but whether they are compatible with the GNU
              General Public License.  GPL compatibility is an
              important topic, covered in
              <xref
              linkend="license-compatibility"/><phrase
              output="printed"> later in this chapter</phrase>.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term><firstterm>proprietary</firstterm>,
                      <firstterm>closed-source</firstterm></term>
    <listitem><para>The opposite of "free" or "open source."  It means
              software distributed under traditional, royalty-based
              licensing terms, where users pay per copy, or under any
              other terms sufficiently restrictive to prevent open
              source dynamics from operating.  Even software
              distributed at no charge can still be proprietary, if
              its license does not permit free redistribution and
              modification.</para>

              <para>Generally "proprietary" and "closed-source" are
              synonyms.  However, "closed-source" additionally implies
              that the source code cannot even be seen.  Since the
              source code cannot be seen with most proprietary
              software, this is normally a distinction without a
              difference.  However, occasionally someone releases
              proprietary software under a license that allows others
              to view the source code.  Confusingly, they sometimes
              call this "open source" or "nearly open source," etc.,
              but that's misleading. The
              <emphasis>visibility</emphasis> of the source code is
              not the issue; the important question is what you're
              allowed to do with it.  Thus, the difference between
              proprietary and closed-source is mostly irrelevant, and
              the two can be treated as synonyms.</para>

              <para>Sometimes <firstterm>commercial</firstterm> is
              used as a synonym for "proprietary," but properly
              speaking, the two are not the same thing.  Free software
              can be commercial software.  After all, free software
              can be sold, as long as the buyers are not restricted
              from giving away copies themselves.  It can be
              commercialized in other ways as well, for example by
              selling support, services, and certification.  There are
              multimillion dollar companies built on free software
              today, so it is clearly neither inherently
              anti-commercial nor anti-corporate.  On the other hand,
              it <emphasis>is</emphasis> anti-proprietary by its
              nature, and this is the key way in which it differs from
              traditional per-copy license models.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term><firstterm>public domain</firstterm></term>
    <listitem><para>Having no copyright holder, meaning that there is
              no one who has the right to restrict copying of the
              work.  Being in the public domain is not the same as
              having no author.  Everything has an author, and even if a
              work's author or authors choose to put it in the public
              domain, that doesn't change the fact that they wrote
              it.</para>

              <para>When a work is in the public domain, material from
              it can be incorporated into a copyrighted work, and
              thereafter <emphasis>that copy</emphasis> of the
              material is covered under the same copyright as the
              whole work.  But this does not affect the availability
              of the original work, which remains in the public
              domain.  Thus, releasing something into the public
              domain is technically one way to make it "free,"
              according to the guidelines of most free software
              certifying organizations.  However, there are usually
              good reasons to use a license instead of just releasing
              into the public domain: even with free software, certain
              restrictions can be useful, not only to the copyright
              holder but even to recipients as well, as the next
              section makes clear.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term><firstterm>copyleft</firstterm></term>
    <listitem><para>A license that uses copyright law to achieve a
              result opposite to traditional copyright.  Depending on
              whom you ask, this means either licenses that permit
              the freedoms under discussion here, or, more narrowly,
              licenses that not only permit those freedoms but
              <emphasis>enforce</emphasis> them, by stipulating that
              the freedoms must travel with the work.  The Free
              Software Foundation uses the second definition
              exclusively; elsewhere, it's a toss-up: a lot of people
              use the term the same way the FSF does, but
              others&mdash;including some who write for mainstream
              media&mdash;tend to use the first definition.  It's not
              clear that everyone using the term is aware that there's
              a distinction to be made.</para>

              <para>The canonical example of the narrower, stricter
              definition is the GNU General Public License, which
              stipulates that any derivative works must also be
              licensed under the GPL; see
              <xref
              linkend="license-compatibility"/><phrase
              output="printed"> later in this chapter</phrase> for
              more.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="license-aspects">
<title>Aspects of Licenses</title>

<para>Although there are many different free software licenses
available, in the important respects they all say the same things:
that anyone can modify the code, that anyone can redistribute it both
in original and modified form, and that the copyright holders and
authors provide no warranties whatsoever (avoiding liability is
especially important given that people might run modified versions
without even knowing it).  The differences between licences boil down
to a few oft-recurring issues:</para>

<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term>compatibility with proprietary licenses</term>
    <listitem><para>Some free licenses allow the covered code to be
              used in proprietary programs.  This does not affect the
              licensing terms of the proprietary program: it is still
              as proprietary as ever, it just happens to contain some
              code from a non-proprietary source.  The Apache License,
              X Consortium License, BSD-style license, and the
              MIT-style license are all examples of
              proprietary-compatible licenses.</para> 
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>compatibility with other free licenses</term>
    <listitem><para>Most free licenses are compatible with each other,
              meaning that code under one license can be combined with
              code under another, and the result distributed under
              either license without violating the terms of the
              other.  The major exception to this is the GNU General
              Public License, which requires that any work using GPLed
              code be itself distributed under the GPL, and without
              adding any further restrictions beyond what the GPL
              requires.  The GPL is compatible with some free
              licenses, but not with others.  This is discussed in more
              detail in
              <xref linkend="license-compatibility"/><phrase
              output="printed"> later in this chapter</phrase>.</para> 
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>enforcement of crediting</term>
    <listitem><para>Some free licenses stipulate that any use of the
              covered code be accompanied by a notice, whose placement
              and display is usually specified, giving credit to the
              authors or copyright holders of the code.  These
              licenses are often still proprietary-compatible: they do
              not necessarily demand that the derivative work be free,
              merely that credit be given to the free code.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>protection of trademark</term>
    <listitem><para>A variant of credit enforcement.
              Trademark-protecting licenses specify that the name of
              the original software (or its copyright holders, or
              their institution, etc.) may <emphasis>not</emphasis> be
              used by derivative works without prior written
              permission.  Although credit enforcement insists that a
              certain name be used, and trademark protection insists
              that it not be used, they are both expressions of the
              same desire: that the original code's reputation be
              preserved and transmitted, but not tarnished by
              association.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>protection of "artistic integrity"</term>
    <listitem><para>Some licenses (the Artistic License, used
              for the most popular implementation of the Perl
              programming language, and Donald Knuth's TeX license,
              for example) require that modification and
              redistribution be done in a manner that distinguishes
              clearly between the pristine original version of the
              code and any modifications.  They permit essentially the
              same freedoms as other free license, but impose certain
              requirements that make the integrity of the original
              code easy to verify.  These licenses have not caught on
              much beyond the specific programs they were made for,
              and will not be discussed in this chapter; they are
              mentioned here only for the sake of completeness.</para> 
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>Most of these stipulations are not mutually exclusive, and some
licenses include several.  The common thread among them is that they
place demands on the recipient in exchange for the recipient's right
to use and/or redistribute the code.  For example, some projects want
their name and reputation to be transmitted along with the code, and
this is worth imposing the extra burden of a credit or trademark
clause; depending on its onerousness, that burden may result in some
users choosing a package with a less demanding license.</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="license-compatibility">
<title>The GPL and License Compatibility</title>

<para>By far the sharpest dividing line in licensing is that between
proprietary-incompatible and proprietary-compatible licenses, that is,
between the GNU General Public License and everything else.  Because
the primary goal of the GPL's authors is the promotion of free
software, they deliberately crafted the license to make it impossible
to mix GPLed code into proprietary programs.  Specifically, among the
GPL's requirements (see
<ulink url="http://www.fsf.org/licensing/licenses/gpl.html"/> for its
full text) are these two:</para>

<orderedlist>
  <listitem><para>Any derivative work&mdash;that is, any work
            containing a nontrivial amount of GPLed code&mdash;must
            itself be distributed under the GPL.</para> 
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>No additional restrictions may be placed on the
            redistribution of either the original work or a derivative
            work.  (The exact language is: "You may not impose any
            further restrictions on the recipients' exercise of the
            rights granted herein.")</para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>With these conditions, the GPL succeeds in making freedom
contagious.  Once a program is copyrighted under the GPL, its terms of
redistribution are <firstterm>viral</firstterm>&mdash;they are passed
on to anything else the code gets incorporated into, making it
effectively impossible to use GPLed code in closed-source programs.
However, these same clauses also make the GPL incompatible with
certain other free licenses.  The usual way this happens is that the
other license imposes a requirement&mdash;for example, a credit clause
requiring the original authors to be mentioned in some way&mdash;that
is incompatible with the GPL's "You may not impose any further
restrictions..." language.  From the point of view of the Free
Software Foundation, these second-order consequences are desirable, or
at least not regrettable.  The GPL not only keeps your software free,
but effectively makes your software an agent in pushing
<emphasis>other</emphasis> software to enforce freedom as well.</para>

<para>The question of whether or not this is a good way to
promote free software is one of the most persistent holy wars on the
Internet (see <xref linkend="holy-wars"/><phrase output="printed">
in <xref linkend="communications"/></phrase>), and we won't
investigate it here.  What's important for our purposes is that
GPL compatibility is an important issue when choosing a license.  The
GPL is by far the most popular open source license; at <ulink
url="http://freshmeat.net/stats/#license"/>, it is at 68%, and the
next highest license is at 6%.  If you want your code to be able to be
mixed freely with GPLed code&mdash;and there's a lot of GPLed code out
there&mdash;then you should pick a GPL-compatible license.  Most of
the GPL-compatible open source licenses are also
proprietary-compatible: that is, code under such a license can be used
in a GPLed program, and it can be used in a proprietary program.  Of
course, the <emphasis>results</emphasis> of these mixings would not be
compatible with each other, since one would be under the GPL and the
other would be under a closed-source license.  But that concern
applies only to the derivative works, not to the code you distribute
in the first place.</para>

<para>Fortunately, the Free Software Foundation maintains a list
showing which licenses are compatible with the GPL and which are not,
at <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/license-list.html"/>.  All
of the licenses discussed in this chapter are present on that list, on
one side or the other.</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="license-choosing">
<title>Choosing a License</title>

<para>When choosing a license to apply to your project, if at all
possible use an existing license instead of making up a new one.
There are two reasons why existing licenses are better:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>Familiarity.  If you use one of the three or four
            most popular licenses, people won't feel they have to read
            the legalese in order to use your code, because they'll
            have already done so for that license a long time ago.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>Quality.  Unless you have a team of lawyers at your
            disposal, you are unlikely to come up with a legally solid
            license.  The licenses mentioned here are the products of
            much thought and experience; unless your project has truly
            unusual needs, it is unlikely you would do better.</para> 
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
   
<para>To apply one of these licenses to your project, see
<xref linkend="license-quickstart-applying"/><phrase output="printed">
in <xref linkend="getting-started"/></phrase>.</para>

<sect2 id="license-choosing-mit-x">
<title>The MIT / X Window System License</title>

<para>If your goal is that your code be accessible by the greatest
possible number of developers and derivative works, and you do not
mind the code being used in proprietary programs, choose the MIT / X
Window System license (so named because it is the license under which
the Massachusetts Institute of Technology released the original X
Window System code).  This license's basic message is "You are free to
use this code however you want."  It is compatible with the GNU GPL,
and it is short, simple, and easy to understand:</para>

<screen>Copyright (c) &lt;year&gt; &lt;copyright holders&gt;

Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining
a copy of this software and associated documentation files (the
"Software"), to deal in the Software without restriction, including
without limitation the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish,
distribute, sublicense, and/or sell copies of the Software, and to
permit persons to whom the Software is furnished to do so, subject to
the following conditions:

The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be
included in all copies or substantial portions of the Software.

THE SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED "AS IS", WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND,
EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO THE WARRANTIES OF
MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE AND
NONINFRINGEMENT. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHORS OR COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE
LIABLE FOR ANY CLAIM, DAMAGES OR OTHER LIABILITY, WHETHER IN AN ACTION
OF CONTRACT, TORT OR OTHERWISE, ARISING FROM, OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION
WITH THE SOFTWARE OR THE USE OR OTHER DEALINGS IN THE SOFTWARE.</screen>

<para>(Taken from <ulink
url="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/mit-license.php"/>.)</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="license-choosing-gpl">
<title>The GNU General Public License</title>

<para>If you prefer that your project's code not be used in
proprietary programs, or if you at least don't care whether or not it
can be used in proprietary programs, choose the GNU General Public
License
(<ulink url="http://www.fsf.org/licensing/licenses/gpl.html"/>).  The
GPL is probably the most widely-used free software license in the
world today; this instant recognizability is itself one of the GPL's
major advantages.</para>

<para>When writing a code library that is meant mainly to be used as
part of other programs, consider carefully whether the restrictions
imposed by the GPL are in line with your project's goals.  In some
cases&mdash;for example, when you're trying to unseat a competing,
proprietary library that does the same thing&mdash;it may make more
strategic sense to license your code in such a way that it can be
mixed into proprietary programs, even though you would otherwise not
wish this.  The Free Software Foundation even fashioned an alternative
to the GPL for such circumstances: the <firstterm>GNU Library
GPL</firstterm>, later renamed to the <firstterm>GNU Lesser
GPL</firstterm> (most people just use the acronym
<firstterm>LGPL</firstterm>, in any case).  The LGPL has looser
restrictions than the GPL, and can be mixed more easily with non-free
code.  However, it's also a bit complex and takes some time to
understand, so if you're not going to use the GPL, I recommend just
using the MIT/X-style license.</para>

<sect3 id="is-the-gpl-free">
<title>Is the GPL free or not free?</title>

<para>One consequence of choosing the GPL is the
possibility&mdash;small, but not infinitely small&mdash;of finding
yourself or your project embroiled in a dispute about whether or not
the GPL is truly "free", given that it places some restrictions on
what you can do with the code&mdash;namely, the restriction that the
code cannot be distributed under any other license.  For some people,
the existence of this restriction means the GPL is "less free" than
more permissive licenses such as the MIT/X license.  Where this
argument usually goes, of course, is that since "more free" must be
better than "less free" (after all, who's not in favor of freedom?),
it follows that those licenses are better than the GPL.</para>

<para>This debate is another popular holy war (see
<xref linkend="holy-wars"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="communications"/></phrase>).  Avoid participating
in it, at least in project forums.  Don't attempt to prove that the
GPL is less free, as free, or more free than other licenses.  Instead,
emphasize the specific reasons your project chose the GPL.  If the
recognizability of license was a reason, say that.  If the enforcement
of a free license on derivative works was also a reason, say that too,
but refuse to be drawn into discussion about whether this makes the
code more or less "free".  Freedom is a complex topic, and there is
little point talking about it if terminology is going to be used as a
stalking horse for substance.</para>

<para>Since this is a book and not a mailing list thread, however, I
will admit that I've never understood the "GPL is not free" argument.
The only restriction the GPL imposes is that it prevents people from
imposing <emphasis>further</emphasis> restrictions.  To say that this
results in less freedom has always seemed to me like saying that
outlawing slavery reduces freedom, because it prevents some people
from owning slaves.</para>

<para>(Oh, and if you do get drawn into a debate about it, don't raise
the stakes by making inflammatory analogies.)</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="license-bsd">
<title>What About The BSD License?</title>

<para>A fair amount of open source software is distributed under
a <firstterm>BSD license</firstterm> (or sometimes
a <firstterm>BSD-style license</firstterm>).  The original BSD license
was used for the Berkeley Software Distribution, in which the
University of California released important portions of a Unix
implementation.  This license (the exact text may be seen in section
2.2.2 of
<ulink url="http://www.xfree86.org/3.3.6/COPYRIGHT2.html#6"/>) was
similar in spirit to the MIT/X license, except for one
clause:</para>

<blockquote>
<para><emphasis>All advertising materials mentioning features or use
of this software must display the following acknowledgement: This
product includes software developed by the University of California,
Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory.</emphasis></para>
</blockquote>

<para>The presence of that clause not only made the original BSD
license GPL-incompatible, it also set a dangerous precedent: as other
organizations put similar advertising clauses into
<emphasis>their</emphasis> free software&mdash;substituting their own
organization's name in place of "the University of California,
Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory"&mdash;software redistributors faced an
ever-increasing burden in what they were required to display.
Fortunately, many of the projects that used this license became aware
of the problem, and simply dropped the advertising clause.  In 1999,
even the University of California did so.</para>

<para>The result is the revised BSD license, which is simply the
original BSD license with the advertising clause removed.  However,
this history makes the phrase "BSD license" a bit ambiguous: does it
refer to the original, or the revised version?  This is why I prefer
the MIT/X license, which is essentially equivalent, and which does not
suffer from any ambiguity.  However, there is perhaps one reason to
prefer the revised BSD license to the MIT/X license, which is that the
BSD includes this clause:</para>

<blockquote>
<para><emphasis>Neither the name of the &lt;ORGANIZATION&gt; nor the
names of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products
derived from this software without specific prior written
permission.</emphasis></para>
</blockquote>

<para>It's not clear that without such a clause, a recipient of the
software would have had the right to use the licensor's name anyway,
but the clause removes any possible doubt.  For organizations worried
about trademark control, therefore, the revised BSD license may be
slightly preferable to MIT/X.  In general, however, a liberal
copyright license does not imply that recipients have any right to use
or dilute your trademarks &mdash; copyright law and trademark law are
two different beasts.</para>

<para>If you wish to use the revised BSD license, a template is
available at <ulink
url="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/bsd-license.php"/>.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="copyright-assignment">
<title>Copyright Assignment and Ownership</title>

<para>There are three ways to handle copyright ownership for free code
and documentation that were contributed to by many people.  The first
is to ignore the issue of copyright entirely (I don't recommend this).
The second is to collect a <firstterm>contributor license
agreement</firstterm> (<firstterm>CLA</firstterm>) from each person
who works on the project, explicitly granting the project the right to
use that person's contributions.  This is usually enough for most
projects, and the nice thing is that in some jurisdictions, CLAs can
be sent in by email.  The third way is to get actual copyright
assignments from contributors, so that the project (i.e., some legal
entity, usually a nonprofit) is the copyright owner for everything.
This is the most legally airtight way, but it's also the most
burdensome for contributors; only a few projects insist on it.</para>

<para>Note that even under centralized copyright ownership, the
code<footnote><para>I'll use "code" to refer to both code and
documentation, from now on.</para></footnote> remains free, because
open source licenses do not give the copyright holder the right to
retroactively proprietize all copies of the code.  So even if the
project, as a legal entity, were to suddenly turn around and started
distributing all the code under a restrictive license, that wouldn't
cause a problem for the public community.  The other developers would
simply start a fork based on the latest free copy of the code, and
continue as if nothing had happened.  Because they know they can do
this, most contributors cooperate when asked to sign a CLA or an
assignment of copyright.</para>

<sect2 id="copyright-assignment-none">
<title>Doing Nothing</title>

<para>Most projects never collect CLAs or copyright assignments from
their contributors.  Instead, they accept code whenever it seems
reasonably clear that the contributor intended it to be incorporated
into the project.</para>

<para>Under normal circumstances, this is okay.  But every now and
then, someone may decide to sue for copyright infringement, alleging
that they are the true owner of the code in question and that they
never agreed to its being distributed by the project under an open
source license.  For example, the SCO Group did something like this to
the Linux project, see
<ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SCO-Linux_controversies"/>
for details.  When this happens, the project will have no
documentation showing that the contributor formally granted the right
to use the code, which could make some legal defenses more
difficult.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="copyright-assignment-cla">
<title>Contributor License Agreements</title>

<para>CLAs probably offer the best tradeoff between safety and
convenience.  A CLA is typically an electronic form that a developer
fills out and sends in to the project.  In many jurisdictions, email
submission is enough.  A secure digital signature may or may not be
required; consult a lawyer to find out what method would be best for
your project.</para>

<para>Most projects use two slightly different CLAs, one for
individuals, and one for corporate contributors.  But in both types,
the core language is the same: the contributor grants the
project <emphasis>"...perpetual, worldwide, non-exclusive, no-charge,
royalty-free, irrevocable copyright license to reproduce, prepare
derivative works of, publicly display, publicly perform, sublicense,
and distribute [the] Contributions and such derivative
works."</emphasis> Again, you should have a lawyer approve any CLA,
but if you get all those adjectives into it, you're probably
fine.</para>

<para>When you request CLAs from contributors, make sure to emphasize
that you are <emphasis>not</emphasis> asking for actual copyright
assignment.  In fact, many CLAs start out by reminding the reader of
this:</para>

<blockquote>
<para><emphasis>This is a license agreement only; it does not transfer
copyright ownership and does not change your rights to use your own
Contributions for any other purpose.</emphasis></para>
</blockquote>

<para>Here are some examples:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>Individual contributor CLAs:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><ulink
        url="http://apache.org/licenses/icla.txt"/>
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink
        url="http://code.google.com/legal/individual-cla-v1.0.html"/>
      </para></listitem>
<!--  <listitem><para><ulink
 url="http://svn.collab.net/repos/svn-org/trunk/documents/individual-cla.txt"/>
      </para></listitem>  -->
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>Corporate contributor CLAs:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><ulink
        url="http://apache.org/licenses/cla-corporate.txt"/>
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink
        url="http://code.google.com/legal/corporate-cla-v1.0.html"/>
      </para></listitem>
<!--  <listitem><para><ulink
 url="http://svn.collab.net/repos/svn-org/trunk/documents/corporate-cla.txt"/>
      </para></listitem>  -->
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="copyright-assignment-transfer">
<title>Transfer of Copyright</title>

<para>Copyright transfer means that the contributor assigns to the
project copyright ownership on her contributions.  Ideally, this is
done on paper and either faxed or snail-mailed to the project.</para>

<para>Some projects insist on full assignment because having a single
legal entity own the copyright on the entire code base can be useful
if the terms of the open source license ever need to be enforced in
court.  If no single entity has the right to do it, all the
contributors might have to cooperate, but some might not have time or
even be reachable when the issue arises.</para>

<para>Different organizations apply different amounts of rigor to the
task of collecting assignments.  Some simply get an informal statement
from a contributor on a public list mailing list&mdash;something to
the effect of "I hereby assign copyright in this code to the project,
to be licensed under the same terms as the rest of the code."  At
least one lawyer I've talked to says that's really enough, presumably
because it happens in a context where copyright assignment is normal
and expected anyway, and because it represents a <foreignphrase>bona
fide</foreignphrase> effort on the project's part to ascertain the
developer's true intentions.  On the other hand, the Free Software
Foundation goes to the opposite extreme: they require contributors to
physically sign and mail in a piece of paper containing a formal
statement of copyright assignment, sometimes for just one
contribution, sometimes for current and future contributions.  If the
developer is employed, the FSF asks that the employer sign it
too.</para>

<para>The FSF's paranoia is understandable.  If someone violates the
terms of the GPL by incorporating some of their software into a
proprietary program, the FSF will need to fight that in court, and
they want their copyrights to be as airtight as possible when that
happens.  Since the FSF is copyright holder for a lot of popular
software, they view this as a real possibility.  Whether your
organization needs to be similarly scrupulous is something only you
can decide, in consultation with lawyers.  In general, unless there's
some specific reason why your project needs full copyright assignment,
just go with CLAs; they're easier for everyone.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="dual-licensing">
<title>Dual Licensing Schemes</title>

<para>Some projects try to fund themselves by using a dual licensing
scheme, in which proprietary derivative works may pay the copyright
holder for the right to use the code, but the code still remains free
for use by open source projects.  This tends to work better with code
libraries than with standalone applications, naturally.  The exact
terms differ from case to case.  Often the license for the free side
is the GNU GPL, since it already bars others from incorporating the
covered code into their proprietary product without permission from
the copyright holder, but sometimes it is a custom license that has
the same effect.  An example of the former is the MySQL license,
described at
<ulink url="http://www.mysql.com/company/legal/licensing/"/>; an
example of the latter is Sleepycat Software's licensing strategy,
described at
<ulink
url="http://www.sleepycat.com/download/licensinginfo.shtml"/>.</para>

<para>You might be wondering: how can the copyright holder offer
proprietary licensing for a mandatory fee if the terms of the GNU GPL
stipulate that the code must be available under less restrictive
terms?  The answer is that the GPL's terms are something the copyright
holder imposes on everyone else; the owner is therefore free to
decide <emphasis>not</emphasis> to apply those terms to itself.  A
good way to think of it is to imagine that the copyright owner has an
infinite number of copies of the software stored in a bucket.  Each
time it takes one out of the bucket to send into the world, it can
decide what license to put on it: GPL, proprietary, or something else.
Its right to do this is not tied to the GPL or any other open source
license; it is simply a power granted by copyright law.</para>

<para>The attractiveness of dual licensing is that, at its best, it
provides a way for a free software project to get a reliable income
stream.  Unfortunately, it can also interfere with the normal dynamics
of open source projects.  The problem is that any volunteer who makes
a code contribution is now contributing to two distinct entities: the
free version of the code and the proprietary version.  While the
contributor will be comfortable contributing to the free version,
since that's the norm in open source projects, she may feel funny
about contributing to someone else's semi-proprietary revenue stream.
The awkwardness is exacerbated by the fact that in dual licensing, the
copyright owner really needs to gather formal, signed copyright
assignments from all contributors, in order to protect itself from a
disgruntled contributor later claiming a percentage of royalties from
the proprietary stream.  The process of collecting these assignment
papers means that contributors are starkly confronted with the fact
that they are doing work that makes money for someone else.</para>

<para>Not all volunteers will be bothered by this; after all, their
contributions go into the open source edition as well, and that may be
where their main interest lies.  Nevertheless, dual licensing is an
instance of the copyright holder assigning itself a special right that
others in the project do not have, and is thus bound to raise
tensions at some point, at least with some volunteers.</para>

<para>What seems to happen in practice is that companies based on
dual licensed software do not have truly egalitarian development
communities.  They get small-scale bug fixes and cleanup patches from
external sources, but end up doing most of the hard work with internal
resources.  For example, Zack Urlocker, vice president of marketing at
MySQL, told me that the company generally ends up hiring the most
active volunteers anyway.  Thus, although the product itself is open
source, licensed under the GPL, its development is more or less
controlled by the company, albeit with the (extremely unlikely)
possibility that someone truly dissatisfied with the company's
handling of the software could fork the project.  To what degree this
threat pre&euml;mptively shapes the company's policies I don't know,
but at any rate, MySQL does not seem to be having acceptance problems
either in the open source world or beyond.</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="patents">
<title>Patents</title>

<para>Software patents are the lightning rod issue of the moment in
free software, because they pose the only real threat against which
the free software community cannot defend itself.  Copyright and
trademark problems can always be gotten around.  If part of your code
looks like it may infringe on someone else's copyright, you can just
rewrite that part.  If it turns out someone has a trademark on your
project's name, at the very worst you can just rename the project.
Although changing names would be a temporary inconvenience, it
wouldn't matter in the long run, since the code itself would still do
what it always did.</para>

<para>But a patent is a blanket injunction against implementing a
certain idea.  It doesn't matter who writes the code, nor even what
programming language is used.  Once someone has accused a free
software project of infringing a patent, the project must either stop
implementing that particular feature, or face an expensive and
time-consuming lawsuit.  Since the instigators of such lawsuits are
usually corporations with deep pockets&mdash;that's who has the
resources and inclination to acquire patents in the first
place&mdash;most free software projects cannot afford the latter
possibility, and must capitulate immediately even if they think it
highly likely that the patent would be unenforceable in court.  To
avoid getting into such a situation in the first place, free software
projects are starting to code defensively, avoiding patented
algorithms in advance even when they are the best or only available
solution to a programming problem.<footnote><para>Sun Microsystems and
IBM have also made at least a gesture at the problem from the other
direction, by freeing large numbers of software patents&mdash;1600 and
500 respectively&mdash;for use by the open source community.  I am not
a lawyer and thus can't evaluate the real utility of these grants, but
even if they are all important patents, and the terms of the grants
make them truly free for use by any open source project, it would
still be only a drop in the bucket.</para></footnote></para>

<para>Surveys and anecdotal evidence show that not only the vast
majority of open source programmers, but a majority
of <emphasis>all</emphasis> programmers, think that software patents
should be abolished entirely.<footnote><para>See
<ulink url="http://lpf.ai.mit.edu/Whatsnew/survey.html"/> for one such
survey.</para></footnote> Open source programmers tend to feel
particularly strongly about it, and may refuse to work on projects
that are too closely associated with the collection or enforcement of
software patents.  If your organization collects software patents,
then make it clear, in a public and irrevocable way, that the patents
would never be enforced on open source projects, and that they are
only to be used as a defense in case some other party initiates an
infringement suit against your organization.  This is not only the
right thing to do, it's also good open source public relations.<footnote>
<para>For example, RedHat has pledged that open source projects are
safe from its patents, see
<ulink url="http://www.redhat.com/legal/patent_policy.html"/>.</para>
</footnote></para>

<para>Unfortunately, collecting patents for defensive purposes is a
rational action.  The current patent system, at least in the United
States, is by its nature an arms race: if your competitors have
acquired a lot of patents, then your best defense is to acquire a lot
of patents yourself, so that if you're ever hit with a patent
infringement suit you can respond with a similar threat&mdash;then the
two parties usually sit down and work out a cross-licensing deal so
that neither of them has to pay anything, except to their intellectual
property lawyers of course.</para>

<para>The harm done to free software by software patents is more
insidious than just direct threats to code development, however.
Software patents encourage an atmosphere of secrecy among firmware
designers, who justifiably worry that by publishing details of their
interfaces they will be giving technical help to competitors seeking
to slap them with patent infringement suits.  This is not just a
theoretical danger; it has apparently been happening for a long time
in the video card industry, for example.  Many video card
manufacturers are reluctant to release the detailed programming
specifications needed to produce high-performance open source drivers
for their cards, thus making it impossible for free operating systems
to support those cards to their full potential.  Why would the
manufacturers do this?  It doesn't make sense for them to
work <emphasis>against</emphasis> software support; after all,
compatibility with more operating systems can only mean more card
sales.  But it turns out that, behind the design room door, these
shops are all violating one another's patents, sometimes knowingly and
sometimes accidentally.  The patents are so unpredictable and so
potentially broad that no card manufacturer can ever be certain it's
safe, even after doing a patent search.  Thus, manufacturers dare not
publish their full interface specifications, since that would make it
much easier for competitors to figure out whether any patents are
being infringed.  (Of course, the nature of this situation is such
that you will not find a written admission from a primary source that
it is going on; I learned it through a personal communication.)</para>

<para>Some free software licenses have special clauses to combat, or at
least discourage, software patents.  The GNU GPL, for example, contains
this language:</para>

<screen>
  7. If, as a consequence of a court judgment or allegation of patent
infringement or for any other reason (not limited to patent issues),
conditions are imposed on you (whether by court order, agreement or
otherwise) that contradict the conditions of this License, they do not
excuse you from the conditions of this License.  If you cannot
distribute so as to satisfy simultaneously your obligations under this
License and any other pertinent obligations, then as a consequence you
may not distribute the Program at all.  For example, if a patent
license would not permit royalty-free redistribution of the Program by
all those who receive copies directly or indirectly through you, then
the only way you could satisfy both it and this License would be to
refrain entirely from distribution of the Program.

[...]

It is not the purpose of this section to induce you to infringe any
patents or other property right claims or to contest validity of any
such claims; this section has the sole purpose of protecting the
integrity of the free software distribution system, which is
implemented by public license practices.  Many people have made
generous contributions to the wide range of software distributed
through that system in reliance on consistent application of that
system; it is up to the author/donor to decide if he or she is willing
to distribute software through any other system and a licensee cannot
impose that choice.
</screen>

<para>The Apache License, Version 2.0
(<ulink url="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0"/>) also
contains anti-patent requirements.  First, it stipulates that anyone
distributing code under the license must implicitly include a
royalty-free patent license for any patents they might hold that could
apply to the code.  Second, and most ingeniously, it punishes anyone
who initiates a patent infringement claim on the covered work, by
automatically terminating their implicit patent license the moment
such a claim is made:</para>

<screen>
3. Grant of Patent License. Subject to the terms and conditions of
this License, each Contributor hereby grants to You a perpetual,
worldwide, non-exclusive, no-charge, royalty-free, irrevocable (except
as stated in this section) patent license to make, have made, use,
offer to sell, sell, import, and otherwise transfer the Work, where
such license applies only to those patent claims licensable by such
Contributor that are necessarily infringed by their Contribution(s)
alone or by combination of their Contribution(s) with the Work to
which such Contribution(s) was submitted. If You institute patent
litigation against any entity (including a cross-claim or counterclaim
in a lawsuit) alleging that the Work or a Contribution incorporated
within the Work constitutes direct or contributory patent
infringement, then any patent licenses granted to You under this
License for that Work shall terminate as of the date such litigation
is filed.
</screen>

<para>Although it is useful, both legally and politically, to build
patent defenses into free software licenses this way, in the end these
steps will not be enough to dispel the chilling effect that the threat
of patent lawsuits has on free software.  Only changes in the
substance or interpretation of international patent law will do that.
To learn more about the problem, and how it's being fought, go to
<ulink url="http://www.nosoftwarepatents.com/"/>.  The Wikipedia
article <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_patent"/>
also has a lot of useful information on software patents.  I've also
written a blog post summarizing the arguments against software
patents, at
<ulink url="http://www.rants.org/2007/05/01/how-to-tell-that-software-patents-are-a-bad-idea/"/>.</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="licensing-further-resources">
<title>Further Resources</title>

<para>This chapter has only been an introduction to free software
licensing issues.  Although I hope it contains enough information to
get you started on your own open source project, any serious
investigation of licensing issues will quickly exhaust what this book
can provide.  Here is a list of further resources on open source
licensing:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para><citetitle>Understanding Open Source and Free
            Software Licensing</citetitle> by Andrew M. St. Laurent.
            Published by O'Reilly Media, first edition August 2004,
            ISBN:&nbsp;0-596-00581-4.</para>

            <para>This is a full-length book on open source licensing
            in all its complexity, including many topics omitted from
            this chapter.  See
            <ulink url="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/osfreesoft/"/>
            for details.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para><citetitle>Make Your Open Source Software
            GPL-Compatible.  Or Else.</citetitle> by David
            A. Wheeler, at
            <ulink
            url="http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/gpl-compatible.html"/>.</para>

            <para>This is a detailed and well-written article on why
            it is important to use a GPL-compatible license even if
            you don't use the GPL itself.  The article also touches on
            many other licensing questions, and has a high density of
            excellent links.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para><ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/"/></para>

            <para>Creative Commons is an organization that promotes a
            range of more flexible and liberal copyrights than
            traditional copyright practice encourages.  They offer
            licenses not just for software, but for text, art, and
            music as well, all accessible via a user-friendly license
            selector; some of the licenses are copylefts, some are
            non-copyleft but still free, others are simply traditional
            copyrights but with some restrictions relaxed.  The
            Creative Commons web site gives extremely clear
            explanations of what it's about.  If I had to pick one
            site to demonstrate the broader philosophical implications
            of the free software movement, this would be it.</para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->

