<chapter id="technical-infrastructure">

<title>Technical Infrastructure</title>

<simplesect>

<para>Free software projects rely on technologies that support the
selective capture and integration of information.  The more skilled
you are at using these technologies, and at persuading others to use
them, the more successful your project will be.</para>

<para>This only becomes
more true as the project grows.  Good information management is what
prevents open source projects from collapsing under the weight of
Brooks' Law<footnote><para>From his book <citetitle>The Mythical Man
Month</citetitle>, 1975.  See <ulink
url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Mythical_Man-Month"
>en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Mythical_Man-Month</ulink>, <ulink
url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brooks_Law"
>en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brooks_Law</ulink>, and
<ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fred_Brooks"
>en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fred_Brooks</ulink>.</para></footnote>,
which states that adding manpower to a late software project makes it
later.  Fred Brooks observed that the complexity of communications in
a project
increases as the <emphasis>square</emphasis> of the number of
participants.  When only a few people are involved, everyone can easily
talk to everyone else, but when hundreds of people are involved, it is
no longer possible for each person to remain constantly aware of what
everyone else is doing.  If good free software project management is
about making everyone feel like they're all working together in the
same room, the obvious question is: what happens when everyone in a
crowded room tries to talk at once?</para>

<para>This problem is not new.  In non-metaphorical crowded rooms, the
solution is <firstterm>parliamentary procedure</firstterm>: formal
guidelines for how to have real-time discussions in large groups, how
to make sure important dissents are not lost in floods of "me-too"
comments, how to form subcommittees, how to recognize and record when
decisions
are made, etc.  An important part of parliamentary procedure is
specifying how the group interacts with its information management
system.  Some remarks are made "for the record", others are not.  The
record itself is subject to direct manipulation, and is understood to
be not a literal transcript of what occurred, but a representation of
what the group is willing to <emphasis>agree</emphasis> occurred.  The
record is not monolithic, but takes different forms for different
purposes.  It comprises the minutes of individual meetings, the
complete collection of all minutes of all meetings, summaries, agendas
and their annotations, committee reports, reports from correspondents
not present, lists of action items, etc.</para>

<para>Because the Internet is not really a room, we don't have to
worry about replicating those parts of parliamentary procedure that
keep some people quiet while others are speaking.  But when it comes
to information management techniques, well-run open source projects
are parliamentary procedure on steroids.  Since almost all
communication in open source projects happens in writing, elaborate
systems have evolved for routing and labeling data appropriately, for
minimizing repetitions so as to avoid spurious divergences, for
storing and retrieving data, for correcting bad or obsolete
information, and for associating disparate bits of information with
each other as new connections are observed.  Active participants in
open source projects internalize many of these techniques, and will
often perform complex manual tasks to ensure that information is
routed correctly.  But the whole endeavor ultimately depends on
sophisticated software support.  As much as possible, the
communications media themselves should do the routing, labeling, and
recording, and should make the information available to humans in the
most convenient way possible.  In practice, of course, humans will
still need to intervene at many points in the process, and it's
important that the software make such interventions convenient too.
But in general, if the humans take care to label and route information
accurately on its first entry into the system, then the software
should be configured to make as much use of that metadata as
possible.</para>

<para>The advice in this chapter is intensely practical, based on
experiences with specific software and usage patterns.  But the point
is not just to teach a particular collection of techniques.  It is
also to demonstrate, by means of many small examples, the overall
attitude that will best encourage good information management in your
project.  This attitude will involve a combination of technical skills
and people skills.  The technical skills are essential because
information management software always requires configuration, plus a
certain amount of ongoing maintenance and tweaking as new needs arise
(for example, see the discussion of how to handle project growth in
<xref linkend="bug-filtering"/><phrase output="printed"> later in
this chapter</phrase>).  The people skills are necessary
because the human community also requires maintenance: it's not always
immediately obvious how to use these tools to full advantage, and in
some cases projects have conflicting conventions (for example, see the
discussion of setting <systemitem>Reply-to</systemitem> headers on
outgoing mailing list posts, in <xref linkend="message-forums"/>).
Everyone involved with the project will need to be encouraged, at the
right times and in the right ways, to do their part to keep the
project's information well organized.  The more involved the
contributor, the more complex and specialized the techniques she can
be expected to learn.</para>

<para>Information management has no cut-and-dried solution.  There are
too many variables.  You may finally get everything configured just
the way you want it, and have most of the community participating, but
then project growth will make some of those practices unscalable.  Or
project growth may stabilize, and the developer and user communities
settle into a comfortable relationship with the technical
infrastructure, but then someone will come along and invent a whole
new information management service, and pretty soon newcomers will be
asking why your project doesn't use it&mdash;for example, this
happened to a lot of free software projects that predate the invention
of the wiki (see <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wiki"
>en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wiki</ulink>), and more recently has been
happening to projects whose workflows were developed before the rise
of GitHub PRs (see <xref linkend="pull-requests"/>) as the canonical
way to package proposed contributions.  Many infrastructure questions
are matters of judgement, involving tradeoffs between the convenience
of those producing information and the convenience of those consuming
it, or between the time required to configure information management
software and the benefit it brings to the project.</para>

<para>Beware of the temptation to over-automate, that is, to automate
things that really require human attention.  Technical infrastructure
is important, but what makes a free software project work is
care&mdash;and intelligent expression of that care&mdash;by the humans
involved.  The technical infrastructure is mainly about giving humans
easy ways to apply care.</para>

</simplesect>


<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="tools-needed">
<title>What a Project Needs</title>

<para>Most open source projects offer at least a minimum, standard set
of tools for managing information:</para>

<variablelist>

   <varlistentry><term>Web site</term>
     <listitem>
     <para>Primarily a centralized, one-way conduit of
           information from the project out to the public.  The web
           site may also serve as an administrative interface for
           other project tools.</para>
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry><term>Mailing lists / Message forums</term>
     <listitem>
       <para>Usually the most active communications forum in the
             project, and the "medium of record."</para>
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry><term>Version control</term>
     <listitem>
       <para>Enables developers to manage code changes conveniently,
             including reverting and "change porting".  Enables
             everyone to watch what's happening to the code.</para>
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry><term>Bug tracking</term>
     <listitem>
       <para>Enables developers to keep track of what they're working
             on, coordinate with each other, and plan releases.  Enables
             everyone to query the status of bugs and record
             information (e.g., reproduction recipes) about particular
             bugs.  Can be used for tracking not only bugs, but also
             tasks, releases, new features, etc.</para>
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry><term>Real-time chat</term>
     <listitem>
       <para>A place for quick, lightweight discussions and
             question/answer exchanges.  Not always archived
             completely.</para>
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

<!-- TODO: Add blogs/planets to this list?  At least mention them
     later in the chapter. -->

<!-- TODO: What about Q&A software like OSQA and other things
     similar to Stack Exchange?  Worth mentioning.  See:

     http://projects.opensource.org/cgi-bin/mailman/private/infrastructure/2014-January/thread.html#1586

     (Thread "Q&A-style software for eventual qa.opensource.org site."
     on OSI infrastructure@ list.)
-->

</variablelist>

<para>Each tool in this set addresses a distinct need, but their functions
are also interrelated, and the tools must be made to work together.
Below we will examine how they can do so, and more importantly, how to
get people to use them.</para>

<para>You may be able to avoid a lot of the headache of choosing and
configuring many of these tools by using a <firstterm>canned
hosting</firstterm> site: an online service that offers prepackaged,
templatized web services with some or all of the collaboration tools
needed to run a free software project.  See
<xref linkend="canned-hosting"/><phrase output="printed"> later
in this chapter</phrase> for a discussion of the advantages and
disadvantages of canned hosting.</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="web-site">
<title>Web Site</title>

<para><emphasis>possv2 24 March 2013: If you're reading this note, then
you've encountered this chapter while it's undergoing substantial
revision; see <ulink url="http://producingoss.com/v2.html"
>producingoss.com/v2.html</ulink> for details.</emphasis></para>

<para>For our purposes, <emphasis>the web site</emphasis> means web
pages devoted to helping people participate in the project as
developers, documenters, etc.  Note that this is different from the
main user-facing web site.  In many projects, users have different
needs and often (statistically speaking) a different mentality from
the developers.  The kinds of web pages most helpful to users are not
necessarily the same as those helpful for
developers&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;don't try to make a "one size fits all"
web site just to save some writing and maintenance effort: you'll end
up with a site that is not quite right for either audience.</para>

<para>The two types of sites should cross-link, of course, and in
particular it's important that the user-oriented site have, tucked a
way in a corner somewhere, a clear link to the developers' site, since
most new developers will start out at the user-facing pages and look
for a path from there to the developers' area.</para>

<para>An example may make this clearer.  As of this writing in
November 2013, the office suite LibreOffice has its main user-oriented
web site at <ulink url="https://libreoffice.org/"
>libreoffice.org</ulink>, as you'd expect.  If you were a user wanting
to download and install LibreOffice, you'd start there, go straight to
the "Download" link, and so on.  But if you were a developer looking
to (say) fix a bug in LibreOffice, you might
<emphasis>start</emphasis> at <ulink url="https://libreoffice.org/"
>libreoffice.org</ulink>, but you'd be looking for a link that says
something like "Developers", or "Development", or "Get
Involved"&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;in other words, you'd be looking for the
gateway to the development area.</para>

<para>In the case of LibreOffice, as with some other large projects,
they actually have a couple of different gateways.  There's one link
that says <ulink url="https://www.libreoffice.org/get-involved/"
>"Get&nbsp;Involved"</ulink>, and another that says <ulink
url="https://www.libreoffice.org/developers/" >"Developers"</ulink>.
The "Get Involved" page is aimed at the broadest possible range of
potential contributors: developers, yes, but also documenters,
quality-assurance testers, marketing volunteers, web infrastructure
volunteers, financial or in-kind donors, interface designers, support
forum volunteers, etc.  This frees up the "Developers" page to target
the rather narrower audience of programmers who want to get involved
in improving the LibreOffice code.  The set of links and short
descriptions provided on both pages is admirably clear and concise:
you can tell immediately from looking whether you're in the right
place for what you want do, and if so what the next thing to click on
is.  The "Development" page gives some information about where to find
the code, how to contact the other developers, how to file bugs, and
things like that, but most importantly it points to what most seasoned
open source contributors would instantly recognize as the
<emphasis>real</emphasis> gateway to actively-maintained development
information: the development wiki at <ulink
url="http://wiki.documentfoundation.org/Development"
>wiki.documentfoundation.org/Development</ulink>.</para>

<para>This division into two contributor-facing gateways, one for all
kinds of contributions and another for coders specifically, is
probably right for a large, multi-faceted project like LibreOffice.
You'll have to use your judgement as to whether that kind of
subdivision is appropriate for your project; at least at the
beginning, it probably isn't.  It's better to start with one unified
contributor gateway, aimed at all the types of contributors you
expect, and if that page ever gets large enough or complex enough to
feel unwieldy&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;listen carefully for complaints about
it, since you and other long-time participants will be naturally
desensitized to weaknesses in introductory
pages!&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;then you can divide it up however seems
best.</para>

<para>From a technical point of view there is not much to say about
setting up the project web site.  Configuring a web server and writing
web pages are fairly simple tasks, and most of the important things to
say about layout and arrangement were covered in the previous chapter.
The web site's main function is to present a clear and welcoming
overview of the project, and to bind together the other tools (the
version control system, bug tracker, etc.).  If you don't have the
expertise to set up a web server yourself, it's usually not hard to
find someone who does and is willing to help out.  Nonetheless, to
save time and effort, people often prefer to use one of the canned
hosting sites.</para>

<sect2 id="canned-hosting">
<title>Canned Hosting</title>

<para>A <firstterm>canned hosting</firstterm> site is an online
service that offers some or all of the online collaboration tools
needed to run a free software project.  At a minimal, a canned hosting
site offers public version control repositories and bug tracking; most
also offer wiki space, many offer mailing list hosting too, and some
offer continuous integration testing and other services.</para>

<!-- possv2 todo: link to 'fund-servers' in Chapter 5, re the mention
     of continuous integration above?  Should one be firstterm? -->

<para>There are two main advantages to using a canned site.  The first
is server capacity and bandwidth: their servers are beefy boxes
sitting on really fat pipes.  No matter how successful your project
gets, you're not going to run out of disk space or swamp the network
connection.  The second advantage is simplicity.  They have already
chosen a bug tracker, a version control system, perhaps discussion
forum software, and everything else you need to run a project.
They've configured the tools, arranged single-sign-on authentication
where appropriate, are taking care of backups for all the data stored
in the tools, etc.  You don't need to make many decisions.  All you
have to do is fill in a registration form, press a button, and
suddenly you've got a project development web site.</para>

<para>These are pretty significant benefits.  The disadvantage, of
course, is that you must accept <emphasis>their</emphasis> choices and
configurations, even if something different would be better for your
project.  Usually canned sites are adjustable within certain narrow
parameters, but you will never get the fine-grained control you would
have if you set up the site yourself and had full administrative
access to the server.</para>

<para>A perfect example of this is the handling of generated files.
Certain project web pages may be generated files&mdash;for example,
there are systems for keeping FAQ data in an easy-to-edit master
format, from which HTML, PDF, and other presentation formats can be
generated.  As explained in
<xref linkend="version-everything"/><phrase output="printed">
earlier in this chapter</phrase>,
you wouldn't want to version the generated formats, only the master
file.  But when your web site is hosted on someone else's server, it
may be difficult to set up a custom hook to regenerate the online
HTML version of the FAQ whenever the master file is changed.</para>

<para>If you choose a canned site, leave open the option of switching
to a different site later, by using a custom domain name as the
project's development home address.  You can forward that URL to the
canned site, or have a fully customized development home page at the
main URL and link to the canned site for specific functionality.  Just
try to arrange things such that if you later decide to use a different
hosting solution, the project's main address doesn't need to
change.</para>

<para>And if you're not sure whether to use canned hosting, then you
should probably use canned hosting.  These sites have integrated their
services in myriad ways (just one example: if a commit mentions a bug
ticket number using a certain format, then people browsing that commit
later will find that it automatically links to that ticket), ways that
would be laborious for you to reproduce, especially if it's your first
time running an open source project.  The universe of possible
configurations of collaboration tools is vast and complex, but the
same set of choices has faced everyone running an open source project
and there are some settled solutions now.  Each of the canned hosting
sites implements a reasonable subset of that solution space, and
unless you have reason to believe you can do better, your project will
probably run best just using one of those sites.</para>

<sect3 id="canned-hosting-choosing">
<title>Choosing a canned hosting site</title>

<para>There are now so many sites providing free-of-charge canned
hosting for projects released under open source licenses that there is
not space here to review the field.</para>

<para>So I'll make this easy: choose <a href="http://github.com/"
>GitHub</a>.  It's by far the most popular and appears set to stay
that way, or even grow in dominance, for some years to come.  It has a
good set of features and integrations.  Many developers are already
familiar with GitHub and have an account there.  It has an <ulink
url="http://develop.github.com/" >API</ulink> for interacting
programmatically with project resources, and while it does not
currently offer mailing lists, there are plenty of other places you
can host those, such as <ulink url="http://groups.google.com/" >Google
Groups</ulink>.</para>

<para>If you're not convinced by GitHub (for example because your
project uses, say, Mercurial instead of Git), but you aren't sure
where to host, take a look at Wikipedia's thorough <ulink
url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comparison_of_open_source_software_hosting_facilities"
>comparison of open source software hosting facilities</ulink>; it's
the first place to look for up-to-date, comprehensive information on
open source project hosting options.  Currently the two most popular
other hosting sites are <ulink url="http://code.google.com/hosting/"
>Google Code Hosting</ulink>, <ulink url="http://sourceforge.net/"
>SourceForge</ulink>, but consult the Wikipedia page before making a
decision.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="hosting-on-freedom">
<title>Hosting on fully open source infrastructure</title>

<para>Although all the canned hosting sites use plenty of free
software in their stack, most of them also wrote their own proprietary
software to glue it all together, which means the hosting environment
is not easily reproducible by others.  For example, while Git itself
is free software, GitHub is a hosted service running partly with
proprietary software&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;if you leave GitHub, you can't
take it with you, at least not all of it.</para>

<para>Some projects prefer a canned hosting site that runs an entirely
free software infrastructure and that could, in theory, be reproduced
independently were that ever to become necessary.  Fortunately, there
are such sites, the most well-known being <ulink
url="http://gitorious.org/" >Gitorious</ulink>, <ulink
url="http://savannah.gnu.org/" >GNU Savannah</ulink>, and <ulink
url="http://gitlab.com/" >GitLab</ulink> (as of this writing in early
2014).  Furthermore, any service that offers hosting of the <ulink
url="http://redmine.org/" >Redmine</ulink> or <ulink
url="http://trac.edgewall.org" >Trac</ulink> code collaboration
platforms effectively offers fully freedom-preserving project hosting,
because those platforms include most of the features needed to run an
open source project; some companies offer that kind of commercial
platform hosting with a zero-cost or very cheap rate for open source
projects.</para>

<para>Should you host your project on fully open source
infrastructure?  While it would be ideal to have access to all the
code that runs the site, my opinion is that the crucial thing is to
have a way to export project data, and to be able to interact with the
data in automatable ways.  A site that meets these criteria can never
truly lock you in, and will even be extensible, to some degree,
through its programmatic interface.  While there is some value in
having all the code that runs a hosting site available under open
source terms, in practice the demands of actually deploying that code
in a production environment are prohibitive for most projects anyway.
These sites need multiple servers, customized networks, and full-time
staffs to keep them running; merely having the code would not be
sufficient to duplicate or "fork" the service anyway.  The main thing
is just to make sure your data isn't trapped.</para>

<para>Of course, all the above applies only to the servers.  Your
project should never require participants to run proprietary
collaboration software on their own machines.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="anonymity">
<title>Anonymity and involvement</title>

<para>A problem that is not strictly limited to the canned sites, but
is most often found there, is the over-requirement of user
registration to participate in various aspects of the project.  The
proper degree of requirement is a bit of a judgement call.  User
registration helps prevent spam, for one thing, and even if every
commit gets reviewed you still probably don't want anonymous strangers
pushing changes into your repository, for example.</para>

<para>But sometimes user registration ends up being required for tasks
that ought to be permitted to unregistered visitors, especially the
ability to file tickets in the bug tracker, and to comment on existing
tickets.  By requiring a logged-in username for such actions, the
project raises the involvement bar for what should be quick,
convenient tasks.  It also changes the demographics of who files bugs,
since those who take the trouble to set up a user account at the
project site are hardly a random sample even from among users who are
willing to file bugs (who in turn are already a biased subset of all
the project's users).  Of course, one wants to be able to contact
someone who's entered data into the ticket tracker, but having a field
where she can enter her email address (if she wants to) is sufficient.
If a new user spots a bug and wants to report it, she'll only be
annoyed at having to fill out an account creation form before she can
enter the bug into the tracker.  She may simply decide not to file the
bug at all.</para>

<para>If you have control over which actions can be done anonymously,
make sure that at least <emphasis>all</emphasis> read-only actions are
permitted to non-logged-in visitors, and if possible that data entry
portals, such as the bug tracker, that tend to bring information from
users to developers, can also be used anonymously, although of course
anti-spam techniques, such as captchas, may still be necessary.</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ========================== SECTION =========================== -->
<sect1 id="message-forums">
<!-- For link compatibility with the old section ID. -->
<anchor id="mailing-lists" />
<title>Mailing Lists / Message Forums</title>

<para>Discussion forums in which participants post and respond to
messages are the bread and butter of project communications.  For a
long time these were mainly email-based discussion lists, but the
distinction between Web-based forums and mailing lists is, thankfully,
slowly disappearing.  Services like <ulink
url="https://groups.google.com/" >Google Groups</ulink> (which is not
itself open source) and <ulink url="http://Gmane.org/"
>Gmane.org</ulink> (which is) have now established that
cross-accessibility of message forums as mailing lists and vice versa
is the minimum bar to meet, and modern discussion management systems
like GroupServer and Sympa reflect this.</para>

<para>Because of this nearly-completed unification between email lists
and web-based forums<footnote><para>Which was a long time
coming&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;see <ulink
url="http://www.rants.org/2008/03/06/thread_theory/"
>rants.org/2008/03/06/thread_theory</ulink> for more.  And no, I'm not
too dignified to refer to my own blog post.</para></footnote>, I will
use the terms <firstterm>message&nbsp;forum</firstterm> and
<firstterm>mailing&nbsp;list</firstterm> more or less interchangeably.
They refer to any kind of message-based forum where posts are linked
together in threads (topics), people can subscribe, archives of past
messages can be browsed, and the forum can be interacted with via
email or via a web browser.</para>

<para>If a user is exposed to any channel besides a project's web
pages, it is most likely to be one of the project's message forums.
But before she experiences the forum itself, she will experience the
process of finding the right forums.  Your project should
have a prominently-placed description of all the available public
forums, to give newcomers guidance in deciding which ones to browse or
post to first.  A typical such description might say something like
this:</para>

<screen>
  The mailing lists are the main day-to-day communication channels for
  the Scanley community.  You don't have to be subscribed to post to a
  list, but if it's your first time posting (whether you're subscribed
  or not), your message may be held in a moderation queue until a
  human moderator has a chance to confirm that the message is not spam.
  We're sorry for this delay; blame the spammers who make it necessary.

  Scanley has the following lists:

  <emphasis role="bold"><literal>users&nbsp;{_AT_}&nbsp;scanley.org</literal></emphasis>:
    Discussion about using Scanley or programming with the Scanley
    API, suggestions of possible improvements, etc.  You can browse the
    users@ archives at <emphasis role="bold">&lt;&lt;&lt;link to archive&gt;&gt;&gt;</emphasis> or subscribe here:
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;&lt;&lt;link to subscribe&gt;&gt;&gt;</emphasis>.

  <emphasis role="bold"><literal>dev&nbsp;{_AT_}&nbsp;scanley.org</literal></emphasis>:
    Discussion about developing Scanley.  Maintainers and contributors
    are subscribed to this list.  You can browse the dev@ archives at
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;&lt;&lt;link to archive&gt;&gt;&gt;</emphasis> or subscribe here: <emphasis role="bold">&lt;&lt;&lt;link to subscribe&gt;&gt;&gt;</emphasis>.

    (Sometimes threads cross over between users@ and dev@, and
    Scanley's developers will often participate in discussions on both
    lists.  In general if you're unsure where a question or post
    should go, start it out on <literal>users@</literal>.  If it should be a
    development discussion, someone will suggest moving it over to
    <literal>dev@</literal>.)

  <emphasis role="bold"><literal>announcements&nbsp;{_AT_}&nbsp;scanley.org</literal></emphasis>:
    This is a low-traffic, subscribe-only list.  The Scanley
    developers post announcements of new releases and occasional other
    news items of interest to the entire Scanley community here, but
    followup discussion takes place on users@ or dev@.
    <emphasis role="bold">&lt;&lt;&lt;link to subscribe&gt;&gt;&gt;</emphasis>.

  <emphasis role="bold"><literal>notifications&nbsp;{_AT_}&nbsp;scanley.org</literal></emphasis>:
    All code commit messages, bug tracker tickets, automated
    build/integration failures, etc, are sent to this list.  Most
    developers should subscribe: <emphasis role="bold">&lt;&lt;&lt;link to subscribe&gt;&gt;&gt;</emphasis>.

  There is also a non-public list you may need to send to, although
  only developers are subscribed:

  <emphasis role="bold"><literal>security&nbsp;{_AT_}&nbsp;scanley.org</literal></emphasis>:
    Where the Scanley project receives confidential reports of
    security vulnerabilities.  Of course, the report will be made
    public eventually, but only after a fix is released; see our
    security procedures page for more [...]
</screen>

<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="message-forum-choosing">
<title>Choosing the Right Forum Management Software</title>

<para>It's worth investing some time in choosing the right mailing
list management system for your project.  Modern list management tools
offer at least the following features:</para>

<variablelist>

  <varlistentry><term>Both email- and web-based access</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Users should be able to subscribe to the forums by email,
            and read them on the web (where they are organized into
            conversations or "threads", just as they would be in a
            mailreader).</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Moderation features</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>To "moderate" is to check posts, especially first-time
            posts, to make sure they are not spam before they go out
            to the entire list.  Moderation necessarily involves
            human administrators, but software can do a great deal to
            make it easier on the moderators.  There is more said
            about moderation in <xref linkend="spam-prevention"/>
            later in this chapter.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Rich administrative interface</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>There are many things administrators need to do besides
            spam moderation&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;for example, removing
            obsolete addresses, a task that can become urgent when a
            recipient's address starts sending "I am no longer at this
            address" bounces back to the list in response to every
            list post (though some systems can even detect this and
            unsubscribe the person automatically).  If your forum
            software doesn't have decent administrative capabilities,
            you will quickly realize it, and should consider switching
            to software that does.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Header manipulation</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Some people have sophisticated filtering and replying
            rules set up in their mail readers, and rely on the forum
            adding or manipulating certain standard headers.  See 
            <xref linkend="header-management"/> later in this chapter
            for more on this.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Archiving</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>All posts to the managed lists are stored and made
            available on the web (see <xref
            linkend="using-archives"/><phrase output="printed"> in
            <xref linkend="communications"/></phrase> for more on the
            importance of public archives).  Usually the archiver is a
            native part of the message forum system; occasionally, it
            is a separate tool that needs to be integrated.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

</variablelist>

<para>The point of the above list is really just to show that forum
management is a complex problem that has already been given a lot of
thought, and to some degree been solved.  You don't need to become an
expert, but you will have to learn at least a little bit about
it, and you should expect list management to occupy your attention
from time to time in the course of running any free software project.
Below we'll examine a few of the most common issues.</para>

<sect3 id="spam-prevention">
<title>Spam Prevention</title>

<para>Between when this sentence is written and when it is published,
the Internet-wide spam problem will probably double in
severity&mdash;or at least it will feel that way.  There was a time,
not so long ago, when one could run a mailing list without taking any
spam-prevention measures at all.  The occasional stray post would
still show up, but infrequently enough to be only a low-level
annoyance.  That era is gone forever.  Today, a mailing list that
takes no spam prevention measures will quickly be submerged in junk
emails, to the point of unusability.  Spam prevention is
mandatory.</para>

<para>We divide spam prevention into two categories: preventing spam
posts from appearing on your mailing lists, and preventing your
mailing list from being a source of new email addresses for spammers'
harvesters.  The former is more important to your project, so we
examine it first.</para>

<sect4 id="spam-filtering">
<title>Filtering posts</title>

<para>There are three basic techniques for preventing spam posts, and
most mailing list software offers all three.  They are best used in
tandem:</para>

<orderedlist>

  <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Only auto-allow postings from
            list subscribers.</emphasis></para>

            <para>This is effective as far as it goes, and also
            involves very little administrative overhead, since it's
            usually just a matter of changing a setting in the mailing
            list software's configuration.  But note that posts which
            aren't automatically approved must not be simply
            discarded.  Instead, they should go into a moderation
            queue, for two reasons.  First, you want to allow
            non-subscribers to post: a person with a question or
            suggestion should not need to subscribe to a mailing list
            just to ask a question there.  Second, even
            subscribers may sometimes post from an address other than
            the one by which they're subscribed.  Email addresses are
            not a reliable method of identifying people, and shouldn't
            be treated as such.</para>
            </listitem>

  <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Filter posts through
            spam-detection software.</emphasis></para>

            <para>If the mailing list software makes it possible (most
            do), you can have posts filtered by spam-filtering
            software.  Automatic spam-filtering is not perfect, and
            never will be, since there is a never-ending arms race
            between spammers and filter writers.  However, it can
            greatly reduce the amount of spam that makes it through to the
            moderation queue, and since the longer that queue is the
            more time humans must spend examining it, any amount of
            automated filtering is beneficial.</para>

            <para>There is not space here for detailed instructions
            on setting up spam filters.  You will have to consult
            your mailing list software's documentation for that (see
            <xref
            linkend="mailing-list-software"/><phrase
            output="printed"> later in this chapter</phrase>).  List
            software often comes with some built-in spam prevention
            features, but you may want to add some third-party
            filters.  I've had good experiences with SpamAssassin
            (<ulink url="http://spamassassin.apache.org/"
            >spamassassin.apache.org</ulink>) and SpamProbe
            (<ulink url="http://spamprobe.sourceforge.net/"
            >spamprobe.sourceforge.net</ulink>), but this
            is not a comment on the many other open source spam
            filters out there, some of which are apparently also quite
            good.  I just happen to have used those two myself and
            been satisfied with them.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Moderation.</emphasis></para>
            <para>For mails that aren't automatically allowed by
            virtue of being from a list subscriber, and which make it
            through the spam filtering software, if any, the last stage
            is <firstterm>moderation</firstterm>: the mail is routed
            to a special holding area, where a human examines it and
            confirms or rejects it.</para>

            <para>Confirming a post usually takes one of two forms:
            you can accept the sender's post just this once, or you
            can tell the system to allow this and all future posts
            from the same sender.  You almost always want to do the
            latter, in order to reduce the future moderation
            burden&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;after all, someone who has made a
            valid post to a forum is unlikely to suddenly turn into a
            spammer later.</para>

            <para>Rejecting is done by either marking the item to be
            discarded, or by explicitly telling the system the message
            was spam so the system can improve its ability to
            recognize future spams.  Sometimes
            you also have the option to automatically discard future
            mails from the same sender without them ever being held in
            the moderation queue, but there is rarely any point doing
            this, since spammers don't send from the same address
            twice anyway.</para>

            <para>Oddly, most message-forum systems have not yet given
            the moderation queue administrative interface the
            attention it deserves, considering how common the task is,
            so moderation often still requires more clicks and UI
            gestures than it should.  I hope this situation will
            improve in the future.  In the meantime, perhaps knowing
            you're not alone in your frustration will temper your
            disappointment somewhat.</para>
            </listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>Be sure to use moderation <emphasis>only</emphasis> for
filtering out spams, and perhaps for clearly off-topic messages such
as when someone accidentally posts to the wrong mailing list.
Although the moderation system may give you a way to respond directly
to the sender, you should never use that method to answer questions
that really belong on the mailing list itself, even if you know the
answer off the top of your head.  To do so would deprive the project's
community of an accurate picture of what sorts of questions people are
asking, and deprive people of a chance to answer questions themselves
and/or see answers from others.  Mailing list moderation is strictly
about keeping the list free of spam and of wildly off-topic emails,
nothing more.</para>

</sect4>

<sect4 id="address-hiding">
<title>Address hiding in archives</title>

<para>To prevent your mailing lists from being a source of addresses
for spammers, a common technique is for the archiving software to
obscure people's email addresses, for example by replacing</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para><literal>jrandom@somedomain.com</literal></para>
    </blockquote>

<para>with</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para><literal>jrandom_AT_somedomain.com</literal></para>
    </blockquote>

<para>or</para>

    <blockquote>
      <para><literal>jrandomNOSPAM@somedomain.com</literal></para>
    </blockquote>

<para>or some similarly obvious (to a human) encoding.  Since spam
address harvesters often work by crawling through web
pages&mdash;including your mailing list's online archives&mdash;and
looking for sequences containing "@", encoding the addresses is a way
of making people's email addresses invisible or useless to spammers.
This does nothing to prevent spam from being sent to the mailing list
itself, of course, but it does avoid increasing the amount of spam
sent directly to list users' personal addresses.</para>

<para>Address hiding can be controversial.  Some people like it a lot,
and will be surprised if your archives don't do it automatically.
Other people think it's too much of an inconvenience (because humans
also have to translate the addresses back before using them).
Sometimes people assert that it's ineffective, because a harvester
could in theory compensate for any consistent encoding pattern.
However, note that there is empirical evidence that address hiding
<emphasis>is</emphasis> effective; see <ulink
url="http://www.cdt.org/speech/spam/030319spamreport.shtml"
>cdt.org/speech/spam/030319spamreport.shtml</ulink>.</para>

<para>Ideally, the list management software would leave the choice up
to each individual subscriber, either through a special yes/no header
or a setting in that subscriber's list account preferences.  However,
I don't know of any software which offers per-subscriber or per-post
choice in the matter, so for now the list manager must make a decision
for everyone (assuming the archiver offers the feature at all, which
is not always the case).  For what it's worth, I lean toward turning
address hiding on.  Some people are very careful to avoid posting
their email addresses on web pages or anywhere else a spam harvester
might see it, and they would be disappointed to have all that care
thrown away by a mailing list archive; meanwhile, the inconvenience
address hiding imposes on archive users is very slight, since it's
trivial to transform an obscured address back to a valid one if you
need to reach the person.  But keep in mind that, in the end, it's
still an arms race: by the time you read this, harvesters might well
have evolved to the point where they can recognize most common forms
of hiding, and we'll have to think of something else.</para>

</sect4>

</sect3>

<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect3 id="header-management">
<title>Identification and Header Management</title>

<para>When interacting with the forum by email, subscribers often want
to put mails from the list into a project-specific folder, separate
from their other mail.  Their mail reading software can do this
automatically by examining the mail's <firstterm>headers</firstterm>.
The headers are the fields at the top of the mail that indicate the
sender, recipient, subject, date, and various other things about the
message.  Certain headers are well known and are effectively
mandatory:</para>

<screen>
From: ...
To: ...
Subject: ...
Date: ...
</screen>

<para>Others are optional, though still quite standard.  For example,
emails are not strictly required to have the</para>

<screen>
Reply-to: sender@email.address.here
</screen>

<para>header, but most do, because it gives recipients a foolproof way
to reach the author (it is especially useful when the author had to
send from an address other than the one to which replies should be
directed).</para>

<para>Some mail reading software offers an easy-to-use interface for
filing mails based on patterns in the Subject header.  This leads
people to request that the mailing list add an automatic prefix to all
Subjects, so they can set their readers to look for that prefix and
automatically file the mails in the right folder.  The idea is that
the original author would write:</para>

<screen>
Subject: Making the 2.5 release.
</screen>

<para>but the mail would show up on the list looking like this:</para>

<screen>
Subject: [Scanley Discuss] Making the 2.5 release.
</screen>

<para>Although most list management software offers the option to do
this, you may decide against turning the option on.  The problem
it solves can often be solved in less obtrusive ways (see below), and
there is a cost to eating space in the Subject field.  Experienced
mailing list users typically scan the Subjects of the day's incoming
list mail to decide what to read and/or respond to.  Prepending the
list's name to the Subject can push the right side of the Subject off
the screen, rendering it invisible.  This obscures information that
people depend on to decide what mails to open, thus reducing the
overall functionality of the mailing list for everyone.</para>

<para>Instead of munging the Subject header, your project could take
advantage of the other standard headers, starting with the To header,
which should say the mailing list's address:</para>

<screen>
To: &lt;discuss@lists.example.org&gt;
</screen>

<para>Any mail reader that can filter on Subject should be able to filter on
To just as easily.</para>

<para>There are a few other optional-but-standard headers expected for
mailing lists; they are sometimes not displayed by most mailreader
software, but they are present nonetheless.  Filtering on them is
even more reliable than using the "To" or "Cc" headers, and since these
headers are added to each post by the mailing list management software
itself, some users may be counting on their presence:</para>

<screen>
list-help: &lt;mailto:discuss-help@lists.example.org&gt;
list-unsubscribe: &lt;mailto:discuss-unsubscribe@lists.example.org&gt;
list-post: &lt;mailto:discuss@lists.example.org&gt;
Delivered-To: mailing list discuss@lists.example.org
Mailing-List: contact discuss-help@lists.example.org; run by ezmlm
</screen>

<para>For the most part, they are self-explanatory.  See <ulink
url="http://www.nisto.com/listspec/list-manager-intro.html"
>nisto.com/listspec/list-manager-intro.html</ulink> for more
explanation, or if you need the really detailed, formal specification,
see <ulink url="http://www.faqs.org/rfcs/rfc2369.html"
>faqs.org/rfcs/rfc2369.html</ulink>.
</para>

<para>Having said all that, these days I find that most subscribers
just request that the Subject header include a list-identifying
prefix.  That's increasingly how people are accustomed to filtering
email: Subject-based filtering is what many of the major online email
services (like Gmail) offer users by default, and those services tend
not to make it easy to see the presence of less-commonly used headers
like the ones I mentioned above&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;thus making it hard
for people to figure out that they would even have the option of
filtering on those other headers.</para>

<para>Therefore, reluctantly, I recommend using a Subject prefix (keep
it as short as you can) if that's what your community wants.  But if
your project highly technical and most of its participants are
comfortable using the other headers, then that option is always there
as a more space-efficient alternative.</para>

<para>It also used to be the case that if you have a mailing list
named "foo", then you also have administrative addresses "foo-help"
and "foo-unsubscribe" available.  In addition to these, it was
traditional to have "foo-subscribe" for joining, and "foo-owner",
for reaching the list administrators.  Increasingly, however,
subscribers manage their list membership via Web-based interfaces, so
even if the list management software you use sets up these
administrative addresses, they may go largely unused.</para>

<para>Some mailing list software offers an option to append
unsubscription instructions to the bottom of every post.  If that
option is available, turn it on.  It causes only a couple of extra
lines per message, in a harmless location, and it can save you a lot
of time, by cutting down on the number of people who mail you&mdash;or
worse, mail the list!&mdash;asking how to unsubscribe.</para>

</sect3>

<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect3 id="reply-to">
<title>The Great Reply-to Debate</title>

<para>Earlier, in <xref linkend="avoid-private-discussions"/>, I stressed the
importance of making sure discussions stay in public forums, and
talked about how active measures are sometimes needed to prevent
conversations from trailing off into private email threads;
furthermore, this chapter is all about setting up project
communications software to do as much of the work for people as possible.
Therefore, if the mailing list management software offers a way to
automatically cause discussions to stay on the list, you would think
turning on that feature would be the obvious choice.</para>

<para>Well, not quite.  There is such a feature, but it has some
pretty severe disadvantages.  The question of whether or not to use it
is one of the hottest debates in mailing list
management&mdash;admittedly, not a controversy that's likely to make
the evening news in your city, but it can flare up from time to time
in free software projects.  Below, I will describe the feature, give
the major arguments on both sides, and make the best recommendation I
can.</para>

<para>The feature itself is very simple: the mailing list software
can, if you wish, automatically set the Reply-to header on every post
to redirect replies to the mailing list.  That is, no matter what the
original sender puts in the Reply-to header (or even if they don't
include one at all), by the time the list subscribers see the post,
the header will contain the list address:</para>

<screen>
Reply-to: discuss@lists.example.org
</screen>

<para>On its face, this seems like a good thing.  Because virtually
all mail reading software pays attention to the Reply-to header, now
when anyone responds to a post, their response will be automatically
addressed to the entire list, not just to the sender of the message
being responded to.  Of course, the responder can still manually
change where the message goes, but the important thing is that
<emphasis>by default</emphasis> replies are directed to the list.
It's a perfect example of using technology to encourage
collaboration.</para>

<para>Unfortunately, there are some disadvantages.  The first is known
as the <firstterm>Can't Find My Way Back Home</firstterm> problem:
sometimes the original sender will put their "real" email address in
the Reply-to field, because for one reason or another they send email
from a different address than where they receive it.  People who
always read and send from the same location don't have this problem,
and may be surprised that it even exists.  But for those who have
unusual email configurations, or who cannot control how the From
address on their mails looks (perhaps because they send from work and
do not have any influence over the IT department), using Reply-to may
be the only way they have to ensure that responses reach them.  When
such a person posts to a mailing list that he's not subscribed to, his
setting of Reply-to becomes essential information.  If the list
software overwrites it<footnote><para>In theory, the list software
could <emphasis>add</emphasis> the lists's address to whatever
Reply-to destination were already present, if any, instead of
overwriting.  In practice, for reasons I don't know, most list
software overwrites instead of appending.</para></footnote>, he may
never see the responses to his post.</para>

<para>The second disadvantage has to do with expectations, and in my
opinion is the most powerful argument against Reply-to munging.  Most
experienced mail users are accustomed to two basic methods of
replying: <firstterm>reply-to-all</firstterm> and
<firstterm>reply-to-author</firstterm>.  All modern mail reading
software has separate keys for these two actions.  Users know that to
reply to everyone (that is, including the list), they should choose
reply-to-all, and to reply privately to the author, they should choose
reply-to-author.  Although you want to encourage people to reply to
the list whenever possible, there are certainly circumstances where a
private reply is the responder's prerogative&mdash;for example, they
may want to say something confidential to the author of the original
message, something that would be inappropriate on the public
list.</para>

<para>Now consider what happens when the list has overridden the
original sender's Reply-to.  The responder hits the reply-to-author
key, expecting to send a private message back to the original author.
Because that's the expected behavior, he may not bother to look
carefully at the recipient address in the new message.  He composes
his private, confidential message, one which perhaps says embarrassing
things about someone on the list, and hits the send key.
Unexpectedly, a few minutes later his message appears <emphasis>on the
mailing list!</emphasis> True, in theory he should have looked
carefully at the recipient field, and should not have assumed anything
about the Reply-to header.  But authors almost always set Reply-to to
their own personal address (or rather, their mail software sets it for
them), and many longtime email users have come to expect that.  In
fact, when a person deliberately sets Reply-to to some other address,
such as the list, she usually makes a point of mentioning this in the
body of her message, so people won't be surprised at what happens when
they reply.</para>

<para>Because of the possibly severe consequences of this unexpected
behavior, my own preference is to configure list management software
to never touch the Reply-to header.  This is one instance where using
technology to encourage collaboration has, it seems to me, potentially
dangerous side-effects.  However, there are also some powerful
arguments on the other side of this debate.  Whichever way you choose,
you will occasionally get people posting to your list asking why you
didn't choose the other way.  Since this is not something you ever
want as the main topic of discussion on your list, it might be good to
have a canned response ready, of the sort that's more likely to stop
discussion than encourage it.  Make sure you do
<emphasis>not</emphasis> insist that your decision, whichever it is,
is obviously the only right and sensible one (even if you think that's
the case).  Instead, point out that this is a very old debate, there
are good arguments on both sides, no choice is going to satisfy
all users, and therefore you just made the best decision you
could.  Politely ask that the subject not be revisited unless someone
has something genuinely new to say, then stay out of the thread and
hope it dies a natural death.</para>

<para>Someone may suggest a vote to choose one way or the other.  You
can do that if you want, but I personally do not feel that counting
heads is a satisfactory solution in this case.  The penalty for
someone who is surprised by the behavior is so huge (accidentally
sending a private mail to a public list), and the inconvenience for
everyone else is fairly slight (occasionally having to remind someone
to respond to the whole list instead of just to you), that it's not
clear that the majority, even though they are the majority, should be
able to put the minority at such risk.</para>

<para>I have not addressed all aspects of this issue here, just the
ones that seemed of overriding importance.  For a full discussion, see
these two canonical documents, which are the ones people always cite
when they're having this debate:

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
     <para><emphasis role="bold">Leave Reply-to alone</emphasis>,
     <emphasis>by Chip Rosenthal</emphasis></para>
     <para><ulink
        url="http://www.unicom.com/pw/reply-to-harmful.html"
        >unicom.com/pw/reply-to-harmful.html</ulink></para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
     <para><emphasis role="bold">Set Reply-to to list</emphasis>,
     <emphasis>by Simon Hill</emphasis></para>
     <para><ulink
        url="http://www.metasystema.net/essays/reply-to.mhtml"
        >metasystema.net/essays/reply-to.mhtml</ulink></para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</para>

<para>Despite the mild preference indicated above, I do not feel there
is a "right" answer to this question, and happily participate in many
lists that <emphasis>do</emphasis> set Reply-to.  The most important
thing you can do is settle on one way or the other early, and try not
to get entangled in debates about it after that.  When the debate
re-arises every few years, as it inevitably will, you can point people
to the archived discussion from last time.</para>

<sect4 id="reply-fantasies">
<title>Two fantasies</title>

<para>Someday, someone will get the bright idea to implement a
<firstterm>reply-to-list</firstterm> key in a mail reader.  It would
use some of the custom list headers mentioned earlier to figure out
the address of the mailing list, and then address the reply directly
to the list only, leaving off any other recipient addresses, since
most are probably subscribed to the list anyway.  Eventually, other
mail readers will pick up the feature, and this whole debate will go
away.  (Actually, the <ulink url="http://www.mutt.org/" >Mutt</ulink>
mail reader does offer this feature.<footnote><para>Shortly after this
book appeared, <ulink url="http://www.michaelbernstein.com/"
>Michael Bernstein</ulink> wrote me to say: "There are other email
clients that implement a reply-to-list function besides Mutt. For
example, Evolution has this function as a keyboard shortcut, but not a
button (Ctrl+L)."</para></footnote>)</para>

<para>An even better solution would be for Reply-to munging to be a
per-subscriber preference.  Those who want the list to set Reply-to
munged (either on others' posts or on their own posts) could ask for
that, and those who don't would ask for Reply-to to be left alone.
However, I don't know of any list management software that offers this
on a per-subscriber basis.  For now, we seem to be stuck with a global
setting.<footnote><para>Since I wrote that, I've learned that there is
at least one list management system that offers this
feature: <ulink url="http://siesta.unixbeard.net/">Siesta</ulink>.
See also this article about it:
<ulink url="http://www.perl.com/pub/a/2004/02/05/siesta.html"
>perl.com/pub/a/2004/02/05/siesta.html</ulink></para></footnote></para>

</sect4>

</sect3>

<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect3 id="archiving">
<title>Archiving</title>

<para>The technical details of setting up mailing list archiving are
specific to the software that's running the list, and are beyond the
scope of this book.  If you have to choose or configure an archiver,
consider these qualities:</para>

<variablelist>

  <varlistentry><term>Prompt updating</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>People will often want to refer to an archived message
            that was posted recently.  If possible, the archiver
            should archive each post instantaneously, so that by the
            time a post appears on the mailing list, it's already
            present in the archives.  If that option isn't available,
            then at least try to set the archiver to update itself
            every hour or so.  (By default, some archivers run their
            update processes once per night, but in practice that's
            far too much lag time for an active mailing list.)</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Referential stability</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Once a message is archived at a particular URL, it should
            remain accessible at that exact same URL forever, or as
            close to forever as possible.  Even if the archives are
            rebuilt, restored from backup, or otherwise fixed, any
            URLs that have already been made publicly available
            should remain the same.  Stable references make it
            possible for Internet search engines to index the
            archives, which is a major boon to users looking for
            answers.  Stable references are also important because
            mailing list posts and threads are often linked to from
            the bug tracker (see
            <xref
            linkend="bug-tracker"/><phrase output="printed">
            later in this chapter</phrase>) or
            from other project documents.</para>

      <para>Ideally, mailing list software would include a message's
            archive URL, or at least the message-specific portion of
            the URL, in a header when it distributes the message to
            recipients.  That way people who have a copy of the
            message would be able to know its archive location
            without having to actually visit the archives, which would
            be helpful because any operation that involves one's web
            browser is automatically time-consuming.  Whether any
            mailing list software actually offers this feature, I don't
            know; unfortunately, the ones I have used do not.
            However, it's something to look for (or, if you write
            mailing list software, it's a feature to consider
            implementing, please).</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Thread support</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>It should be possible to go from any individual message to
            the <firstterm>thread</firstterm> (group of related
            messages) that the original message is part of.  Each
            thread should have its own URL too, separate from the URLs
            of the individual messages in the thread.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>Searchability</term>
    <listitem>
      <para>An archiver that doesn't support searching&mdash;on the
            bodies of messages, as well as on authors and
            subjects&mdash;is close to useless.  Note that some archivers 
            support searching by simply farming the work out to an
            external search engine such as <ulink
            url="http://www.google.com/" >Google</ulink>.  This is
            acceptable, but direct search support is usually more
            fine-tuned, because it allows the searcher to specify that
            the match must appear in a subject line versus the body,
            for example.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

</variablelist>

<para>The above is just a technical checklist to help you evaluate and
set up an archiver.  Getting people to
actually <emphasis>use</emphasis> the archiver to the project's
advantage is discussed in later chapters, in particular
<xref linkend="using-archives"/>.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="message-forum-software">
<!-- For link compatibility with the old section ID. -->
<anchor id="mailing-list-software" />
<title>Mailing List / Message Forum Software</title>

<para>Here are some tools for running message forums.  If the site
where you're hosting your project already has a default setup, then
you can just use that and avoid having to choose.  But if you need to
install one yourself, below are some possibilities.  (Of course, there
are probably other tools out there that I just didn't happen to find,
so don't take this as a complete list).</para>

<itemizedlist>
 <listitem>
   <para><emphasis role="bold">Google&nbsp;Groups</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink url="http://groups.google.com/" >groups.google.com</ulink></para>
   <para>Listing Google Groups first was a tough call.  The service is
         not itself open source, and a few of its administrative
         functions can be a bit hard to use.  However, its advantages
         are substantial: your group's archives are always online and
         searchable; you don't have to worry about scalability,
         backups, or other run-time infrastructure issues; the
         moderation and spam-prevention features are pretty good (with
         the latter constantly being improved, which is important in
         the neverending spam arms race); and Google Groups are easily
         accessible via both email and web, in ways that are likely to
         be already familiar to many participants.  These are strong
         advantages.  If you just want to get your project started,
         and don't want to spend too much time thinking about what
         message forum software or service to use, Google Groups
         is a good default choice.</para> 
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
   <para><emphasis role="bold">GroupServer</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
         url="http://www.groupserver.org/"/></para>
   <para>Has built-in archiver and integrated Web-based interface.
         GroupServer is a bit of work to set up, but once you have it
         up and running it offers users a good experience.
         You may  able to find free or low-cost hosted GroupServer
         hosting for your project's forums, for example from <ulink
         url="https://OnlineGroups.net/" >OnlineGroups.net</ulink>.</para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
   <para><emphasis role="bold">Sympa</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
         url="http://www.sympa.org/" >sympa.org</ulink></para>
   <para>Developed and maintained by a consortium of French
         universities, and designed for a given instance to handle
         both very large lists (> 700000 members, they claim) and a
         large number of lists.  Sympa can work with a variety of
         dependencies; for example, you can run it with sendmail,
         postfix, qmail or exim as the underlying message transfer
         agent.  It has built-in Web-based archiving.</para>
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
   <para><emphasis role="bold">Mailman</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
         url="http://www.list.org/" >list.org</ulink></para>
   <para>For many years, Mailman was the standard for open source
         project mailing lists.  It comes with a built-in archiver,
         Pipermail, and hooks for plugging in external archivers.
         Unfortunately, Mailman is showing its age now, and while
         it is very reliable in terms of message delivery and other
         under-the-hood functionality, its administrative
         interfaces&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;especially for spam moderation
         and subscription moderation&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;are frustrating
         for those accustomed to the modern Web.  As of this writing
         in late 2013, the long-awaited Mailman 3 was still in
         development but was about to enter beta-testing; by the time
         you read this, Mailman 3 may be released, and would be worth
         a look.  It is supposed to solve many of the problems of
         Mailman 2, and may make Mailman a reasonable choice again.</para> 
 </listitem>
 <listitem>
   <para><emphasis role="bold">Dada</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
         url="http://dadamailproject.com/" >dadamailproject.com</ulink></para>
   <para>I've not used Dada myself, but it is actively maintained and,
         at least from outward appearances, quite spiffy.  Note that
         to use it for participatory lists, as opposed to announcement
         lists, you apparently need to activate the plug-in "Dada
         Bridge".  Commercial Dada hosting and installation offerings
         are available, or you can download the code and install it
         yourself.</para>
 </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ========================== SECTION =========================== -->
<sect1 id="vc">
<title>Version Control</title>

<para>A <firstterm>version control system</firstterm> (or
<firstterm>revision control system</firstterm>) is a combination of
technologies and practices for tracking and controlling changes to a
project's files, in particular to source code, documentation, and web
pages.  If you have never used version control before, the first thing
you should do is go find someone who has, and get them to join your
project.  These days, everyone will expect at least your project's
source code to be under version control, and probably will not take
the project seriously if it doesn't use version control with at least
minimal competence.</para>

<para>The reason version control is so universal is that it helps with
virtually every aspect of running a project: inter-developer
communications, release management, bug management, code stability and
experimental development efforts, and attribution and authorization of
changes by particular developers.  The version control system provides
a central coordinating force among all of these areas.  The core of
version control is <firstterm>change management</firstterm>:
identifying each discrete change made to the project's files,
annotating each change with metadata like the change's date and
author, and then replaying these facts to whoever asks, in whatever
way they ask.  It is a communications mechanism where a change is the
basic unit of information.</para>

<para>This section does not discuss all aspects of using a version
control system.  It's so all-encompassing that it must be addressed
topically throughout the book.  Here, we will concentrate on choosing
and setting up a version control system in a way that will foster
cooperative development down the road.</para>

<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-vocabulary">
<title>Version Control Vocabulary</title>

<para>This book cannot teach you how to use version control if you've
never used it before, but it would be impossible to discuss the
subject without a few key terms.  These terms are useful independently
of any particular version control system: they are the basic nouns and
verbs of networked collaboration, and will be used generically
throughout the rest of this book.  Even if there were no version
control systems in the world, the problem of change management would
remain, and these words give us a language for talking about that
problem concisely.</para>

<para>If you're comfortably experienced with version control already,
you can probably skip this section.  If you're not sure, then read
through this section at least once.  Certain version control terms
have gradually changed in meaning since the early 2000s, and you may
occasionally find people using them in incompatible ways in the same
conversation.  Being able to detect that phenomenon early in a
discussion can often be helpful.</para>

<variablelist>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-commit">
  <term><firstterm>commit</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>To make a change to the project; more formally, to
  store a change in the version control database in such a way that it
  can be incorporated into future releases of the project.  "Commit"
  can be used as a verb or a noun.  For example: "I just committed a
  fix for the server crash bug people have been reporting on Mac OS X.
  Jay, could you please review the commit and check that I'm not
  misusing the allocator there?"</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-push">
  <term><firstterm>push</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>To publish a commit to a publicly online repository,
  from which others can incorporate it into their copy of the
  project's code.  When one says one has pushed a commit, the
  destination repository is usually implied.  Often it is the
  project's master repository, the one from which public releases are
  made, but not always.</para>
  <para>Note that in some version control systems (e.g., Subversion),
  commits are automatically and unavoidably pushed up to a
  predetermined central repository, while in others (e.g., Git,
  Mercurial) the developer chooses when and where to push commits.
  Because the former types privilege a particular central repository,
  they are known as "centralized" version control systems, while the
  latter are known as "decentralized".  In general, 
  decentralized systems are the modern trend, especially for open
  source projects, which benefit from the peer-to-peer relationship
  between developers' repositories.</para></listitem> 
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-pull">
  <!-- For link compatibility with the old varlistentry ID. -->
  <anchor id="vc-vocabulary-update" />
  <term><firstterm>pull</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para><emphasis>(or
           "<firstterm>update</firstterm>")</emphasis></para>
  <para>To pull others' changes (commits) into your local
  copy of the project.  When pulling changes from a project's mainline
  development branch (see <xref linkend="vc-vocabulary-branch"/>),
  people often say "update" instead of "pull", for example: "Hey, I
  noticed the indexing code is always dropping the last byte.  Is this
  a new bug?" "Yes, but it was fixed last week&mdash;try updating and
  it should go away."</para></listitem>
  <!-- possv2 todo: link to 'pull-requests' from here? -->
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-commit-message">
  <!-- For link compatibility with the old varlistentry ID. -->
  <anchor id="vc-vocabulary-log-message" />
  <term><firstterm>commit&nbsp;message</firstterm>&nbsp;<emphasis>or</emphasis>&nbsp;<firstterm>log&nbsp;message</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>A bit of commentary attached to each commit,
  describing the nature and purpose of the commit (both terms are used
  about equally often; I'll use them interchangeably in this book).
  Log messages are among the most important documents in any project:
  they are the bridge between the detailed, highly technical meaning
  of each individual code changes and the more user-visible world of
  bugfixes, features and project progress.  Later in this section,
  we'll look at ways to distribute them to the appropriate audiences;
  also, <xref linkend="codifying-tradition"/><phrase
  output="printed"> in <xref linkend="communications"/></phrase>
  discusses ways to encourage contributors to write concise and useful
  commit messages.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-repository">
  <term><firstterm>repository</firstterm></term> <listitem><para>A
  database in which changes are stored and from which they are
  published.  In centralized version control systems, there is a
  single, master repository, which stores all changes to the project,
  and each developer works with a kind of latest summary on her own
  machine.  In decentralized systems, each developer has her own
  repository, changes can be swapped back and forth between
  repositories arbitrarily, and the question of which repository is
  the "master" (that is, the one from which public releases are
  rolled) is defined purely by social convention, instead of by a
  combination of social convention and technical
  enforcement.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-clone">
  <term><firstterm>clone</firstterm>&nbsp;<emphasis>(see also
  <xref linkend="vc-vocabulary-checkout">"checkout"</xref>)</emphasis></term>
  <listitem><para>To obtain one's own development repository by making
  a copy of the project's central repository.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-checkout">
  <term><firstterm>checkout</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>When used in discussion, "checkout" usually means
  something like "clone", except that centralized systems don't really
  clone the full repository, they just obtain a <xref
  linkend="vc-vocabulary-working-copy">working copy</xref>.  When
  decentralized systems use the word "checkout", they also mean the
  process of obtaining working files from a repository, but since the
  repository is local in that case, the user experience is quite
  different because the network is not involved.</para>
  <para>In the centralized sense, a checkout produces a directory tree
  called a "working copy" (see below), from which changes may be
  sent back to the original repository.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-working-copy">
  <anchor id="vc-vocabulary-working-files" />
  <term><firstterm>working copy</firstterm>&nbsp;<emphasis>or</emphasis>&nbsp;<firstterm>working files</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>A developer's private directory tree containing the
  project's source code files, and possibly its web pages or other
  documents, in a form that allows the developer to edit them.  A
  working copy also contains some version control metadata saying what
  repository it comes from, what branch it represents, and a few other
  things.  Typically, each developer has her own working copy, from
  which she edits, tests, commits, pulls, pushes,
  etc.</para>
  <para>In decentralized systems, working copies and repositories are
  usually colocated anyway, so the term "working copy" is less often
  used.  Developers instead tend to say "my clone" or "my copy" or
  sometimes "my fork".</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-revision">
  <term><firstterm>revision</firstterm>,
        <firstterm>change</firstterm>,
        <firstterm>changeset</firstterm>,
        or (again) <emphasis>commit</emphasis></term>
  <listitem><para>A "revision" is a precisely specified incarnation of
  the project at a point in time, or of a particular file or directory
  in the project.  These days, most systems also use "revision",
  "change", "changeset", or "commit" to refer to a set of changes
  committed together as one conceptual unit, if multiple files were
  involved, though colloquially most people would refer to changeset
  12's effect on file F as "revision 12 of F".</para>

  <para>These terms occasionally have distinct technical meanings in
  different version control systems, but the general idea is always
  the same: they give a way to speak precisely about exact points in
  time in the history of a file or a set of files (say, immediately
  before and after a bug is fixed).  For example: "Oh yes, she fixed
  that in revision 10" or "She fixed that in commit fa458b1fac".</para>

  <para>When one talks about a file or collection of files without
  specifying a particular revision, it is generally assumed that one
  means the most recent revision(s) available.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

  <sidebar id="version-vs-revision">
  <title>"Version" Versus "Revision"</title>
  <para>The word <firstterm>version</firstterm> is sometimes used as a
  synonym for "revision", but I will not use it that way in this
  book, because it is too easily confused with "version" in the sense
  of a version of a piece of software&mdash;that is, the release or
  edition number, as in "Version 1.0".  However, since the phrase
  "version control" is already standard, I will continue to use it as
  a synonym for "revision control" and "change control".  Sorry.  One
  of open source's most endearing characteristics is that it has two
  words for everything, and one word for every two things.</para>
  </sidebar>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-diff">
  <term><firstterm>diff</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>A textual representation of a change.  A diff shows
  which lines were changed and how, plus a few lines of surrounding
  context on either side.  A developer who is already familiar with
  some code can usually read a diff against that code and understand
  what the change did, and often even spot bugs.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-tag">
  <term><firstterm>tag</firstterm>&nbsp;<emphasis>or</emphasis>&nbsp;<firstterm>snapshot</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>A label for a particular state of the project at a
  point in time.  Tags are generally used to mark interesting
  snapshots of the project.  For example, a tag is usually made for
  each public release, so that one can obtain, directly from the
  version control system, the exact set of files/revisions comprising
  that release.  Tag names are often things like
  <literal>Release_1_0</literal>, <literal>Delivery_20130630</literal>,
  etc.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-branch">
  <term><firstterm>branch</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>A copy of the project, under version control but
  isolated so that changes made to the branch don't affect other
  branches of the project, and vice versa, except when changes are
  deliberately "merged" from one branch to another (see below).
  Branches are also known as "lines of development".  Even when a
  project has no explicit branches, development is still considered
  to be happening on the "main branch", also known as the "main line"
  or "<firstterm>trunk</firstterm>" or
  "<firstterm>master</firstterm>".</para>

  <para>Branches offer a way to keep different lines of development
  from interfering with each other.  For example, a branch can be used
  for experimental development that would be too destabilizing for the
  main trunk.  Or conversely, a branch can be used as a place to
  stabilize a new release.  During the release process, regular
  development would continue uninterrupted in the main branch of the
  repository; meanwhile, on the release branch, no changes are allowed
  except those approved by the release managers.  This way, making a
  release needn't interfere with ongoing development work.  See <xref
  linkend="branches"/><phrase output="printed"> later in this
  chapter</phrase> for a more detailed discussion of
  branching.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-merge">
  <anchor id="vc-vocabulary-port" />
  <term><firstterm>merge</firstterm>&nbsp;<emphasis>or</emphasis>&nbsp;<firstterm>port</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>To move a change from one branch to another.  This
  includes merging from the main trunk to some other branch, or vice
  versa.  In fact, those are the most common kinds of merges; it is
  less common to port a change between two non-trunk branches.  See
  <xref linkend="vc-singularity"/> for more on change porting.</para>

  <para>"Merge" has a second, related meaning: it is what some version
  control systems do when they see that two people have changed the
  same file but in non-overlapping ways.  Since the two changes do not
  interfere with each other, when one of the people updates their copy
  of the file (already containing their own changes), the other
  person's changes will be automatically merged in.  This is very
  common, especially on projects where multiple people are hacking on
  the same code.  When two different changes <emphasis>do</emphasis>
  overlap, the result is a "conflict"; see below.</para>
  </listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-conflict">
  <term><firstterm>conflict</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>What happens when two people try to make different
  changes to the same place in the code.  All version control systems
  automatically detect conflicts, and notify at least one of the
  humans involved that their changes conflict with someone else's.  It
  is then up to that human to <firstterm>resolve</firstterm> the
  conflict, and to communicate that resolution to the version control
  system.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

 <varlistentry id="vc-vocabulary-lock">
  <term><firstterm>lock</firstterm></term>
  <listitem><para>A way to declare an exclusive intent to change a
  particular file or directory.  For example, "I can't commit any
  changes to the web pages right now.  It seems Alfred has them all
  locked while he fixes their background images."  Not all version
  control systems even offer the ability to lock, and of those that
  do, not all require the locking feature to be used.  This is because
  parallel, simultaneous development is the norm, and locking people
  out of files is (usually) contrary to this ideal.</para>

  <para>Version control systems that require locking to make commits
  are said to use the <firstterm>lock-modify-unlock</firstterm> model.
  Those that do not are said to use the
  <firstterm>copy-modify-merge</firstterm> model.  An excellent
  in-depth explanation and comparison of the two models may be found
  at <ulink
  url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.basic.version-control-basics.html#svn.basic.vsn-models"
  >svnbook.red-bean.com/nightly/en/svn.basic.version-control-basics.html#svn.basic.vsn-models</ulink>.  In
  general, the copy-modify-merge model is better for open source
  development, and all the version control systems discussed in this
  book support that model.</para></listitem>
 </varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</sect2>


<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-choosing">
<title>Choosing a Version Control System</title>

<para>If you don't already have a strong opinion about which version
control system your project should use, then choose Git (<ulink
url="http://git-scm.com/" >git-scm.com</ulink>), and host your
project's repositories at <ulink url="http://github.com/"
>GitHub.com</ulink>, which offers unlimited free hosting for open
source projects.</para>

<para>Git is by now the <foreignphrase>de facto</foreignphrase>
standard in the open source world, as is hosting one's repositories at
GitHub.  Because so many developers are already comfortable with that
combination, choosing it sends the signal that your project is ready
for participants.  But Git-at-GitHub is not the only viable
combination.  Two other reasonable choices of version control system
are <ulink url="http://mercurial.selenic.com/" >Mercurial</ulink> and
<ulink url="http://subversion.apache.org/" >Subversion</ulink>.
Mercurial and Git are both decentralized systems, whereas Subversion
is centralized.  All three are offered at many different free hosting
services; some services even support more than one of them (though
GitHub only supports Git, as its name suggests).  While some projects
host their repositories on their own servers, most just put their
repositories on one of the free hosting services, as described in
<xref linkend="canned-hosting-sites"/>.</para>

<para>There isn't space here for an in-depth exploration of why you
might choose something other than Git.  If you have a reason to do so,
then you already know what that reason is.  If you don't, then just
use Git (and probably on GitHub).  If you find yourself using
something other than Git, Mercurial, or Subversion, ask yourself
why&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;because whatever that other version control
system is, most other developers won't be familiar with it, and it
likely has a smaller and less stable community of support around it
than the big three do.</para>

</sect2>


<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-using">
<title>Using the Version Control System</title>

<para>The recommendations in this section are not targeted toward a
particular version control system, and should be implementable in any
of them.  Consult your specific system's documentation for
details.</para>

<sect3 id="version-everything">
<title>Version everything</title>

<para>Keep not only your project's source code under version control,
but also its web pages, documentation, FAQ, design notes, and anything
else that people might want to edit.  Keep them right with the
source code, in the same repository tree.  Any piece of information
worth writing down is worth versioning&mdash;that is, any piece of
information that could change.  Things that don't change should be
archived, not versioned.  For example, an email, once posted, does not
change; therefore, versioning it wouldn't make sense (unless it becomes
part of some larger, evolving document).</para>

<para>The reason to version everything together in one place is so
that people only have to learn one mechanism for submitting changes.
Often a contributor will start out making edits to the web pages or
documentation, and move to small code contributions later, for
example.  When the project uses the same system for all kinds of
submissions, people only have to learn the ropes once.  Versioning
everything together also means that new features can be committed
together with their documentation updates, that branching the code
will branch the documentation too, etc.</para>

<para>Don't keep <firstterm>generated files</firstterm> under version
control.  They are not truly editable data, since they are produced
programmatically from other files.  For example, some build systems
create a file named <filename>configure</filename> based on a template
in <filename>configure.in</filename>.  To make a change to the
<filename>configure</filename>, one would edit
<filename>configure.in</filename> and then regenerate; thus, only the
template <filename>configure.in</filename> is an "editable file."
Just version the templates&mdash;if you version the generated files as
well, people will inevitably forget to regenerate them when they commit a
change to a template, and the resulting inconsistencies will cause no
end of confusion.</para>

<para>There are technical exceptions to the rule that all editable
data should be kept in the same version control system as the code.
For example, a project's bug tracker and its wiki hold plenty of
editable data, but usually do not store that data in the main version
control system<footnote><para>There are development environments that
integrate everything into one unified version control world; see <xref
linkend="vc-veracity"/> for an example.</para></footnote>.  However,
they should still have versioning systems of their own, e.g., the
comment history in a bug ticket, and the ability to browse past
revisions and view differences between them in a wiki.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="vc-browsing">
<title>Browsability</title>

<para>The project's repository should be browsable on the Web.  This
means not only the ability to see the latest revisions of the
project's files, but to go back in time and look at earlier revisions,
view the differences between revisions, read log messages for selected
changes, etc.</para>

<para>Browsability is important because it is a lightweight portal to
project data.  If the repository cannot be viewed through a web
browser, then someone wanting to inspect a particular file (say, to
see if a certain bugfix had made it into the code) would first have to
install version control client software locally, which could turn
their simple query from a two-minute task into a half-hour or longer
task.</para>

<para>Browsability also implies canonical URLs for viewing a particular
change (i.e., a commit), and for viewing the latest revision at any given
time without specifying its commit identifier.  This can be very
useful in technical discussions or when
pointing people to documentation.  For example, instead of saying "For
bug management guidelines, see the community-guide/index.html file
in your working copy," one can say "For bug management guidelines,
see
<emphasis>http://subversion.apache.org/docs/community-guide/</emphasis>,"
giving a URL that always points to the latest revision of the
<filename>community-guides/index.html</filename> file.  The URL is
better because it is completely unambiguous, and avoids the question
of whether the addressee has an up-to-date working copy.</para>

<para>Some version control systems come with built-in
repository-browsing mechanisms, and in any case most hosting sites
offer a good web interface.  But if you need to install a third-party
tool for repository browsing, there are many out there.  Three that
support Git are <firstterm>GitLab</firstterm> (<ulink
url="http://gitlab.org/" >gitlab.org</ulink>),
<firstterm>GitWeb</firstterm> (<ulink
url="https://git.wiki.kernel.org/index.php/Gitweb"
>git.wiki.kernel.org/index.php/Gitweb</ulink>), and
<firstterm>GitList</firstterm> (<ulink url="http://gitlist.org/"
>gitlist.org</ulink>).  For Subversion, there is
<firstterm>ViewVC</firstterm> (<ulink url="http://viewvc.org/"
>viewvc.org</ulink>).  A web search will turn up plenty of others
besides these.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="branches">
<title>Use branches to avoid bottlenecks</title>

<para>Non-expert version control users are sometimes a bit afraid of
branching and merging.  If you are among those people, resolve right
now to conquer any fears you may have and take the time to learn how
to do branching and merging.  They are not difficult operations, once
you get used to them, and they become increasingly important as a
project acquires more developers.</para>

<para>Branches are valuable because they turn a scarce
resource&mdash;working room in the project's code&mdash;into an
abundant one.  Normally, all developers work together in the same
sandbox, constructing the same castle.  When someone wants to add a
new drawbridge, but can't convince everyone else that it would be an
improvement, branching makes it possible for her to make a copy of the
castle, take it off to an isolated corner, and try out the new
drawbridge design.  If the effort succeeds, she can invite the
other developers to examine the result (in GitHub-speak, this
invitation is known as a "pull request"&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;see <xref
linkend="pull-requests"/>).  If everyone agrees that the
result is good, she or someone else can tell the version control
system to move ("merge") the drawbridge from the branch version of the
castle over to the main version, sometimes called the
<firstterm>master branch</firstterm>.</para>

<para>It's easy to see how this ability helps collaborative
development.  People need the freedom to try new things without
feeling like they're interfering with others' work.  Equally
importantly, there are times when code needs to be isolated from the
usual development churn, in order to get a bug fixed or a release
stabilized (see <xref linkend="stabilizing-a-release"/> and
<xref linkend="release-lines"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="development-cycle"/></phrase>) without worrying
about tracking a moving target.  At the same time, people need to be
able to review and comment on experimental work, whether it's
happening in the master branch or somewhere else.  Treating branches
as first-class, publishable objects makes all this possible.</para>

<para>Use branches liberally, and encourage others to use them.  But
also make sure that a given branch is only active for as long as
needed.  Every active branch is a slight drain on the community's
attention.  Even those who are not working in a branch still maintain
a peripheral awareness of what's going on in it.  Such awareness is
desirable, of course, and commit notices should be sent out for branch
commits just as for any other commit.  But branches should not become
a mechanism for dividing the development community.  With rare
exceptions, the eventual goal of most branches should be to merge
their changes back into the main line and disappear.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="vc-singularity">
<title>Singularity of information</title>

<para>Merging has an important corollary: never commit the same change
twice.  That is, a given change should enter the version control
system exactly once.  The revision (or set of revisions) in which the
change entered is its unique identifier from then on.  If it needs to
be applied to branches other than the one on which it entered, then it
should be merged from its original entry point to those other
destinations&mdash;as opposed to committing a textually identical
change, which would have the same effect in the code, but would make
accurate bookkeeping and release management much harder.</para>

<para>The practical effects of this advice differ from one version
control system to another.  In some systems, merges are special
events, fundamentally distinct from commits, and carry their own
metadata with them.  In others, the results of merges are committed
the same way other changes are committed, so the primary means of
distinguishing a "merge commit" from a "new change commit" is in the
log message.  In a merge's log message, don't repeat the log message
of the original change.  Instead, just indicate that this is a merge,
and give the identifying revision of the original change, with at most
a one-sentence summary of its effect.  If someone wants to see the
full log message, she should consult the original revision.</para>

<para>One reason it's important to avoid repeating the log message is
that, in some systems, log messages are sometimes edited after they've
been committed.  If a change's log message were repeated at each merge
destination, then even if someone edited the original message, she'd
still leave all the repeats uncorrected&mdash;which would only cause
confusion down the road.  Another reason is that non-duplication makes
it easier to be sure when one has tracked down the original source of
a change.  When you're looking at a complete log message that doesn't
refer to a some other merge source, you can know that it must be the
original change, and handle it accordingly.</para>

<para>The same principle applies to reverting a change.  If a change
is withdrawn from the code, then the log message for the reversion
should merely state that some specific revision(s) is being reverted,
<emphasis>not</emphasis> describe the actual code change that results
from the reversion, since the semantics of the change can be derived
by reading the original log message and change.  Of course, the
reversion's log message should also state the reason why the change is
being reverted, but it should not duplicate anything from the original
change's log message.  If possible, go back and edit the original
change's log message to point out that it was reverted.</para>

<para>All of the above implies that you should use a consistent syntax
for referring to changes.  This is helpful not only in log messages,
but in emails, the bug tracker, and elsewhere.  In Git and Mercurial,
the syntax is usually "commit bb2377" (where the commit hash code on
the right is long enough to be unique in the relevant context); in
Subversion, revision numbers are linearly incremented integers and the
standard syntax for, say, revision 1729 is "r1729".  In other systems,
there is usually a standard syntax for expressing the changeset name.
Whatever the appropriate syntax is for your system, encourage people
to use it when referring to changes.  Consistent expression of change
names makes project bookkeeping much easier (as we will see in <xref
linkend="communications"/> and <xref linkend="development-cycle"/>),
and since a lot of the bookkeeping may be done by volunteers, it
needs to be as easy as possible.</para>

<para>See also
<xref
linkend="releases-and-daily-development"/><phrase
output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="development-cycle"/></phrase>.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="vc-authz">
<title>Authorization</title>

<para>Many version control systems offer a feature whereby certain
people can be allowed or disallowed from committing in specific
sub-areas of the master repository.  Following the principle that when
handed a hammer, people start looking around for nails, many projects use
this feature with abandon, carefully granting people access to just
those areas where they have been approved to commit, and making sure
they can't commit anywhere else.  (See
<xref linkend="committers"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="managing-volunteers"/></phrase> for how projects
decide who can put changes where.)</para>

<para>Exercising such tight control is usually unnecessary, and may
even be harmful.  Some projects simply use an honor system: when a
person is granted commit access, even for a sub-area of the project,
what they actually receive is the ability to commit anywhere in the
master repository.  They're just asked to keep their commits in their
area.  Remember that there is little real risk here: the repository
provides an audit trail, and in an active project, all commits are
reviewed anyway.  If someone commits where they're not supposed to,
others will notice it and say something.  If a change needs to be
undone, that's simple enough&mdash;everything's under version control
anyway, so just revert.</para>

<para>There are several advantages to this more relaxed approach.
First, as developers expand into other areas (which they usually will
if they stay with the project), there is no administrative overhead to
granting them wider privileges.  Once the decision is made, the person
can just start committing in the new area right away.</para>

<para>Second, expansion can be done in a more fine-grained manner.
Generally, a committer in area X who wants to expand to area Y will
start posting patches against Y and asking for review.  If someone who
already has commit access to area Y sees such a patch and approves of
it, she can just tell the submitter to commit the change directly
(mentioning the reviewer/approver's name in the log message, of
course).  That way, the commit will come from the person who actually
wrote the change, which is preferable from both an information
management standpoint and from a crediting standpoint.</para>

<para>Last, and perhaps most important, using the honor system
encourages an atmosphere of trust and mutual respect.  Giving someone
commit access to a subdomain is a statement about their technical
preparedness&mdash;it says: "We see you have expertise to make commits
in a certain domain, so go for it."  But imposing strict authorization
controls says: "Not only are we asserting a limit on your expertise,
we're also a bit suspicious about
your <emphasis>intentions</emphasis>."  That's not the sort of
statement you want to make if you can avoid it.  Bringing someone into
the project as a committer is an opportunity to initiate them into a
circle of mutual trust.  A good way to do that is to give them more
power than they're supposed to use, then inform them that it's up to
them to stay within the stated limits.</para>

<para>The Subversion project has operated on this honor system way or
well over a decade, with more than 40 full committers and many more
partial committers as of this writing.  The only distinction the
system actually enforces is
between committers and non-committers; further subdivisions are
maintained solely by human judgement.  Yet the project never had a
serious problem with someone deliberately committing outside their
domain.  Once or twice there's been an innocent misunderstanding about
the extent of someone's commit privileges, but it's always been
resolved quickly and amiably.</para>

<para>Obviously, in situations where self-policing is impractical, you
must rely on hard authorization controls.  But such situations are
rare.  Even when there are millions of lines of code and hundreds or
thousands of developers, a commit to any given code module should
still be reviewed by those who work on that module, and they can
recognize if someone committed there who wasn't supposed to.  If
regular commit review <emphasis>isn't</emphasis> happening, then the
project has bigger problems to deal with than the authorization system
anyway.</para>

<para>In summary, don't spend too much time fiddling with the version
control authorization system, unless you have a specific reason to.  It
usually won't bring much tangible benefit, and there are advantages to
relying on human controls instead.</para>

<para>None of this should be taken to mean that the restrictions
themselves are unimportant, of course.  It would be bad for a project
to encourage people to commit in areas where they're not qualified.
Furthermore, in many projects, full (unrestricted) commit access has a
special corollary status: it implies voting rights on project-wide
questions.  This political aspect of commit access is discussed more
in <xref linkend="electorate"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="social-infrastructure"/></phrase>.</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<!-- ========================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="commit-review-tools">
<title>Tools for commit review</title>

<para><emphasis>9 September 2013: If you're reading this note, then
you've encountered this section while it's in the process of being
written as part of the overall update of this book (see <ulink
url="http://producingoss.com/v2.html"
>producingoss.com/v2.html</ulink>).</emphasis></para>

<para>poss2 todo: there are three main things to cover here: Gerrit
and similar tools, the GitHub PR model, and commit emails.  Intro
paragraph should give an overview and describe how they interact, then
a short section on each.  The section for commit emails is already
done as it was just moved here from its old home as a subsection of
the "Using the Version Control System" section.  Discuss how
human-centered commit review can be linked with automated buildbots
that may or may not be a hard gateway to the central repository.</para>

<!-- http://programmers.stackexchange.com/questions/173262/gerrit-code-review-or-githubs-fork-and-pull-model is worth looking at -->

<sect3 id="pull-requests">
<title>Pull requests</title>

<!-- http://julien.danjou.info/blog/2013/rant-about-github-pull-request-workflow-implementation is an interesting read for this -->

<!-- In Gitorious, and perhaps elsewhere (Phabricator?), these are
     called by the IMHO more intuitive name "merge requests".  Make
     sure to mention that too. -->

</sect3>

<sect3 id="commit-review-tbd">
<title>TBD (Gerrit et al)</title>

<!-- See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_tools_for_code_review ,
as Gerrit isn't the only thing out there, though it's probably the
most popular.  I guess Review Board is the other. -->

</sect3>

<sect3 id="commit-emails">
<title>Commit emails</title>

<para>Every commit to the repository should generate an email showing
who made the change, when they made it, what files and directories
changed, and how they changed.  The email should go to a special
mailing list devoted to commit emails, separate from the mailing lists
to which humans post.  Developers and other interested parties should
be encouraged to subscribe to the commits list, as it is the most
effective way to keep up with what's happening in the project at the
code level.  Aside from the obvious technical benefits of peer review
(see <xref linkend="code-review"/>), commit emails help create a
sense of community, because they establish a shared environment in
which people can react to events (commits) that they know are visible
to others as well.</para>

<para>The specifics of setting up commit emails will vary depending on
your version control system, but usually there's a script or other
packaged facility for doing it.  If you're having trouble finding it,
try looking for documentation on <firstterm>hooks</firstterm> (or
sometimes <firstterm>triggers</firstterm>) specifically a
<firstterm>post-commit hook</firstterm> hook.  Post-commit hooks are a
general means of launching automated tasks in response to commits.
The hook is triggered when a given commit finalizes, is fed all the
information about that commit, and is then free to use that
information to do anything&mdash;for example, to send out an
email.</para>

<para>With pre-packaged commit email systems, you may want to
modify some of the default behaviors:</para>

<orderedlist>

  <listitem>
  <para>Some commit mailers don't include the actual diffs in the
  email, but instead provide a URL to view the change on the web using
  the repository browsing system.  While it's good to provide the URL,
  so the change can be referred to later, it is also important that
  the commit email include
  the diffs themselves.  Reading email is already part of people's
  routine, so if the content of the change is visible right there in
  the commit email, developers will review the commit on the spot,
  without leaving their mail reader.  If they have to click on a URL to
  review the change, most won't do it, because that requires a new
  action instead of a continuation of what they were already doing.
  Furthermore, if the reviewer wants to ask something about the
  change, it's vastly easier to hit reply-with-text and simply
  annotate the quoted diff than it is to visit a web page and
  laboriously cut-and-paste parts of the diff from web browser to
  email client.</para>

  <para>(Of course, if the diff is huge, such as when a large body of
  new code has been added to the repository, then it makes sense to
  omit the diff and offer only the URL.  Most commit mailers can do
  this kind of size-limiting automatically.  If yours can't, then it's
  still better to include diffs, and live with the occasional huge
  email, than to leave the diffs off entirely.  Convenient reviewing
  and commenting is a cornerstone of cooperative development, and much
  too important to do without.)</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>The commit emails should set their Reply-to header
  to the regular development list, not the commit email list.  That
  is, when someone reviews a commit and writes a response, their
  response should be automatically directed toward the human
  development list, where technical issues are normally discussed.
  There are a few reasons for this.  First, you want to keep all
  technical discussion on one list, because that's where people expect
  it to happen, and because that way there's only one archive to
  search.  Second, there might be interested parties not subscribed to
  the commit email list.  Third, the commit email list advertises
  itself as a service for watching commits, not for watching commits
  <emphasis>and</emphasis> having occasional technical discussions.
  Those who subscribed to the commit email list did not sign up for
  anything but commit emails; sending them other material via that
  list would violate an implicit contract.</para>

  <para>Note that this advice to set Reply-to does not contradict the
  recommendations in
  <xref linkend="reply-to"/><phrase output="printed"> earlier in
  this chapter</phrase>.  It's
  always okay for the <emphasis>sender</emphasis> of a message to set
  Reply-to.  In this case, the sender is the version control system
  itself, and it sets Reply-to in order to indicate that the
  appropriate place for replies is the development mailing list, not
  the commit list.</para>

  </listitem>

</orderedlist>

</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1>


<!-- ========================== SECTION =========================== -->
<sect1 id="bug-tracker">
<title>Bug Tracker</title>

<para>Bug tracking is a broad topic; various aspects of it are
discussed throughout this book.  Here I'll concentrate mainly on the
features your project should look for in a bug tracker, and how to use
them.  But to get to those, we have to start with a policy question:
exactly what kind of information should be kept in a bug
tracker?</para>

<para>The term <firstterm>bug tracker</firstterm> is misleading.  Bug
tracking systems are used to track not only bug reports, but new
feature requests, one-time tasks, unsolicited patches&mdash;really
anything that has distinct beginning and end states, with optional
transition states in between, and that accrues information over its
lifetime.  For this reason, bug trackers are also called
<firstterm>issue trackers</firstterm>, <firstterm>ticket
trackers</firstterm>, <firstterm>defect trackers</firstterm>,
<firstterm>artifact trackers</firstterm>, <firstterm>request
trackers</firstterm>, etc.</para>

<para>In this book, I'll generally use the word
<firstterm>ticket</firstterm> to refer the items in the tracker's
database, because that distinguishes between the behavior that the
user encountered or proposed&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;that is, the bug or
feature itself&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;and the tracker's ongoing
<emphasis>record</emphasis> of that discovery, diagnosis, discussion,
and eventual resolution.  But note that many projects use the word
<emphasis>bug</emphasis> or <emphasis>issue</emphasis> to refer to
both the ticket itself and to the underlying behavior or goal that the
ticket is tracking.  (In fact, those usages are probably more common than
"ticket"; it's just that in this book we need to be able to make that
distinction explicitly in a way that projects themselves usually
don't.)</para>

<para>The classic ticket life cycle looks like this:

<orderedlist>
  <listitem><para>Someone files the ticket.  They provide a summary, an
            initial description (including a reproduction recipe, if
            applicable; see
            <xref
            linkend="users-to-volunteers"/><phrase
            output="printed"> in
            <xref linkend="managing-volunteers"/></phrase> for
            how to encourage good bug reports), and whatever other
            information the tracker asks for.  The person who files
            the ticket may be totally unknown to the project&mdash;bug
            reports and feature requests are as likely to come from
            the user community as from the developers.</para>

            <para>Once filed, the ticket is in what's called an
            <firstterm>open</firstterm> state.  Because no action has
            been taken yet, some trackers also label it as
            <firstterm>unverified</firstterm> and/or
            <firstterm>unstarted</firstterm>.  It is not assigned to
            anyone; or, in some systems, it is assigned to a fake
            user to represent the lack of real assignation.  At this
            point, it is in a holding area: the ticket has been
            recorded, but not yet integrated into the project's
            consciousness.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>Others read the ticket, add comments to it, and
            perhaps ask the original filer for clarification on some
            points.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>The bug gets <firstterm>reproduced</firstterm>.
            This may be the most important moment in its
            life cycle.  Although the bug is not actually fixed yet,
            the fact that someone besides the original filer was able
            to make it happen proves that it is genuine, and, no less
            importantly, confirms to the original filer that they've
            contributed to the project by reporting a real bug.
            <emphasis>(This step and some of the others don't apply to
            feature proposals, task tickets, etc, of course.  But most
            filings are for genuine bugs, so we'll focus on that
            here.)</emphasis></para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>The bug gets <firstterm>diagnosed</firstterm>: its
            cause is identified, and if possible, the effort required
            to fix it is estimated.  Make sure these things get
            recorded in the ticket; if the person who diagnosed the
            bug suddenly has to step away from it for a
            while, someone else should be able to pick up where she
            left off.</para>

            <para>In this stage, or sometimes in the previous one,
            a developer may "take ownership" of the ticket and
            <firstterm>assign</firstterm> it to herself (<xref
            linkend="delegation-assignment"/><phrase
            output="printed"> in
            <xref linkend="managing-volunteers"/></phrase>
            examines the assignment process in more detail).  The ticket's
            <firstterm>priority</firstterm> may also be set at this
            stage.  For example, if it is so important that it should
            delay the next release, that fact needs to be identified
            early, and the tracker should have some way of noting
            it.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>The ticket gets scheduled for resolution.
            Scheduling doesn't necessarily mean naming a date by which
            it will be fixed.  Sometimes it just means deciding which
            future release (not necessarily the next one) the bug
            should be fixed by, or deciding that it need not block any
            particular release.  Scheduling may also be dispensed
            with, if the bug is quick to fix.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>The bug gets fixed (or the task completed, or
            the patch applied, or whatever).  The change or set of
            changes that fixed it should be discoverable from
            the ticket.  After this, the ticket is
            <firstterm>closed</firstterm> and/or marked as
            <firstterm>resolved</firstterm>.</para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>

</para>

<para>There are some common variations on this life cycle.  Sometimes
a ticket is closed very soon after being filed, because it turns out
not to be a bug at all, but rather a misunderstanding on the part of
the user.  As a project acquires more users, more and more such
invalid tickets will come in, and developers will close them with
increasingly short-tempered responses.  Try to guard against the
latter tendency.  It does no one any good, as the individual user in
each case is not responsible for all the previous invalid tickets; the
statistical trend is visible only from the developers' point of view,
not the user's.  (In
<xref linkend="bug-filtering"/><phrase output="printed"> later
in this chapter,</phrase> we'll look at
techniques for reducing the number of invalid tickets.)  Also, if
different users are experiencing the same misunderstanding over and
over, it might mean that aspect of the software needs to be
redesigned.  This sort of pattern is easiest to notice when there is
an issue manager monitoring the bug database; see
<xref linkend="issue-manager"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="managing-volunteers"/></phrase>.</para>

<para>Another common life event for the ticket to be closed
as a <firstterm>duplicate</firstterm> soon after Step 1.  A duplicate
is when someone reports something that's already known to the project.
Duplicates are not confined to open tickets: it's possible for a bug to
come back after having been fixed (this is known as a
<firstterm>regression</firstterm>), in which case a reasonable course
is to reopen the original ticket and close any new reports as
duplicates of the original one.  The bug tracking system should keep
track of this relationship bidirectionally, so that reproduction
information in the duplicates is available to the original ticket, and
vice versa.</para>

<para>A third variation is for the developers to close the ticket,
thinking they have fixed it, only to have the original reporter reject
the fix and reopen it.  This is usually because the developers simply
don't have access to the environment necessary to reproduce the bug,
or because they didn't test the fix using the exact same reproduction
recipe as the reporter.</para>

<para>Aside from these variations, there may be other small details of
the life cycle that vary depending on the tracking software.  But the
basic shape is the same, and while the life cycle itself is not
specific to open source software, it has implications for how open
source projects use their bug trackers.</para>

<para>The tracker is as much a public face of the project as the
mailing lists or web pages.  Anyone may file a ticket, anyone may look
at a ticket, and anyone may browse the list of currently open tickets.
It follows that you never know how many people are waiting to see
progress on a given ticket.  While the size and skill of the
development community constrains the rate at which tickets can be
resolved, the project should at least try to acknowledge each ticket
the moment it appears.  Even if the ticket lingers for a while, a
response encourages the reporter to stay involved, because she feels
that a human has registered what she has done (remember that filing a
ticket usually involves more effort than, say, posting an email).
Furthermore, once a ticket is seen by a developer, it enters the
project's consciousness, in the sense that the developer can be on the
lookout for other instances of the ticket, can talk about it with
other developers, etc.</para>

<para>This centrality to the life of the project implies a few things
about trackers' technical features:

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>The tracker should be connected to email, such that
    every change to a ticket, including its initial filing, causes a
    notification mail to go out to some set of appropriate
    recipients.  See <xref linkend="bug-tracker-email-interaction"/>
    later in this chapter for more on this.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>The form for filing tickets should have a place to record
    the reporter's email address or other contact information, so she
    can be contacted for more details.  But if possible, it should not
    <emphasis>require</emphasis> the reporter's email address or real
    identity, as some people prefer to report anonymously.  See <xref
    linkend="anonymity"/><phrase output="printed"> later in this
    chapter</phrase> for more on the importance of anonymity.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>The tracker should have APIs.  I cannot stress the
    importance of this enough.  If there is no way to interact with
    the tracker programmatically, then in the long run there is no way
    to interact with it scalably.  APIs provide a route to customizing
    the behavior of the tracker by, in effect, expanding it to include
    third-party software.  Instead of being just the specific ticket
    tracking software running on a server somewhere, it's that
    software <emphasis>plus</emphasis> whatever custom behaviors your
    project implements elsewhere and plugs in to the tracker via the
    APIs.</para>
    <para>Also, if your project uses a proprietary ticket tracker,
    as is becoming more common now that so many projects host their
    code on proprietary-but-free-of-charge hosting sites and just use
    the site's built-in tracker, APIs provide a way to avoid being
    locked in to that hosting platform.  You can, in theory, take the
    ticket history with you if you choose to go somewhere else (you
    may never exercise this option, but think of it as
    insurance&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;and some projects have actually done
    it).</para>
    <para>Currently, the ticket trackers of the big three hosting
    sites (GitHub, Google Code Hosting, and SourceForge) all have
    APIs, fortunately.  Of them, only SourceForge is itself open
    source, running a platform called
    <firstterm>Allura</firstterm><footnote><para>Oddly, SourceForge's
    API was also the hardest to find documentation for, though it
    helps once you know the platform's name is "Allura".  For
    reference, their API documentation is here: <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/p/forge/documentation/Allura%20API/"
    >sourceforge.net/p/forge/documentation/Allura%20API</ulink
    ></para></footnote>.</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</para>

<sect2 id="bug-tracker-email-interaction">
<!-- For link compatibility with old section ID. -->
<anchor id="bug-tracker-mailing-list-interaction" />
<title>Interaction with Email</title>

<para>Most trackers now have at least decent email integration
features: at a minimum, the ability to create new tickets by email,
the ability to "subscribe" to a ticket to receive
emails about activity on that ticket, and the ability to add new
comments to a ticket by email.  Some trackers even allow one to
manipulate ticket state (e.g., change the status field, the assignee,
etc) by email, and for people who use the tracker a lot, such as an
<xref linkend="issue-manager" >issue manager</xref>, that can make a
huge difference in their ability to stay on top of tracker activity
and keep things organized.</para>

<para>The tracker email feature that is likely to be used by everyone,
though, is simply the ability to read a ticket's activity by email and
respond by email.  This is a valuable time-saver for many people in
the project, since it makes it easy to integrate bug traffic into
one's daily email flow.  But don't let this integration give
anyone the illusion that the total collection of bug tickets and their
email traffic is the equivalent of the development mailing list.  It's
not, and <xref linkend="choose-the-forum"/><phrase output="printed">
in <xref linkend="communications"/></phrase> discusses why this is
important and how to manage the difference.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="bug-filtering">
<title>Pre-Filtering the Bug Tracker</title>

<para>Most ticket databases eventually suffer from the same problem: a
crushing load of duplicate or invalid tickets filed by well-meaning but
inexperienced or ill-informed users.  The first step in combatting
this trend is usually to put a prominent notice on the front page of
the bug tracker, explaining how to tell if a bug is really a bug, how
to search to see if it's already been reported, and finally, how to
effectively report it if one still thinks it's a new bug.</para>

<para>This will reduce the noise level for a while, but as the number
of users increases, the problem will eventually come back.  No
individual user can be blamed for it.  Each one is just trying to
contribute to the project's well-being, and even if their first bug
report isn't helpful, you still want to encourage them to stay
involved and file better tickets in the future.  In the meantime,
though, the project needs to keep the ticket database as free of junk
as possible.</para>

<para>The two things that will do the most to prevent this problem
are: making sure there are people watching the bug tracker who have
enough knowledge to close tickets as invalid or duplicates the moment
they come in, and requiring (or strongly encouraging) users to confirm
their bugs <emphasis>with other people</emphasis> before filing them
in the tracker.</para>

<para>The first technique seems to be used universally.  Even projects
with huge ticket databases (say, the Debian bug tracker at
<ulink url="http://bugs.debian.org/" >bugs.debian.org</ulink>, which
contained 739,542 tickets as of this writing) still arrange things so that
<emphasis>someone</emphasis> sees each ticket that comes in.  It may be
a different person depending on the category of the ticket.  For
example, the Debian project is a collection of software packages, so
Debian automatically routes each ticket to the appropriate package
maintainers.  Of course, users can sometimes misidentify a ticket's
category, with the result that the ticket is sent to the wrong person
initially, who may then have to reroute it.  However, the important
thing is that the burden is still shared&mdash;whether the user
guesses right or wrong when filing, ticket watching is still
distributed more or less evenly among the developers, so each ticket is
able to receive a timely response.</para>

<para>The second technique is less widespread, probably because it's
harder to automate.  The essential idea is that every new ticket gets
"buddied" into the database.  When a user thinks he's found a problem,
he is asked to describe it on one of the mailing lists, or in an IRC
channel, and get confirmation from someone that it is indeed a bug.
Bringing in that second pair of eyes early can prevent a lot of
spurious reports.  Sometimes the second party is able to identify that
the behavior is not a bug, or is fixed in recent releases.  Or she may
be familiar with the symptoms from a previous ticket, and can prevent a
duplicate filing by pointing the user to the older ticket.  Often it's
enough just to ask the user "Did you search the bug tracker to see if
it's already been reported?"  Many people simply don't think of that,
yet are happy to do the search once they know someone's
<emphasis>expecting</emphasis> them to.</para>

<para>The buddy system can really keep the ticket database clean, but
it has some disadvantages too.  Many people will file solo anyway,
either through not seeing, or through disregarding, the instructions
to find a buddy for new tickets.  Thus it is still necessary for
volunteers to watch the ticket database.  Furthermore, because most new
reporters don't understand how difficult the task of maintaining the
ticket database is, it's not fair to chide them too harshly for
ignoring the guidelines.  Thus the volunteers must be vigilant, and
yet exercise restraint in how they bounce unbuddied tickets back to
their reporters.  The goal is to train each reporter to use the
buddying system in the future, so that there is an ever-growing pool
of people who understand the ticket-filtering system.  On seeing an
unbuddied ticket, the ideal steps are:</para>

<orderedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>Immediately respond to the ticket, politely thanking the user
          for filing, but pointing them to the buddying guidelines
          (which should, of course, be prominently posted on the web
          site).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>If the ticket is clearly valid and not a duplicate, approve it
          anyway, and start it down the normal life cycle.  After all,
          the reporter's now been informed about buddying, so there's
          no point closing a valid ticket and wasting the work done so
          far.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>Otherwise, if the ticket is not clearly valid, close it, but
          ask the reporter to reopen it if they get confirmation from
          a buddy.   When they do, they should put a reference to the
          confirmation thread (e.g., a URL into the mailing list
          archives).</para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>Remember that although this system will improve the signal/noise
ratio in the ticket database over time, it will never completely stop
the misfilings.  The only way to prevent misfilings entirely is to
close off the bug tracker to everyone but developers&mdash;a cure that
is almost always worse than the disease.  It's better to accept that
cleaning out invalid tickets will always be part of the project's
routine maintenance, and to try to get as many people as possible to
help.</para>

<para>See also
<xref linkend="issue-manager"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="managing-volunteers"/></phrase>.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ========================== SECTION =========================== -->
<sect1 id="irc">
<title>IRC / Real-Time Chat Systems</title>

<para>Many projects offer real-time chat rooms using
<firstterm>Internet Relay Chat</firstterm>
(<firstterm>IRC</firstterm>), forums where users and developers can
ask each other questions and get instant responses.  IRC has been
around for a long time, and its primarily text-based interface and
command language can look old-fashioned&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;but don't be
fooled: the number of people using IRC continues to
grow<footnote><para>See <ulink url="http://freenode.net/history.shtml"
>freenode.net/history.shtml</ulink> for example.</para></footnote>,
and it is a key communications forum for many open source projects.
It's generally the only place where developers can meet in a shared
space for real-time conversation on a regular basis.</para>

<para>If you've never used IRC before, don't be daunted.  It's not
hard; although there isn't space in this book for an IRC primer,
<ulink url="http://irchelp.org/" >irchelp.org</ulink> is a good guide
to IRC usage and administration, and in particular see the tutorial at
<ulink url="http://www.irchelp.org/irchelp/irctutorial.html"
>irchelp.org/irchelp/irctutorial.html</ulink>.  While in theory your
project <emphasis>could</emphasis> run its own IRC servers, it is
generally not worth the hassle.  Instead, just do what everyone else
does: host your project's IRC channels<footnote><para>An IRC
<firstterm>channel</firstterm> is a single "chat
room"&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;a shared space in which people can "talk" to
each other using text.  A given IRC server usually hosts many
different channels.  When a user connects to the server, she chooses
which of those channels to join, or her client software remembers and
auto-joins them for her.  To speak to a particular person in an IRC
channel, it is standard to address them by their username
(<firstterm>nickname</firstterm> or <firstterm>nick</firstterm>), so
they can pick out your inquiry from the other conversation in the
room; see <ulink
url="http://www.rants.org/2013/01/09/the-irc-curmudgeon/"
>rants.org/2013/01/09/the-irc-curmudgeon</ulink> for more on this
practice.</para></footnote> at Freenode (<ulink
url="http://freenode.net/" >freenode.net</ulink>).  Freenode gives you
the control you need to administer your project's IRC channels, while
sparing you the not-insignificant trouble of maintaining an IRC server
yourself.</para>

<para>The first thing to do is choose a channel name.  The most
obvious choice is the name of your project&mdash;if that's available
at Freenode, then use it.  If not, try to choose something as close to
your project's name, and as easy to remember, as possible.  Advertise
the channel's availabity from your project's web site, so a visitor
with a quick question will see it right away.<footnote><para>In fact,
you can even offer an IRC chat portal right on your web site.  See
<ulink url="https://webchat.freenode.net/"
>webchat.freenode.net</ulink>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;from the dropdown menu
in the upper left corner, choose "Add webchat to your site" and follow
the instructions.</para></footnote>.  If your project's channel gets
too noisy, you can divide into multiple channels, for example one for
installation problems, another for usage questions, another for
development chat, etc (<xref linkend="growth"/><phrase
output="printed"> in <xref linkend="communications"/></phrase>
discusses when and how to divide into multiple channels).  But when
your project is young, there should only be one channel, with everyone
talking together.  Later, as the user-to-developer ratio increases,
separate channels may become necessary.</para>

<para>How will people know all the available channels, let alone which
channel to talk in?  And when they talk, how will they know what the
local conventions are?</para>

<para>The answer is to tell them by setting the <firstterm>channel
topic</firstterm>.<footnote><para>To set a channel topic, use the
<literal>/topic</literal> command.  All commands in IRC start with
"<literal>/</literal>".</para></footnote>  The channel topic is a brief
message each user sees when they first enter the channel.  It gives
quick guidance to newcomers, and pointers to further information.  For
example:</para>

<screen>
The Apache (TM) Subversion (R) version control system
(http://subversion.apache.org/) | Don't ask to ask; just ask your
question! | Read the book: http://www.svnbook.org/ | No one here? Try
http://subversion.apache.org/mailing-lists |
http://subversion.apache.org/faq | Subversion 1.8.8 and 1.7.16 released
</screen>

<para>That's terse, but it tells newcomers what they need to know.  It
says exactly what the channel is for, gives the project home page (in
case someone wanders into the channel without having first been to the
project web site), gives a pointer to some documentation, and gives
recent release news.</para>

<sidebar id="paste-sites">
<title>Paste Sites</title>

<para>An IRC channel is a shared space: everyone can see what everyone
else is saying.  Normally, this is a good thing, as it allows people
to jump into a conversation when they think they have something to
contribute, and allows spectators to learn by watching.  But it
becomes problematic when someone has to provide a large quantity of
information at once, such as a large error message or a transcript
from a debugging session, because pasting too many lines of output
into the room will disrupt other conversations.</para>

<para>The solution is to use one of the
<firstterm>pastebin</firstterm> or <firstterm>pastebot</firstterm>
sites.  When requesting a large amount of data from someone, ask them
not to paste it into the channel, but instead to go to (for example)
<ulink url="http://pastebin.ca/" >pastebin.ca</ulink>, paste their
data into the form there, and tell the resulting new URL to the IRC
channel.  Anyone can then visit the URL and view the data.</para>

<para>There are many free paste sites available, far too many for a
comprehensive list.  Three that I seen used a lot are GitHub Gists
(<ulink url="https://gist.github.com/" >gist.github.com</ulink>),
<ulink url="http://paste.lisp.org/" >paste.lisp.org</ulink> and <ulink
url="http://pastebin.ca/" >pastebin.ca</ulink>.  But there are many
other fine ones, and it's okay if different people in your IRC channel
choose to use different paste sites.</para>
</sidebar>

<sect2 id="irc-bots">
<!-- For link compatibility with the old section ID. -->
<anchor id="bots" />
<title>IRC Bots</title>

<para>Many technically-oriented IRC channels have a non-human member,
a so-called <firstterm>bot</firstterm>, that is capable of storing and
regurgitating information in response to specific commands.
Typically, the bot is addressed just like any other member of the
channel, that is, the commands are delivered by "speaking to" the bot.
For example:</para>

<screen>
&lt;kfogel&gt; wayita: learn diff-cmd = http://subversion.apache.org/faq.html#diff-cmd
&lt;wayita&gt; Thanks!
</screen>

<para>That told the bot, who is logged into the channel as wayita, to
remember a certain URL as the answer to the query "diff-cmd" (wayita
responded, confirming with a "Thanks!").  Now we can address wayita,
asking the bot to tell another user about diff-cmd:</para>

<screen>
&lt;kfogel&gt; wayita: tell jrandom about diff-cmd
&lt;wayita&gt; jrandom: http://subversion.apache.org/faq.html#diff-cmd
</screen>

<para>The same thing can be accomplished via a convenient shorthand:</para>

<screen>
&lt;kfogel&gt; !a jrandom diff-cmd
&lt;wayita&gt; jrandom: http://subversion.apache.org/faq.html#diff-cmd
</screen>

<para>The exact command set and behaviors differ from bot to bot
(unfortunately, the diversity of IRC bot command languages seems to be
rivaled only by the diversity of wiki syntaxes).  The above example
happens to be with <literal>wayita</literal> (<ulink
url="http://repos.borg.ch/svn/wayita/trunk/"
>repos.borg.ch/svn/wayita/trunk</ulink>), of which there is usually an
instance running in <literal>#svn</literal> at Freenode, but there are
many other IRC bots available.  Note that no special server privileges
are required to run a bot.  A bot is just like any other user joining
a channel.</para>

<para>If your channel tends to get the same questions over and over,
I highly recommend setting up a bot.  Only a small percentage of
channel users will acquire the expertise needed to manipulate the bot,
but those users will answer a disproportionately high percentage of
questions, because the bot enables them to respond so much more
efficiently.</para>

<sect3 id="irc-commit-notifications">
<!-- For link compatibility with the old section ID. -->
<anchor id="cia" />
<title>Commit Notifications in IRC</title>

<para>You can also configure a bot to watch your project's version
control repository and broadcast commit activity to the relevant IRC
channels.  Though of somewhat less technical utility than commit
emails, since observers might or might not be around when a commit
notice pops up in IRC, this technique is of immense
<emphasis>social</emphasis> utility.  People get the sense of being
part of something alive and active, and feel that they can see
progress being made right before their eyes.  And because the
notifications appear in a shared space, people in the chat room will
often react in real time, reviewing the commit and commenting on it on
the spot.  The technical details of setting this up are beyond the
scope of this book, but it's usually worth the effort.  This service
used to be provided in an easy-to-use way by the much-missed <ulink
url="http://cia.vc/" >cia.vc</ulink>, which shut down in 2011, but
several replacements are available: Notifico (<ulink
url="http://n.tkte.ch/" >n.tkte.ch</ulink>), Irker (<ulink
url="http://www.catb.org/esr/irker/" >catb.org/esr/irker</ulink>), and
KGB (<ulink url="http://kgb.alioth.debian.org/"
>kgb.alioth.debian.org</ulink>).</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="irc-archiving">
<title>Archiving IRC</title>

<para>Although it is possible to publicly archive everything that
happens in an IRC channel, it's not necessarily expected.  IRC
conversations are nominally public, but many people think of them as
informal and ephemeral conversations.  Users may be careless with
grammar, and often express opinions (for example, about other software
or other programmers) that they wouldn't want preserved forever in a
searchable online archive.  Of course, there will sometimes be
<emphasis>excerpts</emphasis> that get quoted elsewhere, and that's
fine.  But indiscriminate public logging may make some users uneasy.
If you do archive everything, make sure you state so clearly in the
channel topic, and give a URL to the archive.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ========================== SECTION =========================== -->
<sect1 id="rss">
<title>RSS Feeds</title>

<para><firstterm>RSS</firstterm> (Really Simple Syndication) is a
mechanism for distributing meta-data-rich news summaries to
"subscribers", that is, people who have indicated an interest in
receiving those summaries.  A given RSS source is usually called
a <firstterm>feed</firstterm>, and the user's subscription interface
is called a <firstterm>feed reader</firstterm> or <firstterm>feed
aggregator</firstterm>.  <ulink url="http://www.rssbandit.org/">RSS
Bandit</ulink> and the eponymous
<ulink url="http://www.feedreader.com/">Feedreader</ulink> are two
open source RSS readers, for example.</para>

<para>There is not space here for a detailed technical explanation of
RSS<footnote><para>See
<ulink url="http://www.xml.com/pub/a/2002/12/18/dive-into-xml.html"
>xml.com/pub/a/2002/12/18/dive-into-xml.html</ulink>
for that.</para></footnote>, but you should be aware of two main
things.  First, the feed reading software is chosen by the subscriber
and is <emphasis>the same</emphasis> for all the feeds that subscriber
monitors&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;in fact, this is the major selling point of
RSS: that the subscriber chooses one interface to use for all their
feeds, so each feed can concentrate just on delivering content.
Second, RSS is now ubiquitous, so much so that most people who use it
don't even know they're using it.  To the world at large, RSS looks
like a little button on a web page, with a label saying "Subscribe to
this site" or "News feed".  You click on the button, and from then on,
your feed reader (which may well be an applet embedded in your home
page) automatically updates whenever there's news from the
site.</para>

<para>This means that your open source project should probably offer
an RSS feed (note that many of the canned hosting
sites&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;see
<xref linkend="canned-hosting"/>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;offer it right out
of the box).  Be careful not to post so many news items each day that
subscribers can't separate the wheat from the chaff.  If there are too
many news events, people will just ignore the feed, or even
unsubscribe in exasperation.  Ideally, a project would offer separate
feeds, one for big announcements, another following (say) events in
the ticket tracker, another for each mailing list, etc.  In practice,
this is hard to do well: it can result in interface confusion both for
visitors to the project's web site and for the administrators.  But at
a minimum, the project should offer one RSS feed on the front page,
for sending out major announcements such as releases and security
alerts.<footnote><para>Credit where credit is due: this section wasn't
in the first published edition of the book, but Brian Aker's blog
entry
<ulink url="http://krow.livejournal.com/564980.html">"Release Criteria,
Open Source, Thoughts On..."</ulink> reminded me of the usefulness of
RSS feeds for open source projects.</para></footnote></para>

<!-- TODO Rex Karz recommends http://lzone.de/liferea/ as a mature
     feedreader; is using it as a replacement for Google Reader.
     Not sure if we want to recommend feed readers though. -->

</sect1>

<!-- ========================== SECTION =========================== -->
<sect1 id="wikis">
<title>Wikis</title>

<para>When open source software project wikis go bad, they usually go
bad for the same reasons: lack of consistent organization and editing,
leading to a mess of outdated and redundant pages, and lack of clarity
on who the target audience is for a given page or section.</para>

<para>A well-run wiki can be a wonderful thing for users, however, and
is worth some effort to maintain.  Try to have a clear page
organization strategy and even a pleasing visual layout, so that
visitors (i.e., potential editors) will instinctively know how to fit
their contributions in.  Make sure the intended audience is clear at
all times to all editors.  Most importantly, document these standards
in the wiki itself and point people to them, so editors have somewhere
to go for guidance.  Too often, wiki administrators fall victim to the
fantasy that because hordes of visitors are individually adding high
quality content to the site, the sum of all these contributions must
therefore also be of high quality.  That's not how collaborative
editing works.  Each individual page or paragraph may be good when
considered by itself, but it will not be good if embedded in a
disorganized or confusing whole.</para>

<para>In general, wikis will amplify any failings that are present
from early on, since contributors tend to imitate whatever patterns
they see in front of them.  So don't just set up the wiki and hope
everything falls into place.  You must also prime it with well-written
content, so people have a template to follow.</para>

<para>The shining example of a well-run wiki is Wikipedia, of course,
and in some ways it makes a poor example because it gets so much more
editorial attention than any other wiki in the world.  Still, if you
examine Wikipedia closely, you'll see that its administrators laid a
<emphasis>very</emphasis> thorough foundation for cooperation.  There
is extensive documentation on how to write new entries, how to
maintain an appropriate point of view, what sorts of edits to make,
what edits to avoid, a dispute resolution process for contested edits
(involving several stages, including eventual arbitration), and so
forth.  They also have authorization controls, so that if a page is
the target of repeated inappropriate edits, they can lock it down
until the problem is resolved.  In other words, they didn't just throw
some templates onto a web site and hope for the best.  Wikipedia works
because its founders give careful thought to getting thousands of
strangers to tailor their writing to a common vision.  While you may
not need the same level of preparedness to run a wiki for a free
software project, the spirit is worth emulating.</para>

<sect2 id="wiki-spam">
<title>Wikis and Spam</title>

<para>Never allow open, anonymous editing on your wiki.  The days when
that was possible are <emphasis>long</emphasis> gone now; today, any
open wiki other than Wikipedia will be covered completely with spam in
approximately 3 milliseconds.  (Wikipedia is an exception because it
has an exceptionally large number of readers willing to clean up spam
quickly, and because it has a well-funded organization behind it
devoted to resisting spam using various large-scale monitoring
techniques not practically available to smaller projects.)</para>

<para>All edits in your project's wiki must come from registered
users; if your wiki software doesn't already enforce this by default,
then configure it to enforce that.  Even then you may need to keep
watch for spam edits from users who registered under false pretences
for the purpose of spamming.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="wiki-choosing">
<title>Choosing a Wiki</title>

<para>If your project is on GitHub or some other free hosting site,
it's usually best to use the built-in wiki feature that most such
sites offer.  That way your wiki will be automatically integrated with
your repository or other project permissions, and you can rely on the
site's user account system instead of having a separate registration
system for the wiki.</para>

<para>If you are setting up your own wiki, then you're free to choose
which one, and fortunately there are plenty of good free software wiki
implementations available.  I've had good experience with DokuWiki
(<ulink url="https://www.dokuwiki.org/dokuwiki"
>dokuwiki.org/dokuwiki</ulink>), but there are many others.  There is
a wonderful tool called the Wiki Choice Wizard at <ulink
url="http://www.wikimatrix.org/" >wikimatrix.org</ulink> that allows
you to specify the features you care about (an open source license can
be one of them) and then view a chart comparing all the wiki software
that meets those criteria.  Another good resource is Wikipedia's own
list of wikis: <ulink
url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_wiki_software"
>en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_wiki_software</ulink>.</para>

<para>I do not recommend using MediaWiki (<ulink
url="https://www.mediawiki.org" >mediawiki.org</ulink>) as the wiki
software for most projects.  MediaWiki is the software on which
Wikipedia itself runs, and while it is very good at that, its
administrative facilities are tuned to the needs of a site unlike any
other wiki on the Net&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;and actually not so well-tuned
to the needs of smaller editing communities.  Many projects are
tempted to choose MediaWiki because they think it will be easier for
users who already know its editing syntax from having edited at
Wikipedia, but this turns out to be an almost non-existent advantage
for several reasons.  First, wikis in general, including Wikipedia,
are tending toward rich-text in-browser editing anyway, so that no one
really needs to learn the underlying wiki syntax unless they aim to be
a power user.  Second, many other wikis offer a MediaWiki-syntax
plugin, so you can have that syntax anyway if you really want it.
Third, for those who will use a plaintext syntax instead of rich-text
editing, it's better to use a standardized generic markup format like
Markdown (<ulink url="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/"
>daringfireball.net/projects/markdown</ulink>), which is available in
many wikis either natively or via a plugin, than to use a wiki syntax
of any flavor.  If you support Markdown, then people can edit in your
wiki using the same markup syntax they already know from GitHub and
other popular tools.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="q-and-a-forums">
<title>Q&amp;A Forums</title>

<para>In the past few years, online question-and-answer forums (or
<firstterm>Q&amp;A forums</firstterm>) have gone from being an
afterthought offered by the occasional project to an increasingly
expected and normal component of user-facing services.  A high-quality
Q&amp;A forum is like a FAQ with nearly real-time
updates&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;indeed, if your Q&amp;A forum is
sufficiently healthy, it often makes sense to either use it directly
as your project's FAQ, or have the FAQ consist mostly of pointers to
the forum's most popular items.</para>

<para>A project can certainly host its own forums, and many do, using
free software such as <ulink url="http://askbot.com" >Askbot</ulink>,
<ulink url="http://osqa.net" >OSQA</ulink>, <ulink
url="http://shapado.com/" >Shapado</ulink>, or <ulink
url="http://www.coordino.com/" >Coordino</ulink>.  However, there are
also some third-party services that aggregate questions and answers,
the best-known of which, <ulink url="http://stackoverflow.com/"
>stackoverflow.com</ulink>, frequently has its answers coming up first
in generic search engine results for popular questions.</para>

<para>While Stack Overflow hosts Q&amp;A about many things, not just
about open source projects, it seems to have found the right
combination of cultural guidelines and upvoting/downvoting features to
enable its contributors to quickly narrow in on good answers for
questions about open source software in particular.  (The questions
and answers on Stack Overflow are freely licensed, although the code
that runs the site itself is not open source.)  On the other hand,
projects that host their own Q&amp;A forums are lately doing pretty
well in search engine results too.  It may be that the current
dominance of Stack Overflow, as of this writing in 2014, is partly
just an accident of timing, and that the real lesson is that
Q&amp;A-style forums are an important addition to the free software
project communications toolbox&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;one that scales
better with user base than many other tools do.</para>

<para>There is no definite answer to the question of whether or when
you should set up dedicated Q&amp;A forums for your project.  It
depends on available resources, on the type of project, the
demographics of the user community, etc.  But do keep an eye out for
Stack Overflow results, or other third-party results, coming up in
generic question-style searches about your project. Their presence may
indicate that it's time to consider setting up a dedicated Q&amp;A
forum.  Whether you do or not, the project can still learn a lot from
looking at what people are asking on Stack Overflow, and at the
responses.</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="social-networking">
<title>Social Networking Services</title>

<para><emphasis>24 March 2013: If you're reading this note, then
you've encountered this section while it's undergoing substantial
revision; see <ulink url="http://producingoss.com/v2.html"
>producingoss.com/v2.html</ulink> for details.</emphasis></para>

<para>poss2 tbd: subsections for Twitter, Facebook, any others.
Twitter is useful; Facebook appears not to be so relevant to open
source projects but check this with people who use it more.  Identi.ca
(if will persist).  Others?  Eventbrite (mention from
"meeting-in-person" section), what else?  Acknowledge that many of
these services are not open source; times have changed, the train has
left the barn or the horse has left the station or whatever.  One good
example: LibreOffice's "@AskLibreOffice" tweet stream at <ulink
url="https://twitter.com/AskLibreOffice"
>twitter.com/AskLibreOffice</ulink>.  See also <ulink
url="http://ask.libreoffice.org/en/questions/"
>ask.libreoffice.org</ulink>
</para>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->

</sect1>

</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->

