<appendix id="vc-systems">
<title>Free Version Control Systems</title>

<simplesect>

<para>Dessa är alla versionskontrollsystem av öppen källkod
jag var medveten om vid mitten av 2007. Den enda jag använder
regelbundet är Subversion. Jag har liten eller ingen erfarenhet
av dom flesta av dessa system, förutom Subversion och CVS;
informationen här är tagen från respektives hemsidor. Se även 
<ulink
url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_revision_control_software"/>.
</para>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-cvs">
<title><emphasis role="bold">CVS</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://www.nongnu.org/cvs/"/></title>

<para>CVS har hängt med länge, och många utvecklare är bekanta med det.
I dess dagar var det revolutionerande: det var det första
versionskontrollsystemet gjort i öppen mjukvara som hade WAN-access
för utvecklare (mig veterligen), och den första att erbjuda anonym
läsbehörighet för utcheckningar, vilket underlättade för nya
utvecklare att engagera sig i projekt. CVS versionsfiler endast,
inga kataloger; detta medför förgrening, taggning, och god 
prestanda på klientsidan, men hanterar ej stora filer, eller binära
filer särskilt väl. Det stödjer inte heller atomiska uppdateringar.
<emphasis>[Disclaimer: Jag var aktiv i utvecklingen av CVS
i ungefär fem år, före jag hjälpte till att starta upp
efterföljaren Subversion.]</emphasis></para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-subversion">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Subversion</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://subversion.tigris.org/"/></title>

<para>Subversion skrevs i första hand som en ersättare till CVS&mdash;
alltså, samma förhållningssätt till versionskontrollen som CVS, men
utan de problem och den avsaknad av funktioner som irriterar användare
av CVS. Ett av Subversions mål var att dessa vana användare skulle finna
övergången till Subversion någorlunda smärtfri. Det finns inte utrymme här
för detaljer om Subversions egenskaper; besök websidan för mer information.
<emphasis>[Disclaimer: Jag är involverad i utvecklingen av Subversion,
och det är det enda av dessa system jag använder mig av regelbundet.]
</emphasis></para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-svk">
<title><emphasis role="bold">SVK</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://svk.elixus.org/"/></title>

<para>Trots att det är baserat på Subversion, så påminner nog
SVK mer om ett av de decentraliserade systemen som följer än om 
Subversion. SVK erbjuder distribuerad utveckling, lokala uppdateringar,
sofistikerad sammansmältning av ändringar, och förmåga at avspegla
katalogstrukturer från andra, icke-SVK, versionskontrollsystem. 
Se websidan för fler detaljer.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-mercurial">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Mercurial</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://www.selenic.com/mercurial/"/></title>

<para>Mercurial är ett distribuerat versionskontrollsystem som
erbjuder bl.a. "komplett korsindexering av filer och ändringar;
effektiva HTTP- och SSH-protokoll, ur bandbredd och CPU synpunkt;
godtycklig ihopslagning mellan utvecklingsgrenar; integrerat,
självständigt webgränssnitt; [portabilitet till] UNIX, MacOS X,
och Windows" m.fl. (den föregående listan av funktioner var
parafraserad från Mercurials websida).</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-git">
<title><emphasis role="bold">GIT</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://git.or.cz/"/></title>

<para>GIT is a project started by Linus Torvalds to manage the Linux
kernel source tree.  At first GIT was rather narrowly focused on the
needs of kernel development, but it has expanded beyond that and is
now used by projects other than the Linux kernel.  Its home page says
it is "...designed to handle very large projects with speed and
efficiency; it is used mainly for various open source projects, most
notably the Linux kernel.  Git falls in the category of distributed
source code management tools, similar to e.g. GNU Arch or Monotone (or
BitKeeper in the proprietary world).  Every Git working directory is a
full-fledged repository with full revision tracking capabilities, not
dependent on network access or a central server."</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-bazaar">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Bazaar</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://bazaar-vcs.org/"/></title>

<para>Bazaar (or bzr) is a distributed version control system that
concentrates on ease-of-use and having a flexible data model.  It is
an official GNU project, and is the native version control system for
the free software project-hosting site Launchpad.net.  Bazaar does
fully distributed version control: all work takes place in branches,
and every developer typically has a full copy of the branch history.
Branches can be merged into one another in a decentralized manner, but
Bazaar can also be configured to work in a centralized way.  Bazaar
started out as a fork of GNU Arch, but was rewritten from scratch and
now has no direct relation to GNU Arch.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-darcs">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Darcs</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://darcs.net"/></title>

<para>"David's Advanced Revision Control System is yet another
replacement for CVS.  It is written in Haskell, and has been used on
Linux, MacOS X, FreeBSD, OpenBSD and Microsoft Windows.  Darcs
includes a cgi script, which can be used to view the contents of your
repository."</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-arch">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Arch</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://www.gnu.org/software/gnu-arch/"/></title>

<para>GNU Arch supports both distributed and centralized development.
Developers commit their changes to an "archive", which may be local,
and the changes can be pushed and pulled to other archives as the
managers of those archives see fit.  As such a methodology implies,
Arch has more sophisticated merge support than CVS.  Arch also allows
one to easily make branches of archives to which one does not have
commit access.  This is only a brief summary; see the Arch web pages
for details.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-monotone">
<title><emphasis role="bold">monotone</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://www.venge.net/monotone/"/></title>

<para>"monotone is a free distributed version control system.  it
provides a simple, single-file transactional version store, with fully
disconnected operation and an efficient peer-to-peer synchronization
protocol.  it understands history-sensitive merging, lightweight
branches, integrated code review and 3rd party testing.  it uses
cryptographic version naming and client-side RSA certificates.  it has
good internationalization support, has no external dependencies, runs
on linux, solaris, OSX, and windows, and is licensed under the GNU
GPL."</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-codeville">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Codeville</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://codeville.org/"/></title>

<para>"Why yet another version control system? All other version
control systems require that you keep careful track of the
relationships between branches so as not have to repeatedly merge the
same conflicts.  Codeville is much more anarchic.  It allows you to
update from or commit to any repository at any time with no
unnecessary re-merges."</para>

<para>"Codeville works by creating an identifier for each change which
is done, and remembering the list of all changes which have been
applied to each file and the last change which modified each line in
each file.  When there's a conflict, it checks to see if one of the
two sides has already been applied to the other one, and if so makes
the other side win automatically.  When there's an actual not
automatically mergeable version conflict, Codeville behaves in almost
exactly the same way as CVS."</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-vesta">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Vesta</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://www.vestasys.org/"/></title>

<para>"Vesta is a portable SCM [Software Configuration Management]
system targeted at supporting development of software systems of
almost any size, from fairly small (under 10,000 source lines) to very
large (10,000,000 source lines)."</para>

<para>"Vesta is a mature system.  It is the result of over 10 years of
research and development at the Compaq/Digital Systems Research
Center, and it was in production use by Compaq's Alpha microprocessor
group for over two and a half years.  The Alpha group had over 150
active developers at two sites thousands of miles apart, on the east
and west coasts of the United States.  The group used Vesta to manage
builds with as much as 130 MB of source data, each producing 1.5 GB of
derived data.  The builds done at the eastern site in an average day
produced about 10-15 GB of derived data, all managed by Vesta.
Although Vesta was designed with software development in mind, the
Alpha group demonstrated the system's flexibility by using it for
hardware development, checking their hardware description language
files into Vesta's source code control facility and building
simulators and other derived objects with Vesta's builder.  The
members of the former Alpha group, now a part of Intel, are continuing
to use Vesta today in a new microprocessor project."</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-aegis">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Aegis</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://aegis.sourceforge.net/"/></title>

<para>"Aegis is a transaction-based software configuration management
system.  It provides a framework within which a team of developers may
work on many changes to a program independently, and Aegis coordinates
integrating these changes back into the master source of the program,
with as little disruption as possible."</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-cvsnt">
<title><emphasis role="bold">CVSNT</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://cvsnt.org/"/></title>

<para>"CVSNT is an advanced multiplatform version control system.
Compatible with the industry standard CVS protocol it now supports
many more features. ... CVSNT is Open Source, Free software licensed
under the GNU General Public License."  Its feature list includes
authentication via all standard CVS protocols, plus Windows specific
SSPI and Active Directory; secure transport support, via sserver or
encrypted SSPI; cross platform (runs in Windows or Unix environments);
NT version is fully integrated with Win32 system; MergePoint
processing means no more tagging to merge; under active
development.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-meta-cvs">
<title><emphasis role="bold">META-CVS</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://common-lisp.net/project/meta-cvs/"/></title>

<para>"Meta-CVS is a version control system built around CVS.
Although it retains most of the features of CVS, including all of the
networking support, it is more capable than CVS, and easier to use."
The features listed on META-CVS's web site include: directory
structure versioning, improved file type handling, simpler and more
user-friendly branching and merging, support for symbolic links,
property lists attached to versioned data, improved third-party data
importing, and easy upgrading from stock CVS.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-opencm">
<title><emphasis role="bold">OpenCM</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://www.opencm.org/"/></title>

<para>"OpenCM is designed as a secure, high-integrity replacement for
CVS.  A list of the key features can be found on the features page.
While not as 'feature rich' as CVS, it supports some useful things
that CVS lacks.  Briefly, OpenCM provides first-class support for
renames and configuration, cryptographic authentication and access
control, and first-class branches."</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-prcs">
<title><emphasis role="bold">PRCS</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://prcs.sourceforge.net/"/></title>

<para>"PRCS, the Project Revision Control System, is the front end to
a set of tools that (like CVS) provide a way to deal with sets of
files and directories as an entity, preserving coherent versions of
the entire set. ... Its purpose is similar to that of SCCS, RCS, and
CVS, but (according to its authors, at least), it is much simpler than
any of those systems."</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-arx">
<title><emphasis role="bold">ArX</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://www.nongnu.org/arx/"/></title>

<para>ArX is a distributed version control system offering branching
and merging features, cryptographic data integrity verification, and
the ability to publish archives easily on any HTTP server.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-sourcejammer">
<title><emphasis role="bold">SourceJammer</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://www.sourcejammer.org/"/></title>

<para>"SourceJammer is a source control and versioning system written
in Java.  It consists of a server-side component that maintains the
files and version history, and handles check-in, check-out, etc. and
other commands; and a client-side component that makes requests of the
server and manages the files on the client-side file system."</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-fastcst">
<title><emphasis role="bold">FastCST</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://www.zedshaw.com/projects/fastcst/index.html"/></title>

<para>"A 'modern' system that uses changesets over file revisions and
distributed operation rather than centralized control.  As long as you
have an e-mail account you can use FastCST.  For larger distribution
you only need an FTP server and/or an HTTP server or use the built in
'serve' command to serve your stuff up directly.  All changesets are
universally unique and have tons of meta-data so you can reject
anything you don't [want] before you try it.  Merging is done by comparing a
merged changeset against the current directory contents, rather than
trying to merge it with another changeset."</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="vc-superversion">
<title><emphasis role="bold">Superversion</emphasis>&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;<ulink
        url="http://www.superversion.org/"/></title>

<para>"Superversion is a multi-user distributed version control system
based on change sets. It aims to be an industrial-strength, open
source alternative to commercial solutions that is equally easy to use
(or even easier) and similarly powerful. In fact, intuitive and
efficient usability has been one of the top priorities in
Superversion's development from the very beginning."</para>

</sect2>

</simplesect>

</appendix>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "appendix")
end:
-->
