<preface id="producingoss.jp.foreword">

  <prefaceinfo>
    <author>
      <firstname>Karl</firstname>
      <surname>Fogel</surname>
    </author>
    <pubdate>New York, 6 May, 2009</pubdate>
  </prefaceinfo>

  <title>Foreword to the Japanese Edition</title>

  <para>One of the unexpected joys of this book was the privilege of
  working with its translator community after the English version was
  complete.  This was for the most part a passive involvement on my
  side, and especially so with the Japanese translation, as I
  unfortunately cannot read Japanese.</para>

  <para>But although I cannot comment on the translation, I can at least
  comment on the translators: they were a pleasure to work with from
  beginning to end.  My responsibilities were limited to setting up some
  infrastructure (a document repository, an electronic mailing list,
  etc), answering questions when necessary, and trying to stay out of
  their way.  The infrastructure I set up was not particularly easy to
  work with, either.  It required the translators to write in XML, a
  document preparation language that is halfway between a computer
  language and a human language, and it required them to work with a
  checkin/checkout system that was more meant for program files than
  prose files.  The translators bore these burdens without complaint,
  and in fact one of them even fixed some bugs in the original English
  version as he went along.  Just as with free software, putting more
  eyes on the code found bugs that the original author missed!</para>

  <para>Of course, finding bugs in the orginal was only a side-effect.
  The more important result of their work is that an entire 300-page
  book is now available to Japanese readers in their native language,
  both freely online and, for those who prefer it, in a professionally
  printed and bound version.</para>

  <para>I'd like to explore the implications of that for a moment.</para>

  <para>This book appeals to a small audience, relatively speaking.  I
  do not expect it to sell millions of copies, and its publishers do not
  expect it to either.  And yet, two people stepped forward to translate
  the whole thing into Japanese, because of their interest in free and
  open source software.  Thanks to their efforts, it will now be
  accessible to millions of people who could not otherwise read it.
  Most of those millions probably will not read it, but some of them
  will&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;just as it was impossible for me to predict
  which languages volunteers would translate it into, neither the
  translators nor I can predict how its new audience will use it.</para>

  <para>But all this happened only because the book was available online
  under a free, non-restrictive license.  The translators decided to do
  this by themselves; they did not need to ask anyone's permission, and
  they could have done it even without my cooperation (although I was of
  course happy to give my cooperation).  There is an obvious parallel to
  open source software itself here: when something is free, when its
  surface is magnetized to attract volunteers, then all sorts of things
  are possible.  I never expected my little book to gain so many
  potential new readers, yet because of these two translators, it
  did.</para>

  <para>What does this mean for books released under non-free licenses,
  that is, under traditional copyright restrictions?  Unfortunately, I
  think it means that those books are essentially suppressing many
  potential translations.  This book, for example, is translated not
  only into Japanese, but into about eight languages by about sixty
  translators.  Some of the translations are already completed; others
  are still in progress.  And this is for a relatively minor book!  Most
  books in bookstores are more popular (in their original language) than
  my book is, and yet they are translated less.</para>

  <para>That seems like a shame.  Although in the book I try to simply
  explain how free software projects run, and not talk about the social
  or moral implications of free software and open source principles, in
  this foreword to the Japanese edition I can be a bit more direct.
  This translation was possible because two volunteers took advantage of
  freedom, and if that same freedom were available for more
  books&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;or why not for <emphasis>all</emphasis>
  books?&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;then the Japanese public would have a much,
  much wider array of books available to them, and so would everyone
  else.</para>

  <para>After working in free software for so many years, I now find it
  strange that people normally must ask permission to publish a
  translation of a work.  What happened to my book is exactly what
  happens to most free software documentation: translations spring up
  spontaneously, because there is no one to say "no".  So as you read
  this translation, please keep in mind that it is the result of the
  same dynamics that the book talks about: it's about what people do
  when there is complete freedom to modify an existing work to suit a
  new need, and the freedom to collaborate with others in doing so.  If
  the existence of this translation helps encourage those freedoms not
  only for software, but for books and for other types of works as well,
  that would be a wonderful result.</para>

  <para>My humblest thanks to the translators, Yoshinari Takaoka and
  Masahiro Takagi, whose patience and dedication I hope will be
  appreciated by many readers.</para>

</preface>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
