<!--
https://spreadsheets.google.com/pub?hl=ja&hl=ja&key=0AgOqPQzRjQPOdDF5SGdRYXdVSGZWZGVxWWZXWV91WHc&output=html
-->

<chapter id="managing-volunteers">

<title>Managing Volunteers</title>

<simplesect>

<para>Getting people to agree on what a project needs, and to work
together to achieve it, requires more than just a genial atmosphere
and a lack of obvious dysfunction.  It requires someone, or several
someones, consciously managing all the people involved.  Managing
volunteers may not be a technical craft in the same sense as computer
programming, but it is a craft in the sense that it can be improved
through study and practice.</para>

<para>This chapter is a grab-bag of specific techniques for managing
volunteers.  It draws, perhaps more heavily than previous chapters, on
the Subversion project as a case study, partly because I was working
on that project as I wrote this and had all the primary sources close
at hand, and partly because it's more acceptable to cast critical
stones into one's own glass house than into others'.  But I have also
seen in various other projects the benefits of applying&mdash;and the
consequences of not applying&mdash;the recommendations that follow;
when it is politically feasible to give examples from some of those
other projects, I will do so.</para>

<para>Speaking of politics, this is as good a time as any to drag that
much-maligned word out for a closer look.  Many engineers like to
think of politics as something other people engage in.
"<emphasis>I'm</emphasis> just advocating the best course for the
project, but <emphasis>she's</emphasis> raising objections for
political reasons."  I believe this distaste for politics (or for what
is imagined to be politics) is especially strong in engineers because
engineers are bought into the idea that some solutions are objectively
superior to others.  Thus, when someone acts in a way that seems
motivated by outside considerations&mdash;say, the maintenance of his
own position of influence, the lessening of someone else's
influence, outright horse-trading, or avoiding hurting someone's
feelings&mdash;other participants in the project may get annoyed.  Of
course, this rarely prevents them from behaving in the same way when
their own vital interests are at stake.</para>

<para>If you consider "politics" a dirty word, and hope to keep your
project free of it, give up right now.  Politics are inevitable
whenever people have to cooperatively manage a shared resource.  It is
absolutely rational that one of the considerations going into each
person's decision-making process is the question of how a given action
might affect his own future influence in the project.  After all, if
you trust your own judgement and skills, as most programmers do, then
the potential loss of future influence has to be considered a
technical result, in a sense.  Similar reasoning applies to other
behaviors that might seem, on their face, like "pure" politics.  In
fact, there is no such thing as pure politics: it is precisely because
actions have multiple real-world consequences that people become
politically conscious in the first place.  Politics is, in the end,
simply an acknowledgment that <emphasis>all</emphasis> consequences of
decisions must be taken into account.  If a particular decision leads
to a result that most participants find technically satisfying, but
involves a change in power relationships that leaves key people
feeling isolated, the latter is just as important a result as the
former.  To ignore it would not be high-minded, but
shortsighted.</para>

<para>So as you read the advice that follows, and as you work with
your own project, remember that there is <emphasis>no one</emphasis>
who is above politics.  Appearing to be above politics is merely one
particular political strategy, and sometimes a very useful one, but it
is never the reality.  Politics is simply what happens when people
disagree, and successful projects are those that evolve political
mechanisms for managing disagreement constructively.</para>

</simplesect>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="volunteers">
<title>Getting the Most Out of Volunteers</title>

<para>Why do volunteers work on free software
projects?<footnote><para>This question was studied in detail, with
interesting results, in a paper by Karim Lakhani and Robert G. Wolf,
entitled <citetitle>Why Hackers Do What They Do: Understanding
Motivation and Effort in Free/Open Source Software
Projects</citetitle>.  See 
<ulink url="http://freesoftware.mit.edu/papers/lakhaniwolf.pdf"
/>.</para></footnote></para>

<para>When asked, many claim they do it because they want to produce
good software, or want to be personally involved in fixing the bugs
that matter to them.  But these reasons are usually not the whole
story.  After all, could you imagine a volunteer staying with a
project even if no one ever said a word in appreciation of his work,
or listened to him in discussions?  Of course not.  Clearly, people
spend time on free software for reasons beyond just an abstract desire
to produce good code.  Understanding volunteers' true motivations will
help you arrange things so as to attract and keep them.  The desire to
produce good software may be among those motivations, along with the
challenge and educational value of working on hard problems.  But
humans also have a built-in desire to work with other humans, and to
give and earn respect through cooperative activities.  Groups engaged
in cooperative activities must evolve norms of behavior such that
status is acquired and kept through actions that help the group's
goals.</para>

<para>Those norms won't always arise by themselves.  For example, on
some projects&mdash;experienced open source developers can probably
name several off the tops of their heads&mdash;people apparently feel
that status is acquired by posting frequently and verbosely.  They
don't come to this conclusion accidentally; they come to it because
they are rewarded with respect for making long, intricate arguments,
whether or not that actually helps the project.  Following are some
techniques for creating an atmosphere in which status-acquiring
actions are also constructive actions.</para>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="delegation">
<title>Delegation</title>

<para>Delegation is not merely a way to spread the workload around; it
is also a political and social tool.  Consider all the effects when
you ask someone to do something.  The most obvious effect is that, if
he accepts, he does the task and you don't.  But another effect is
that he is made aware that you trusted him to handle the task.
Furthermore, if you made the request in a public forum, then he knows
that others in the group have been made aware of that trust too.  He
may also feel some pressure to accept, which means you must ask in a
way that allows him to decline gracefully if he doesn't really want
the job.  If the task requires coordination with others in the
project, you are effectively proposing that he become more involved,
form bonds that might not otherwise have been formed, and perhaps
become a source of authority in some subdomain of the project.  The
added involvement may be daunting, or it may lead him to become
engaged in other ways as well, from an increased feeling of overall
commitment.</para>

<para>Because of all these effects, it often makes sense to ask
someone else to do something even when you know you could do it faster
or better yourself.  Of course, there is sometimes a strict economic
efficiency argument for this anyway: perhaps the opportunity cost of
doing it yourself would be too high&mdash;there might be something
even more important you could do with that time.  But even when the
opportunity cost argument doesn't apply, you may
<emphasis>still</emphasis> want to ask someone else to take on the
task, because in the long run you want to draw that person deeper into
the project, even if it means spending extra time watching over them
at first.  The converse technique also applies: if you occasionally
volunteer for work that someone else doesn't want or have time to do,
you will gain his good will and respect.  Delegation and
substitution are not just about getting individual tasks done; they're
also about drawing people into a closer committment to the
project.</para>

<sect3 id="delegation-assignment">
<title>Distinguish clearly between inquiry and assignment</title>

<para>Sometimes it is fair to expect that a person will accept a
particular task.  For example, if someone writes a bug into the code,
or commits code that fails to comply with project guidelines in some
obvious way, then it is enough to point out the problem and thereafter
behave as though you assume the person will take care of it.  But
there are other situations where it is by no means clear that you have
a right to expect action.  The person may do as you ask, or may not.
Since no one likes to be taken for granted, you need to be sensitive
to the difference between these two types of situations, and tailor
your requests accordingly.</para>

<para>One thing that almost always causes people instant annoyance is
being asked to do something in a way that implies that you think it is
clearly their responsibility to do it, when they feel otherwise.  For
example, assignment of incoming issues is particularly fertile ground
for this kind of annoyance.  The participants in a project usually
know who is expert in what areas, so when a bug report comes in, there
will often be one or two people whom everyone knows could probably fix
it quickly.  However, if you assign the issue over to one of those
people without her prior permission, she may feel she has been
put into an uncomfortable position.  She senses the pressure of
expectation, but also may feel that she is, in effect, being
punished for her expertise.  After all, the way one acquires
expertise is by fixing bugs, so perhaps someone else should take this
one!  (Note that issue trackers that automatically assign issues to
particular people based on information in the bug report are less
likely to offend, because everyone knows that the assignment was made
by an automated process, and is not an indication of human
expectations.)</para>

<para>While it would be nice to spread the load as evenly as possible,
there are certain times when you just want to encourage the person who
can fix a bug the fastest to do so.  Given that you can't afford a
communications turnaround for every such assignment ("Would you be
willing to look at this bug?"  "Yes."  "Okay, I'm assigning the issue
over to you then." "Okay."), you should simply make the assignment in
the form of an inquiry, conveying no pressure.  Virtually all issue
trackers allow a comment to be associated with the assignment of an
issue.  In that comment, you can say something like this:</para>

<blockquote>
   <para>Assigning this over to you, jrandom, because you're most
   familiar with this code.  Feel free to bounce this back if you
   don't have time to look at it, though.  (And let me know if you'd
   prefer not to receive such requests in the future.)</para>
</blockquote>

<para>This distinguishes clearly between the
<emphasis>request</emphasis> for assignment and the
recipient's <emphasis>acceptance</emphasis> of that assignment.  The
audience here isn't only the assignee, it's everyone: the entire group
sees a public confirmation of the assignee's expertise, but the
message also makes it clear that the assignee is free to accept or
decline the responsibility.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="delegation-followup">
<title>Follow up after you delegate</title>

<para>When you ask someone to do something, remember that you have
done so, and follow up with him no matter what.  Most requests are
made in public forums, and are roughly of the form "Can you take care
of X?  Let us know either way; no problem if you can't, just need to
know."  You may or may not get a response.  If you do, and the
response is negative, the loop is closed&mdash;you'll need to try some
other strategy for dealing with X.  If there is a positive response,
then keep an eye out for progress on the issue, and comment on the
progress you do or don't see (everyone works better when they know
someone else is appreciating their work).  If there is no response
after a few days, ask again, or post saying that you got no
response and are looking for someone else to do it.  Or just do it
yourself, but still make sure to say that you got no response to the
initial inquiry.</para>

<para>The purpose of publicly noting the lack of response is
<emphasis>not</emphasis> to humiliate the person, and your remarks
should be phrased so as not to have that effect.  The purpose is
simply to show that you keep track of what you have asked for, and
that you notice the reactions you get.  This makes people more likely
to say yes next time, because they will observe (even if only
unconsciously) that you are likely to notice any work they do, given
that you noticed the much less visible event of someone failing to
respond.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="delegation-interest">
<title>Notice what people are interested in</title>

<para>Another thing that makes people happy is to have their interests
noticed&mdash;in general, the more aspects of someone's personality
you notice and remember, the more comfortable he will be, and the
more he will want to work with groups of which you are a
part.</para>

<para>For example, there was a sharp distinction in the Subversion
project between people who wanted to reach a definitive 1.0 release
(which we eventually did), and people who mainly wanted to add new
features and work on interesting problems but who didn't much care
when 1.0 came out.  Neither of these positions is better or worse than
the other; they're just two different kinds of developers, and both
kinds do lots of work on the project.  But we swiftly learned that it
was important to <emphasis>not</emphasis> assume that the excitement
of the 1.0 drive was shared by everyone.  Electronic media can be very
deceptive: you may sense an atmosphere of shared purpose when, in fact,
it's shared only by the people you happen to have been talking to,
while others have completely different priorities.</para>

<para>The more aware you are of what people want out of the project,
the more effectively you can make requests of them.  Even just
demonstrating an understanding of what they want, without making any
associated request, is useful, in that it confirms to each person that
she's not just another particle in an undifferentiated mass.</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="praise-and-criticism">
<title>Praise and Criticism</title>

<para>Praise and criticism are not opposites; in many ways, they are
very similar.  Both are primarily forms of attention, and are most
effective when specific rather than generic.  Both should be deployed
with concrete goals in mind.  Both can be diluted by inflation: praise
too much or too often and you will devalue your praise; the same is
true for criticism, though in practice, criticism is usually reactive
and therefore a bit more resistant to devaluation.</para>

<para>An important feature of technical culture is that detailed,
dispassionate criticism is often taken as a kind of praise (as
discussed in <xref linkend="rudeness"/><phrase output="printed">
in <xref linkend="communications"/></phrase>), because of the
implication that the recipient's work is worth the time required to
analyze it.  However, both of those
conditions&mdash;<emphasis>detailed</emphasis> and
<emphasis>dispassionate</emphasis>&mdash;must be met for this to be
true.  For example, if someone makes a sloppy change to the code, it
is useless (and actually harmful) to follow up saying simply "That was
sloppy."  Sloppiness is ultimately a characteristic of a
<emphasis>person</emphasis>, not of their work, and it's important to
keep your reactions focused on the work.  It's much more effective to
describe all the things wrong with the change, tactfully and without
malice.  If this is the third or fourth careless change in a row by
the same person, it's appropriate to say that&mdash;again without
anger&mdash;at the end of your critique, to make it clear that the
pattern has been noticed.</para>

<para>If someone does not improve in response to criticism, the
solution is not more or stronger criticism.  The solution is for the
group to remove that person from the position of incompetence, in a
way that minimizes hurt feelings as much as possible; see
<xref linkend="transitions"/><phrase output="printed"> later in
this chapter</phrase> for examples.  That is a rare
occurrence, however.  Most people respond pretty well to criticism
that is specific, detailed, and contains a clear (even if unspoken)
expectation of improvement.</para>

<para>Praise won't hurt anyone's feelings, of course, but that doesn't
mean it should be used any less carefully than criticism.  Praise is a
tool: before you use it, ask yourself <emphasis>why</emphasis> you
want to use it.  As a rule, it's not a good idea to praise people for
doing what they usually do, or for actions that are a normal and
expected part of participating in the group.  If you were to do that,
it would be hard to know when to stop: should you praise
<emphasis>everyone</emphasis> for doing the usual things?  After all,
if you leave some people out, they'll wonder why.  It's much better to
express praise and gratitude sparingly, in response to unusual or
unexpected efforts, with the intention of encouraging more such
efforts.  When a participant seems to have moved permanently into a
state of higher productivity, adjust your praise threshold for that
person accordingly.  Repeated praise for normal behavior gradually
becomes meaningless anyway.  Instead, that person should sense that
her high level of productivity is now considered normal and natural,
and only work that goes beyond that should be specially noticed.</para>

<para>This is not to say that the person's contributions shouldn't be
acknowledged, of course.  But remember that if the project is set up
right, everything that person does is already visible anyway, and so
the group will know (and the person will know that the rest of the
group knows) everything she does.  There are also ways to acknowledge
someone's work by means other than direct praise.  You could mention
in passing, while discussing a related topic, that she has done a lot
of work in the given area and is the resident expert there; you
could publicly consult her on some question about the code; or perhaps
most effectively, you could conspicuously make further use of the work
she has done, so she sees that others are now comfortable relying on
the results of her work.  It's probably not necessary to do these
things in any calculated way.  Someone who regularly makes large
contributions in a project will know it, and will occupy a position of
influence by default.  There's usually no need to take explicit steps
to ensure this, unless you sense that, for whatever reason, a
contributor is underappreciated.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="territoriality">
<title>Prevent Territoriality</title>

<para>Watch out for participants who try to stake out exclusive
ownership of certain areas of the project, and who seem to want to do
all the work in those areas, to the extent of aggressively taking over
work that others start.  Such behavior may even seem healthy at first.
After all, on the surface it looks like the person is taking on more
responsibility, and showing increased activity within a given area.
But in the long run, it is destructive.  When people sense a "no
trespassing" sign, they stay away.  This results in reduced review in
that area, and greater fragility, because the lone developer becomes a
single point of failure.  Worse, it fractures the cooperative,
egalitarian spirit of the project.  The theory should always be that
any developer is welcome to help out on any task at any time.  Of
course, in practice things work a bit differently: people do have
areas where they are more and less influential, and non-experts
frequently defer to experts in certain domains of the project.  But
the key is that this is all voluntary: informal authority is granted
based on competence and proven judgement, but it should never be
actively
<emphasis>taken</emphasis>.  Even if the person desiring the authority
really is competent, it is still crucial that she hold that authority
informally, through the consensus of the group, and that the authority
never cause her to exclude others from working in that area.</para>

<para>Rejecting or editing someone's work for technical reasons is an
entirely different matter, of course.  There, the decisive factor
is the content of the work, not who happened to act as gatekeeper.  It
may be that the same person happens to do most of the reviewing for a
given area, but as long as he never tries to prevent someone else from
doing that work too, things are probably okay.</para>

<para>In order to combat incipient territorialism, or even the
appearance of it, many projects have taken the step of banning the
inclusion of author names or designated maintainer names in source
files.  I wholeheartedly agree with this practice: we follow it in the
Subversion project, and it is more or less official policy at the
Apache Software Foundation.  ASF member Sander Striker puts it this
way:</para>

<blockquote>
   <para><emphasis>At the Apache Software foundation we discourage the
   use of author tags in source code.  There are various reasons for
   this, apart from the legal ramifications.  Collaborative
   development is about working on projects as a group and caring for
   the project as a group.  Giving credit is good, and should be done,
   but in a way that does not allow for false attribution, even by
   implication.  There is no clear line for when to add or remove an
   author tag.  Do you add your name when you change a comment?  When
   you put in a one-line fix?  Do you remove other author tags when
   you refactor the code and it looks 95% different?  What do you do
   about people who go about touching every file, changing just enough
   to make the virtual author tag quota, so that their name will be
   everywhere?</emphasis></para>

   <para><emphasis>There are better ways to give credit, and our
   preference is to use those.  From a technical standpoint author
   tags are unnecessary; if you wish to find out who wrote a
   particular piece of code, the version control system can be
   consulted to figure that out.  Author tags also tend to get out of
   date.  Do you really wish to be contacted in private about a piece
   of code you wrote five years ago and were glad to have
   forgotten?</emphasis></para>
</blockquote>

<para>A software project's source code files are the core of its
identity.  They should reflect the fact that the developer community
as a whole is responsible for them, and not be divided up into
little fiefdoms.</para>

<para>People sometimes argue in favor of author or maintainer tags in
source files on the grounds that this gives visible credit to those
who have done the most work there.  There are two problems with this
argument.  First, the tags inevitably raise the awkward question of
how much work one must do to get one's own name listed there too.
Second, they conflate the issue of credit with that of authority:
having done work in the past does not imply ownership of the area
where the work was done, but it's difficult if not impossible to avoid
such an implication when individual names are listed at the tops of
source files.  In any case, credit information can already be obtained
from the version control logs and other out-of-band mechanisms like
mailing list archives, so no information is lost by banning it from
the source files themselves.<footnote><para>But see the mailing list
thread entitled <citetitle>"having authors names in .py files"</citetitle>
at <ulink url="http://groups.google.com/group/sage-devel/browse_thread/thread/e207ce2206f0beee"/>
for a good counterargument, particularly the post from William Stein.
The key in that case, I think, is that many of the authors come from a
culture (the academic mathematics community) where crediting directly
at the source is the norm and is highly valued.  In such
circumstances, it may be preferable to put author names into the
source files, along with precise descriptions of what each author did,
since the majority of potential contributors will expect that style of
acknowledgement.</para></footnote></para>

<para>If your project decides to ban individual names from source
files, make sure not to go overboard.  For instance, many
projects have a <filename>contrib/</filename> area where small tools and
helper scripts are kept, often written by people who are otherwise not
associated with the project.  It's fine for those files to contain
author names, because they are not really maintained by the project as
a whole.  On the other hand, if a contributed tool starts getting
hacked on by other people in the project, eventually you may want to
move it to a less isolated location and, assuming the original author
approves, remove the author's name, so that the code looks like any
other community-maintained resource.  If the author is sensitive about
this, compromise solutions are acceptable, for example:</para>

<blockquote>
<programlisting>
# indexclean.py: Remove old data from a Scanley index.
#
# Original Author: K. Maru &lt;kobayashi@yetanotheremailservice.com&gt;
# Now Maintained By: The Scanley Project &lt;http://www.scanley.org/&gt;
#                    and K. Maru.
# 
# ...
</programlisting>
</blockquote>

<para>But it's better to avoid such compromises, if possible, and most
authors are willing to be persuaded, because they're happy that their
contribution is being made a more integral part of the project.</para>

<para>The important thing is to remember that there is a continuum
between the core and the periphery of any project.  The main source
code files for the software are clearly part of the core, and should
be considered as maintained by the community.  On the other hand,
companion tools or pieces of documentation may be the work of single
individuals, who maintain them essentially alone, even though the
works may be associated with, and even distributed with, the project.
There is no need to apply a one-size-fits-all rule to every file, as
long as the principle that community-maintained resources are not
allowed to become individual territories is upheld.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="automation">
<title>The Automation Ratio</title>

<para>Try not to let humans do what machines could do instead.  As a
rule of thumb, automating a common task is worth at least ten times the
effort a developer would spend doing that task manually one time.  For
very frequent or very complex tasks, that ratio could easily go up to
twenty or even higher.</para>

<para>Thinking of yourself as a "project manager", rather than just
another developer, may be a useful attitude here.  Sometimes
individual developers are too wrapped up in low-level work to see the
big picture and realize that everyone is wasting a lot of effort
performing automatable tasks manually.  Even those who do realize it
may not take the time to solve the problem: because each individual
performance of the task does not feel like a huge burden, no one ever
gets annoyed enough to do anything about it.  What makes automation
compelling is that that small burden is multiplied by the number of
times each developer incurs it, and then <emphasis>that</emphasis>
number is multiplied by the number of developers.</para>

<para>Here, I am using the term "automation" broadly, to mean not only
repeated actions where one or two variables change each time, but any
sort of technical infrastructure that assists humans.  The minimum
standard automation required to run a project these days was described
in <xref linkend="technical-infrastructure"/>, but each project
may have its own special problems too.  For example, a group working
on documentation might want to have a web site displaying the most
up-to-date versions of the documents at all times.  Since
documentation is often written in a markup language like XML, there
may be a compilation step, often quite intricate, involved in creating
displayable or downloadable documents.  Arranging a web site where
such compilation happens automatically on every commit can be
complicated and time-consuming&mdash;but it is worth it, even if it
costs you a day or more to set up.  The overall benefits of having
up-to-date pages available at all times are huge, even though the cost
of <emphasis>not</emphasis> having them might seem like only a small
annoyance at any single moment, to any single developer.</para>

<para>Taking such steps eliminates not merely wasted time, but the
griping and frustration that ensue when humans make missteps (as they
inevitably will) in trying to perform complicated procedures manually.
Multi-step, deterministic operations are exactly what computers were
invented for; save your humans for more interesting things.</para>

<sect3 id="automated-testing">
<title>Automated testing</title>

<para>Automated test runs are helpful for any software project, but
especially so for open source projects, because automated testing
(especially regression testing) allows developers to feel comfortable
changing code in areas they are unfamiliar with, and thus encourages
exploratory development.  Since detecting breakage is so hard to do by
hand&mdash;one essentially has to guess where one might have broken
something, and try various experiments to prove that one
didn't&mdash;having automated ways to detect such breakage saves the
project a <emphasis>lot</emphasis> of time.  It also makes people much
more relaxed about refactoring large swaths of code, and therefore
contributes to the software's long-term maintainability.</para>

  <sidebar id="regression-testing">
  <title>Regression Testing</title>

  <para><firstterm>Regression testing</firstterm> means testing for
  the reappearance of already-fixed bugs.  The purpose of regression
  testing is to reduce the chances that code changes will break the
  software in unexpected ways.  As a software project gets bigger and
  more complicated, the chances of such unexpected side effects
  increase steadily.  Good design can reduce the rate at which the
  chances increase, but it cannot eliminate the problem
  entirely.</para>

  <para>As a result, many projects have a <firstterm>test
  suite</firstterm>, a separate program that invokes the project's
  software in ways that have been known in the past to stimulate
  specific bugs.  If the test suite succeeds in making one of these
  bugs happen, this is known as a <firstterm>regression</firstterm>,
  meaning that someone's change unexpectedly unfixed a
  previously-fixed bug.</para>

  <para>See also
  <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regression_testing"/>.</para>

  </sidebar>

<para>Regression testing is not a panacea.  For one thing, it works
best for programs with batch-style interfaces.  Software that is
operated primarily through graphical user interfaces is much harder to
drive programmatically.  Another problem is that the regression test
suite framework itself can often be quite complex, with a learning
curve and maintenance burden all its own.  Reducing this complexity is
one of the most useful things you can do, even though it may take a
considerable amount of time.  The easier it is to add new tests to the
suite, the more developers will do so, and the fewer bugs will survive
to release.  Any effort spent making tests easier to write will be
paid back manyfold over the lifetime of the project.</para>

<para>Many projects have a <firstterm>"Don't break the
build!"</firstterm> rule, meaning: don't commit a change that makes
the software unable to compile or run.  Being the person who broke the
build is usually cause for mild embarrassment and ribbing.  Projects
with regression test suites often have a corollary rule: don't commit
any change that causes tests to fail.  Such failures are easiest to
spot if there are automatic nightly runs of the entire test suite,
with the results mailed out to the development list or to a dedicated
test-results mailing list; that's another example of a worthwhile
automation.</para>

<para>Most volunteer developers are willing to take the extra time to
write regression tests, when the test system is comprehensible and
easy to work with.  Accompanying changes with tests is understood to
be the responsible thing to do, and it's also an easy opportunity for
collaboration: often two developers will divide up the work for a
bugfix, with one writing the fix itself, and the other writing the
test.  The latter developer may often end up with more work, and since
writing a test is already less satisfying than actually fixing the
bug, it is imperative that the test suite not make the experience more
painful than it has to be.</para>

<para>Some projects go even further, requiring that a new test
accompany <emphasis>every</emphasis> bugfix or new feature.  Whether
this is a good idea or not depends on many factors: the nature of the
software, the makeup of the development team, and the difficulty of
writing new tests.  The CVS (<ulink url="http://www.cvshome.org/"/>)
project has long had such a rule.  It is a good policy in theory,
since CVS is version control software and therefore very risk-averse
about the possibility of munging or mishandling the user's data.  The
problem in practice is that CVS's regression test suite is a single
huge shell script (amusingly named <filename>sanity.sh</filename>),
hard to read and hard to modify or extend.  The difficulty of adding
new tests, combined with the requirement that patches be accompanied
by new tests, means that CVS effectively discourages patches.  When I
used to work on CVS, I sometimes saw people start on and even complete
a patch to CVS's own code, but give up when told of the requirement to
add a new test to <filename>sanity.sh</filename>.</para>

<para>It is normal to spend more time writing a new regression test
than on fixing the original bug.  But CVS carried this phenomenon to
an extreme: one might spend hours trying to design one's test
properly, and still get it wrong, because there are just too many
unpredictable complexities involved in changing a 35,000-line Bourne
shell script.  Even longtime CVS developers often grumbled when they
had to add a new test.</para>

<para>This situation was due to a failure on all our parts to consider
the automation ratio.  It is true that switching to a real test
framework&mdash;whether custom-built or off-the-shelf&mdash;would have
been a major effort.<footnote><para>Note that there would be no need
to convert all the existing tests to the new framework; the two could
happily exist side by side, with old tests converted over only as they
needed to be changed.</para></footnote> But neglecting to do so has
cost the project much more, over the years.  How many bugfixes and new
features are <emphasis>not</emphasis> in CVS today, because of the
impediment of an awkward test suite?  We cannot know the exact number,
but it is surely many times greater than the number of bugfixes or new
features the developers might forgo in order to develop a new test
system (or integrate an off-the-shelf system).  That task would only
take a finite amount of time, while the penalty of using the current
test suite will continue forever if nothing is done.</para>

<para>The point is not that having strict requirements to write tests
is bad, nor that writing your test system as a Bourne shell script is
necessarily bad.  It might work fine, depending on how you design it
and what it needs to test.  The point is simply that when the test
system becomes a significant impediment to development, something must
be done.  The same is true for any routine process that turns into a
barrier or a bottleneck.</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="users-to-volunteers">
<title>Treat Every User as a Potential Volunteer</title>

<para>Each interaction with a user is an opportunity to get a new
volunteer.  When a user takes the time to post to one of the project's
mailing lists, or to file a bug report, he has already tagged himself
as having more potential for involvement than most users (from whom
the project will never hear at all).  Follow up on that potential: if
he described a bug, thank him for the report and ask him if he wants
to try fixing it.  If he wrote to say that an important question was
missing from the FAQ, or that the program's documentation was
deficient in some way, then freely acknowledge the problem (assuming
it really exists) and ask if he's interested in writing the missing
material himself.  Naturally, much of the time the user will demur.
But it doesn't cost much to ask, and every time you do, it reminds the
other listeners in that forum that getting involved in the project is
something anyone can do.</para>

<para>Don't limit your goals to acquiring new developers and
documentation writers.  For example, even training people to write
good bug reports pays off in the long run, if you don't spend
<emphasis>too</emphasis> much time per person, and if they go on
to submit more bug reports in the future&mdash;which they are more
likely to do if they got a constructive reaction to their first
report.  A constructive reaction need not be a fix for the bug,
although that's always the ideal; it can also be a solicitation for
more information, or even just a confirmation that the behavior
<emphasis>is</emphasis> a bug.  People want to be listened to.
Secondarily, they want their bugs fixed.  You may not always be able
to give them the latter in a timely fashion, but you (or rather, the
project as a whole) can give them the former.</para>

<para>A corollary of this is that developers should not express anger
at people who file well-intended but vague bug reports.  This is one
of my personal pet peeves; I see developers do it all the time on
various open source mailing lists, and the harm it does is palpable.
Some hapless newbie will post a useless report:</para>

<blockquote>
   <para>Hi, I can't get Scanley to run.  Every time I start it up, it
   just errors.  Is anyone else seeing this problem?</para>
</blockquote>

<para>Some developer&mdash;who has seen this kind of report a
thousand times, and hasn't stopped to think that the newbie has
not&mdash;will respond like this:</para>

<blockquote>
   <para>What are we supposed to do with so little information?
   Sheesh.  Give us at least some details, like the version of
   Scanley, your operating system, and the error.</para>
</blockquote>

<para>This developer has failed to see things from the user's point of
view, and also failed to consider the effect such a reaction might
have on all the <emphasis>other</emphasis> people watching the
exchange.  Naturally a user who has no programming experience, and no
prior experience reporting bugs, will not know how to write a bug
report.  What is the right way to handle such a person?  Educate them!
And do it in such a way that they come back for more:</para>

<blockquote>
   <para>Sorry you're having trouble.  We'll need more information in
   order to figure out what's happening here.  Please tell us the
   version of Scanley, your operating system, and the exact text of
   the error.  The very best thing you can do is send a transcript
   showing the exact commands you ran, and the output they produced.
   See http://www.scanley.org/how_to_report_a_bug.html for more.</para> 
</blockquote>

<para>This way of responding is far more effective at
extracting the needed information from the user, because it is written
to the user's point of view.  First, it expresses sympathy:
<emphasis>You had a problem; we feel your pain</emphasis>.  (This is
not necessary in every bug report response; it depends on the severity
of the problem and how upset the user seemed.)  Second, instead of
belittling her for not knowing how to report a bug, it tells her how,
and in enough detail to be actually useful&mdash;for example, many
users don't realize that "show us the error" means "show us the exact
text of the error, with no omissions or abridgements."  The first time
you work with such a user, you need to be specific about that.
Finally, it offers a pointer to much more detailed and complete
instructions for reporting bugs.  If you have successfully engaged
with the user, she will often take the time to read that document and
do what it says.  This means, of course, that you have to have the
document prepared in advance.  It should give clear instructions about
what kind of information your development team wants to see in every
bug report.  Ideally, it should also evolve over time in response to
the particular sorts of omissions and misreports users tend to make
for your project.</para>

<para>The Subversion project's bug reporting instructions are a fairly
standard example of the form (see <xref
linkend="bug-reporting"/>).  Notice how they close with an
invitation to provide a patch to fix the bug.  This is not because
such an invitation will lead to a greater patch/report
ratio&mdash;most users who are capable of fixing bugs already know
that a patch would be welcome, and don't need to be told.  The
invitation's real purpose is to emphasize to all readers, especially
those new to the project or new to free software in general, that the
project runs on volunteer contributions.  In a sense, the project's
current developers are no more responsible for fixing the bug than is
the person who reported it.  This is an important point that many new
users will not be familiar with.  Once they realize it, they're more
likely to help make the fix happen, if not by contributing code then
by providing a more thorough reproduction recipe, or by offering to
test fixes that other people post.  The goal is to make every user
realize that there is no <emphasis>innate</emphasis> difference
between herself and the people who work on the project&mdash;that
it's a question of how much time and effort one puts in, not a
question of who one is.</para>

<para>The admonition against responding angrily does not apply to rude
users.  Occasionally people post bug reports or complaints that,
regardless of their informational content, show a sneering contempt at
the project for some failing.  Often such people are alternately
insulting and flattering, such as the person who posted this to a
Subversion mailing list:</para>

<blockquote>
<para>Why is it that after almost 6 days there still aren't any
binaries posted for the windows platform?!?  It's the same story every
time and it's pretty frustrating.  Why aren't these things automated
so that they could be available immediately??  When you post an "RC"
build, I think the idea is that you want users to test the build, but
yet you don't provide any way of doing so.  Why even have a soak
period if you provide no means of testing??</para>
</blockquote>

<para>Initial response to this rather inflammatory post was
surprisingly restrained: people pointed out that the project had a
published policy of not providing official binaries, and said, with
varying degrees of annoyance, that he ought to volunteer to produce
them himself if they were so important to him.  Believe it or not, his
next post started with these lines:</para>

<blockquote>
<para>First of all, let me say that I think Subversion is awesome and
I really appreciate the efforts of everyone involved.  [...]</para>
</blockquote>

<para>...and then he went on to berate the project
<emphasis>again</emphasis> for not providing binaries, while
still not volunteering to do anything about it.  After that, about
50 people just jumped all over him, and I can't say I really
minded.  The "zero-tolerance" policy toward rudeness advocated in
<xref linkend="prevent-rudeness"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="getting-started"/></phrase> applies to people with
whom the project has (or would like to have) a sustained interaction.
But when someone makes it clear from the start that he is going to
be a fountain of bile, there is no point making him feel welcome.</para>

<para>Such situations are fortunately quite rare, and they are
noticeably rarer in projects that make an effort to engage users
constructively and courteously from their very first
interaction.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="share-management">
<title>Share Management Tasks as Well as Technical Tasks</title>

<para>Share the management burden as well as the technical burden of
running the project.  As a project becomes more complex, more and more
of the work is about managing people and information flow.  There is
no reason not to share that burden, and sharing it does not
necessarily require a top-down hierarchy either&mdash;what happens in
practice tends to be more of a peer-to-peer network topology than a
military-style command structure.</para>

<para>Sometimes management roles are formalized, and sometimes they
happen spontaneously.  In the Subversion project, we have a patch
manager, a translation manager, documentation managers, issue managers
(albeit unofficial), and a release manager.  Some of these roles we
made a conscious decision to initiate, others just happened by
themselves; as the project grows, I expect more roles to be added.
Below we'll examine these roles, and a couple of others, in detail
(except for release manager, which was already covered in
<xref linkend="release-manager"/> and
<xref linkend="release-owner"/><phrase output="printed"> earlier
in this chapter</phrase>).</para>

<para>As you read the role descriptions, notice that none of them
requires exclusive control over the domain in question.  The issue
manager does not prevent other people from making changes in the
issues database, the FAQ manager does not insist on being the only
person to edit the FAQ, and so on.  These roles are all about
responsibility without monopoly.  An important part of each domain
manager's job is to notice when other people are working in that domain,
and train them to do the things the way the manager does, so that the
multiple efforts reinforce rather than conflict.  Domain managers
should also document the processes by which they do their work, so
that when one leaves, someone else can pick up the slack right
away.</para>

<para>Sometimes there is a conflict: two or more people want the same
role.  There is no one right way to handle this.  You could suggest
that each volunteer post a proposal (an "application") and have all
the committers vote on which is best.  But this is cumbersome and
potentially awkward.  I find that a better technique is just to ask the
multiple candidates to settle it among themselves.  They usually will,
and will be more satisfied with the result than if a decision had been
imposed on them from the outside.</para>

<sect2 id="patch-manager">
<title>Patch Manager</title>

<para>In a free software project that receives a lot of patches,
keeping track of which patches have arrived and what has been decided
about them can be a nightmare, especially if done in a decentralized
way.  Most patches arrive as posts to the project's development
mailing list (though some may appear first in the issue tracker, or on
external web sites), and there are a number of different routes a
patch can take after arrival.</para>

<para>Sometimes someone reviews the patch, finds problems, and bounces
it back to the original author for cleanup.  This usually leads to an
iterative process&mdash;all visible on the mailing list&mdash;in which
the original author posts revised versions of the patch until the
reviewer has nothing more to criticize.  It is not always easy to tell
when this process is done: if the reviewer commits the patch, then
clearly the cycle is complete.  But if she does not, it might be
because she simply didn't have time, or doesn't have commit access
herself and couldn't rope any of the other developers into doing
it.</para>

<para>Another frequent response to a patch is a freewheeling
discussion, not necessarily about the patch itself, but about whether
the concept behind the patch is good.  For example, the patch may fix
a bug, but the project prefers to fix that bug in another way, as part
of solving a more general class of problems.  Often this is not known
in advance, and it is the patch that stimulates the discovery.</para>

<para>Occasionally, a posted patch is met with utter silence.  Usually
this is due to no developer having time <emphasis>at that
moment</emphasis> to review the patch, so each hopes that someone else
will do it.  Since there's no particular limit to how long each person
waits for someone else to pick up the ball, and meanwhile other
priorities are always coming up, it's very easy for a patch to slip
through the cracks without any single person intending for that to
happen.  The project might miss out on a useful patch this way, and
there are other harmful side effects as well: it is discouraging to
the author, who invested work in the patch, and it makes the project
as a whole look a bit out of touch, especially to others considering
writing patches.</para>

<para>The patch manager's job is to make sure that patches don't "slip
through the cracks."  This is done by following every patch through to
some sort of stable state.  The patch manager watches every mailing
list thread that results from a patch posting.  If it ends in a commit
of the patch, he does nothing.  If it goes into a review/revise
iteration, ending with a final version of the patch but no commit, he
files an issue pointing to the final version, and to the mailing list
thread around it, so that there is a permanent record for developers
to follow up on later.  If the patch addresses an existing issue, he
annotates that issue with the relevant information, instead of opening
a new issue.</para>

<para>When a patch gets no reaction at all, the patch manager waits a
few days, then follows up asking if anyone is going to review it.
This usually gets a reaction: a developer may explain that she doesn't
think the patch should be applied, and give the reasons why, or she may
review it, in which case one of the previously described paths is
taken.  If there is still no response, the patch manager may or may
not file an issue for the patch, at his discretion, but at
least the original submitter got <emphasis>some</emphasis>
reaction.</para>

<para>Having a patch manager has saved the Subversion development team
a lot of time and mental energy.  Without a designated person to take
responsibility, every developer would constantly have to worry "If I
don't have time to respond to this patch right now, can I count on
someone else doing it?  Should I try to keep an eye on it?  But if
other people are also keeping an eye on it, for the same reasons, then
we'd have needlessly duplicated effort."  The patch manager removes
the second-guessing from the situation.  Each developer can make the
decision that is right for her at the moment she first sees the patch.
If she wants to follow up with a review, she can do that&mdash;the
patch manager will adjust his behavior accordingly.  If she wants to
ignore the patch completely, that's fine too; the patch manager will
make sure it isn't forgotten.</para>

<para>Because this system works only if people can depend on the patch
manager being there without fail, the role should be held formally.
In Subversion, we advertised for it on the development and users
mailing lists, got several volunteers, and took the first one who
replied.  When that person had to step down (see
<xref linkend="transitions"/><phrase output="printed"> later in
this chapter</phrase>), we did the same thing again.
We've never tried having multiple people share the role, because of
the communications overhead that would be required between them; but
perhaps at very high volumes of patch submission, a multiheaded patch
manager might make sense.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="translation-manager">
<title>Translation Manager</title>

<para>In software projects, "translation" can refer to two very
different things.  It can mean translating the software's
documentation into other languages, or it can mean translating the
software itself&mdash;that is, having the program display errors and
help messages in the user's preferred language.  Both are complex
tasks, but once the right infrastructure is in place, they are largely
separable from other development.  Because the tasks are similar in
some ways, it may make sense (depending on your project) to have a
single translation manager handle both, or it may be better to have
two different managers.</para>

<para>In the Subversion project, we have one translation manager
handle both.  He does not actually write the translations himself, of
course&mdash;he may help out on one or two, but as of this writing, he
would need to speak ten languages (twelve counting dialects) in order
to work on all of them!  Instead, he manages teams of volunteer
translators: he helps them coordinate among each other, and he
coordinates between the teams and the rest of the project.</para>

<para>Part of the reason the translation manager is necessary is that
translators are a different demographic from developers.  They
sometimes have little or no experience working in a version control
repository, or indeed with working as part of a distributed volunteer
team at all.  But in other respects they are often the best kind of
volunteer: people with specific domain knowledge who saw a need and
chose to get involved.  They are usually willing to learn, and
enthusiastic to get to work.  All they need is someone to tell them
how.  The translation manager makes sure that the translations happen
in a way that does not interfere unnecessarily with regular
development.  He also serves as a sort of representative of the
translators as a unified body, whenever the developers must be
informed of technical changes required to support the translation
effort.</para>

<para>Thus, the position's most important skills are diplomatic, not
technical.  For example, in Subversion we have a policy that all
translations should have at least two people working on them, because
otherwise there is no way for the text to be reviewed.  When a new
volunteer shows up offering to translate Subversion to, say, Malagasy,
the translation manager has to either hook him up with someone who
posted six months ago expressing interest in doing a Malagasy
translation, or else politely ask the volunteer to go
find <emphasis>another</emphasis> Malagasy translator to work with as
a partner.  Once enough people are available, the manager sets them up
with the proper kind of commit access, informs them of the project's
conventions (such as how to write log messages), and then keeps an eye
out to make sure they adhere to those conventions.</para>

<para>Conversations between the translation manager and the
developers, or between the translation manager and translation teams,
are usually held in the project's original language&mdash;that is, the
language from which all the translations are being made.  For most
free software projects, this is English, but it doesn't matter what it
is as long as the project agrees on it.  (English is probably best for
projects that want to attract a broad international development
community, though.)</para>

<para>Conversations <emphasis>within</emphasis> a particular
translation team usually happen in their shared language, however, and
one of the other tasks of the translation manager is to set up a
dedicated mailing list for each team.  That way the translators can
discuss their work freely, without distracting people on the project's
main lists, most of whom would not be able to understand the
translation language anyway.</para>

  <sidebar id="i7n">
  <title>Internationalization Versus Localization</title>
  
  <para><firstterm>Internationalization</firstterm>
  (<firstterm>I18N</firstterm>) and <firstterm>localization</firstterm>
  (<firstterm>L10N</firstterm>) both refer to the process of adapting
  a program to work in linguistic and cultural environments other than
  the one for which it was originally written.  The terms are often
  treated as interchangeable, but in fact they are not quite the same
  thing.  As <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G11n"/>
  writes:</para>

  <blockquote>
     <para>The distinction between them is subtle but important:
     Internationalization is the adaptation of products
     for <emphasis>potential</emphasis> use virtually everywhere, while
     localization is the addition of special features for use in
     a <emphasis>specific</emphasis> locale.</para>
  </blockquote>

  <para>For example, changing your software to losslessly handle
  Unicode (<ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unicode"/>) text
  encodings is an internationalization move, since it's not about a
  particular language, but rather about accepting text from any of a
  number of languages.  On the other hand, making your software print
  all error messages in Slovenian, when it detects that it is running
  in a Slovenian environment, is a localization move.</para>

  <para>Thus, the translation manager's task is principally about
  localization, not internationalization.</para>
  
  </sidebar>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="documentation-manager">
<title>Documentation Manager</title>

<para>Keeping software documentation up-to-date is a never-ending
task.  Every new feature or enhancement that goes into the code has
the potential to cause a change in the documentation.  Also, once the
project's documentation reaches a certain level of completeness, you
will find that a lot of the patches people send in are for the
documentation, not for the code.  This is because there are many more
people competent to fix bugs in prose than in code: all users are
readers, but only a few are programmers.</para>

<para>Documentation patches are usually much easier to review and
apply than code patches.  There is little or no testing to be done,
and the quality of the change can be evaluated quickly just by review.
Since the quantity is high, but the review burden fairly low, the
ratio of administrative overhead to productive work is greater for
documentation patches than for code patches.  Furthermore, most of the
patches will probably need some sort of adjustment, in order to
maintain a consistent authorial voice in the documentation.  In many
cases, patches will overlap with or affect other patches, and need to
be adjusted with respect to each other before being committed.</para>

<para>Given the exigencies of handling documentation patches, and the
fact that the code base needs to be constantly monitored so the
documentation can be kept up-to-date, it makes sense to have one
person, or a small team, dedicated to the task.  They can keep a
record of exactly where and how the documentation lags behind the
software, and they can have practiced procedures for handling large
quantities of patches in an integrated way.</para>

<para>Of course, this does not preclude other people in the project
from applying documentation patches on the fly, especially small ones,
as time permits.  And the same patch manager (see
<xref linkend="patch-manager"/><phrase output="printed"> earlier
in this chapter</phrase>) can track both code and
documentation patches, filing them wherever the development and
documentation teams want them, respectively.  (If the total quantity of
patches ever exceeds one human's capacity to track, though, switching
to separate patch managers for code and documentation is probably a
good first step.)  The point of a documentation team is to have people
who think of themselves as responsible for keeping the documentation
organized, up-to-date, and consistent with itself.  In practice, this
means knowing the documentation intimately, watching the code base,
watching the changes
<emphasis>others</emphasis> commit to the documentation, watching for
incoming documentation patches, and using all these information
sources to do whatever is necessary to keep the documentation
healthy.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="issue-manager">
<title>Issue Manager</title>

<para>The number of issues in a project's bug tracker grows in
proportion to the number of people using the software.  Therefore,
even as you fix bugs and ship an increasingly robust program, you
should still expect the number of open issues to grow essentially
without bound.  The frequency of duplicate issues will also increase,
as will the frequency of incomplete or poorly described issues.</para>

<para>Issue managers help alleviate these problems by watching what
goes into the database, and periodically sweeping through it looking
for specific problems.  Their most common action is probably to fix up
incoming issues, either because the reporter didn't set some of the
form fields correctly, or because the issue is a duplicate of one
already in the database.  Obviously, the more familiar an issue
manager is with the project's bug database, the more efficiently she
will be able to detect duplicate issues&mdash;this is one of the main
advantages of having a few people specialize in the bug database,
instead of everyone trying to do it <foreignphrase>ad
hoc</foreignphrase>.  When the group tries to do it in a decentralized
manner, no single individual acquires a deep expertise in the content
of the database.</para>

<para>Issue managers can also help map between issues and individual
developers.  When there are a lot of bug reports coming in, not every
developer may read the issue notification mailing list with equal
attention.  However, if someone who knows the development team is
keeping an eye on all incoming issues, then she can discreetly direct
certain developers' attention to specific bugs when appropriate.  Of
course, this has to be done with a sensitivity to everything else
going on in development, and to the recipient's desires and
temperament.  Therefore, it is often best for issue managers to be
developers themselves.</para>

<para>Depending on how your project uses the issue tracker, issue
managers can also shape the database to reflect the project's
priorities.  For example, in Subversion we schedule issues into
specific future releases, so that when someone asks "When will bug X
be fixed?" we can say "Two releases from now," even if we can't give
an exact date.  The releases are represented in the issue tracker as
target milestones, a field available in
IssueZilla.<footnote><para>IssueZilla is the issue tracker we use; it
is a descendant of BugZilla.</para></footnote> As a rule, every
Subversion release has one major new feature and a list of specific
bug fixes.  We assign the appropriate target milestone to all the
issues planned for that release (including the new feature&mdash;it
gets an issue too), so that people can view the bug database through
the lens of release scheduling.  These targets rarely remain static,
however.  As new bugs come in, priorities sometimes get shifted
around, and issues must be moved from one milestone to another so that
each release remains manageable.  This, again, is best done by people
who have an overall sense of what's in the database, and how various
issues relate to each other.</para>

<para>Another thing issue managers do is notice when issues become
obsolete.  Sometimes a bug is fixed accidentally as part of an
unrelated change to the software, or sometimes the project changes its
mind about whether a certain behavior is buggy.  Finding obsoleted
issues is not easy: the only way to do it systematically is by making
a sweep over all the issues in the database.  Full sweeps become less
and less feasible over time, however, as the number of issues grows.
After a certain point, the only way to keep the database sane is to use a
divide-and-conquer approach: categorize issues immediately on arrival
and direct them to the appropriate developer's or team's attention.
The recipient then takes charge of the issue for the rest of its
lifetime, shepherding it to resolution or oblivion as necessary.  When
the database is that large, the issue manager becomes more of an
overall coordinator, spending less time looking at each issue herself
and more time getting it into the right person's hands.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="faq-manager">
<title>FAQ Manager</title>

<para>FAQ maintenance is a surprisingly difficult problem.  Unlike
most other documents in a project, whose content is planned out in
advance by the authors, a FAQ is a wholly reactive document (see
<xref linkend="starting-a-faq"/>).  No matter how big it gets, you
still never know what the next addition will be.  And because it is
always added to piecemeal, it is very easy for the document as a whole
to become incoherent and disorganized, and even to contain duplicate
or semi-duplicate entries.  Even when it does not have any obvious
problems like that, there are often unnoticed interdependencies
between items&mdash;links that should be made but aren't&mdash;because
the related items were added a year apart.</para>

<para>The role of a FAQ manager is twofold.  First, she maintains the
overall quality of the FAQ by staying familiar with at least the
topics of all the questions in it, so that when people add new items
that are duplicates of, or related to, existing items, the appropriate
adjustments can be made.  Second, she watches the project mailing
lists and other forums for recurring problems or questions, and to
write new FAQ entries based on this input.  This latter task can be
quite complex: one must be able to follow a thread, recognize the core
questions raised in it, post a proposed FAQ entry, incorporate
comments from others (since it's impossible for the FAQ manager to be
an expert in every topic covered by the FAQ), and sense when the
process is finished so the item can at last be added.</para>

<para>The FAQ manager usually also becomes the default expert in FAQ
formatting.  There are a lot of little details involved in keeping a
FAQ in shape (see
<xref linkend="all-as-archives"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="communications"/></phrase>); when random
people edit the FAQ, they will sometimes forget some of these details.
That's okay, as long as the FAQ manager is there to clean up after
them.</para>

<para>Various free software is available to help with the process of
FAQ maintenance.  It's fine to use it, as long as it doesn't
compromise the quality of the FAQ, but beware of over-automation.
Some projects try to fully automate the process of FAQ maintenance,
allowing everyone to contribute and edit FAQ items in a manner similar
to a wiki (see <xref linkend="wikis"/><phrase output="printed">
in <xref linkend="technical-infrastructure"/></phrase>).  I've
seen this happen particularly with Faq-O-Matic
(<ulink url="http://faqomatic.sourceforge.net/"/>), though it may be
that the cases I saw were simply abuses that went beyond what
Faq-O-Matic was originally intended for.  In any case, while complete
decentralization of FAQ maintenance does reduce the workload for the
project, it also results in a poorer FAQ.  There's no one person with
a broad view of the entire FAQ, no one to notice when certain items
need updating or become obsolete entirely, and no one keeping watch for
interdependencies between items.  The result is a FAQ that often fails
to provide users what they were looking for, and in the worst cases
misleads them.  Use whatever tools you need to to maintain your
project's FAQ, but never let the convenience of the tools seduce you
into compromising the quality of the FAQ.</para>

<para>See Sean Michael Kerner's article, <citetitle>The FAQs on
FAQs</citetitle>, at
<ulink url="http://osdir.com/Article1722.phtml"/>, for descriptions
and evaluations of open source FAQ maintenance tools.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="transitions">
<title>Transitions</title>

<para>From time to time, a volunteer in a position of ongoing
responsibility (e.g., patch manager, translation manager, etc.) will
become unable to perform the duties of the position.  It may be
because the job turned out to be more work than he anticipated, or it
may be due to completely external factors: marriage, a new baby, a new
employer, or whatever.</para>

<para>When a volunteer gets swamped like this, he usually doesn't
notice it right away.  It happens by slow degrees, and there's no
point at which he consciously realizes that he can no longer fulfill
the duties of the role.  Instead, the rest of the project just doesn't
hear much from him for a while.  Then there will suddenly be a flurry
of activity, as he feels guilty for neglecting the project for so long
and sets aside a night to catch up.  Then you won't hear from him for
a while longer, and then there might or might not be another flurry.
But there's rarely an unsolicited formal resignation.  The volunteer
was doing the job in his spare time, so resigning would mean openly
acknowledging to himself that his spare time is permanently reduced.
People are often reluctant to do that.</para>

<para>Therefore, it's up to you and the others in the project to
notice what's happening&mdash;or rather, not happening&mdash;and to
ask the volunteer what's going on.  The inquiry should be friendly and
100% guilt-free.  Your purpose is to find out a piece
of information, not to make the person feel bad.  Generally, the
inquiry should be visible to the rest of the project, but if you know
of some special reason why a private inquiry would be better, that's
fine too.  The main reason to do it publicly is so that if the
volunteer responds by saying that he won't be able to do the job
anymore, there's a context established for your
<emphasis>next</emphasis> public post: a request for a new volunteer
to fill that role.</para>

<para>Sometimes, a volunteer is unable to do the job he's taken on,
but is either unaware or unwilling to admit that fact.  Of course,
anyone may have trouble at first, especially if the responsibility is
complex.  However, if someone just isn't working out in the task he's
taken on, even after everyone else has given all the help and
suggestions they can, then the only solution is for him to step aside
and let someone new have a try.  And if the person doesn't see this
himself, he'll need to be told.  There's basically only one way to
handle this, I think, but it's a multistep process and each step is
important.</para>

<para>First, make sure you're not crazy.  Privately talk to others in
the project to see if they agree that the problem is as serious as you
think it is.  Even if you're already positive, this serves the purpose
of letting others know that you're considering asking the person to
step aside.  Usually no one will object to that&mdash;they'll just be
happy you're taking on the awkward task, so they don't have to!</para>

<para>Next, <emphasis>privately</emphasis> contact the volunteer in
question and tell him, kindly but directly, about the problems you
see.  Be specific, giving as many examples as possible.  Make sure to
point out how people had tried to help, but that the problems
persisted without improving.  You should expect this email to take a
long time to write, but with this sort of message, if you don't back
up what you're saying, you shouldn't say it at all.  Say that you
would like to find a new volunteer to fill the role, but also point
out that there are many other ways to contribute to the project.  At
this stage, don't say that you've talked to others about it; nobody
likes to be told that people were conspiring behind his back.</para>

<para>There are a few different ways things can go after that.  The
most likely reaction is that he'll agree with you, or at any rate not
want to argue, and be willing to step down.  In that case, suggest
that he make the announcement himself, and then you can follow up with
a post seeking a replacement.</para>

<para>Or, he may agree that there have been problems, but ask for a
little more time (or for one more chance, in the case of discrete-task
roles like release manager).  How you react to that is a judgement
call, but whatever you do, don't agree to it just because you feel
like you can't refuse such a reasonable request.  That would prolong
the agony, not lessen it.  There is often a very good reason to refuse
the request, namely, that there have already been plenty of chances,
and that's how things got to where they are now.  Here's how I put it
in a mail to someone who was filling the release manager role but was
not really suited for it:</para>

<blockquote>
<screen>
&gt; If you wish to replace me with some one else, I will gracefully
&gt; pass on the role to who comes next.  I have one request, which
&gt; I hope is not unreasonable.  I would like to attempt one more
&gt;  release in an effort to prove myself.

I totally understand the desire (been there myself!), but in
this case, we shouldn't do the "one more try" thing.

This isn't the first or second release, it's the sixth or
seventh... And for all of those, I know you've been dissatisfied
with the results too (because we've talked about it before).  So
we've effectively already been down the one-more-try route.
Eventually, one of the tries has to be the last one... I think
[this past release] should be it.
</screen>
</blockquote>

<para>In the worst case, the volunteer may disagree outright.  Then
you have to accept that things are going to be awkward and plow ahead
anyway.  Now is the time to say that you talked to other people about
it (but still don't say who until you have their permission, since
those conversations were confidential), and that you don't think it's
good for the project to continue as things are.  Be insistent, but
never threatening.  Keep in mind that with most roles, the transition
really happens the moment someone new starts doing the job,
<emphasis>not</emphasis> the moment the old person stops doing it.
For example, if the contention is over the role of, say, issue
manager, at any point you and other influential people in the project
can solicit for a new issue manager.  It's not actually necessary that
the person who was previously doing it stop doing it, as long as he
does not sabotage (deliberately or otherwise) the efforts of the new
volunteer.</para>

<para>Which leads to a tempting thought: instead of asking the person
to resign, why not just frame it as a matter of getting him some help?
Why not just have two issue managers, or patch managers, or whatever
the role is?</para>

<para>Although that may sound nice in theory, it is generally not a
good idea.  What makes the manager roles work&mdash;what makes them
useful, in fact&mdash;is their centralization.  Those things that can
be done in a decentralized fashion are usually already being done that
way.  Having two people fill one managerial role introduces
communications overhead between those two people, as well as the
potential for slippery displacement of responsibility ("I thought you
brought the first aid kit!"  "Me?  No, I thought
<emphasis>you</emphasis> brought the first aid kit!").  Of course,
there are exceptions.  Sometimes two people work extremely well
together, or the nature of the role is such that it can easily be
spread across multiple people.  But these are not likely to be of much
use when you see someone flailing in a role he is not suited for.  If
he'd appreciated the problem in the first place, he would have sought
such help before now.  In any case, it would be disrespectful to let
someone waste time continuing to do a job no one will pay attention
to.</para>

<para>The most important factor in asking someone to step down is
privacy: giving him the space to make a decision without feeling like
others are watching and waiting.  I once made the mistake&mdash;an
obvious mistake, in retrospect&mdash;of mailing all three parties at
once in order to ask Subversion's release manager to step aside in
favor of two other volunteers.  I'd already talked to the two new
people privately, and knew that they were willing to take on the
responsibility.  So I thought, na&iuml;vely and somewhat
insensitively, that I'd save some time and hassle by sending one mail
to all of them to initiate the transition.  I assumed that the current
release manager was already fully aware of the problems and would see
the reasonableness of my point immediately.</para>

<para>I was wrong.  The current release manager was very offended, and
rightly so.  It's one thing to be asked to hand off the job; it's
another thing to be asked that <emphasis>in front of</emphasis> the
people you'll hand it off to.  Once I got it through my head why he
was offended, I apologized.  He eventually did step aside gracefully,
and continues to be involved with the project today.  But his
feelings were hurt, and needless to say, this was not the most
auspicious of beginnings for the new volunteers either.</para>

</sect1>


<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="committers">
<title>Committers</title>

<para>As the only formally distinct class of people found in all open
source projects, committers deserve special attention here.
Committers are an unavoidable concession to discrimination in a system
which is otherwise as non-discriminatory as possible.  But
"discrimination" is not meant as a pejorative here.  The function
committers perform is utterly necessary, and I do not think a project
could succeed without it.  Quality control requires, well, control.
There are always many people who feel competent to make changes to a
program, and some smaller number who actually are.  The project cannot
rely on people's own judgement; it must impose standards and grant
commit access only to those who meet them<footnote><para>Note that the
commit access means something a bit different in decentralized version
control systems, where anyone can set up a repository that is linked
into the project, and give themselves commit access to that
repository.  Nevertheless, the <emphasis>concept</emphasis> of commit
access still applies: "commit access" is shorthand for "the
right to make changes to the code that will ship in the group's next
release of the software."  In centralized version control systems,
this means having direct commit access; in decentralized ones, it
means having one's changes pulled into the main distribution by
default.  It is the same idea either way; the mechanics by which it is
realized are not terribly important.</para></footnote>.  On the other
hand, having people who can commit changes directly working
side-by-side with people who cannot sets up an obvious power dynamic.
That dynamic must be managed so that it does not harm the
project.</para>

<para>In <xref linkend="electorate"/><phrase output="printed">
in <xref linkend="social-infrastructure"/></phrase>, we already
discussed the mechanics of considering new committers.  Here we will
look at the standards by which potential new committers should be
judged, and how this process should be presented to the larger
community.</para>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="choosing-committers">
<title>Choosing Committers</title>

<para>In the Subversion project, we choose committers primarily on the
Hippocratic Principle: <emphasis>first, do no harm</emphasis>.  Our
main criterion is not technical skill or even knowledge of the code,
but merely that the committer show good judgement.  Judgement can mean
simply knowing what not to take on.  A person might post only small
patches, fixing fairly simple problems in the code; but if the patches
apply cleanly, do not contain bugs, and are mostly in accord with the
project's log message and coding conventions, and there are enough
patches to show a clear pattern, then an existing committer will
usually propose that person for commit access.  If at least three
people say yes, and no one objects, then the offer is made.  True, we
might have no evidence that the person is able to solve complex
problems in all areas of the code base, but that does not matter: the
person has made it clear that he is capable of at least judging
his own abilities.  Technical skills can be learned (and taught),
but judgement, for the most part, cannot.  Therefore, it is the one
thing you want to make sure a person has before you give him commit
access.</para>

<para>When a new committer proposal does provoke a discussion, it is
usually not about technical ability, but rather about the person's
behavior on the mailing lists or in IRC.  Sometimes someone shows
technical skill and an ability to work within the project's formal
guidelines, yet is also consistently belligerent or uncooperative in
public forums.  That's a serious concern; if the person doesn't
seem to shape up over time, even in response to hints, then we won't
add him as a committer no matter how skilled he is.  In a
volunteer group, social skills, or the ability to "play well in the
sandbox", are as important as raw technical ability.  Because
everything is under version control, the penalty for adding a
committer you shouldn't have is not so much the problems it could
cause in the code (review would spot those quickly anyway), but that
it might eventually force the project to revoke the person's commit
access&mdash;an action that is never pleasant and can sometimes be
confrontational.</para>

<para>Many projects insist that the potential committer demonstrate a
certain level of technical expertise and persistence, by submitting
some number of nontrivial patches&mdash;that is, not only do these
projects want to know that the person will do no harm, they want to
know that she is likely to do good across the code base.  This is
fine, but be careful that it doesn't start to turn committership into
a matter of membership in an exclusive club.  The question to keep in
everyone's mind should be "What will bring the best results for the
code?" not "Will we devalue the social status associated with
committership by admitting this person?"  The point of commit access
is not to reinforce people's self-worth, it's to allow good changes to
enter the code with a minimum of fuss.  If you have 100
committers, 10 of whom make large changes on a regular basis, and the
other 90 of whom just fix typos and small bugs a few times a year,
that's still better than having only the 10.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="revoking-committers">
<title>Revoking Commit Access</title>

<para>The first thing to be said about revoking commit access is: try
not to be in that situation in the first place.  Depending on whose
access is being revoked, and why, the discussions around such an
action can be very divisive.  Even when not divisive, they will be a
time-consuming distraction from productive work.</para>

<para>However, if you must do it, the discussion should be had
privately among the same people who would be in a position to vote for
<emphasis>granting</emphasis> that person whatever flavor of commit
access they currently have.  The person herself should not be
included.  This contradicts the usual injunction against secrecy, but
in this case it's necessary.  First, no one would be able to speak
freely otherwise.  Second, if the motion fails, you don't necessarily
want the person to know it was ever considered, because that could
open up questions ("Who was on my side?  Who was against me?") that
lead to the worst sort of factionalism.  In certain rare
circumstances, the group may want someone to know that revocation of
commit access is or was being considered, as a warning, but this
openness should be a decision the group makes.  No one should ever, on
her own initiative, reveal information from a discussion and ballot
that others assumed were secret.</para>

<para>Once someone's access is revoked, that fact is unavoidably
public (see
<xref linkend="commit-access-openness"/><phrase output="printed">
later in this chapter</phrase>), so try to be as tactful as you can in
how it is presented to the outside world.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="partial-committers">
<title>Partial Commit Access</title>

<para>Some projects offer gradations of commit access.  For example,
there might be contributors whose commit access gives them free rein
in the documentation, but who do not commit to the code itself.
Common areas for partial commit access include documentation,
translations, binding code to other programming languages,
specification files for packaging (e.g., RedHat RPM spec files,
etc.), and other places where a mistake will not result in a problem for
the core project.</para>

<para>Since commit access is not only about committing, but about
being part of an electorate (see
<xref linkend="electorate"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="social-infrastructure"/></phrase>),
the question naturally arises: what can the partial committers vote
on?  There is no one right answer; it depends on what sorts of partial
commit domains your project has.  In Subversion we've kept things
fairly simple: a partial committer can vote on matters confined
exclusively to that committer's domain, and not on anything else.
Importantly, we do have a mechanism for casting advisory votes
(essentially, the committer writes "+0" or "+1&nbsp;(non-binding)"
instead of just "+1" on the ballot).  There's no reason to silence
people entirely just because their vote isn't formally binding.</para>

<para>Full committers can vote on anything, just as they can commit
anywhere, and only full committers vote on adding new committers of
any kind.  In practice, though, the ability to add new partial
committers is usually delegated: any full committer can "sponsor" a
new partial committer, and partial committers in a domain can often
essentially choose new committers for that same domain (this is
especially helpful in making translation work run smoothly).</para>

<para>Your project may need a slightly different arrangement,
depending on the nature of the work, but the same general principles
apply to all projects.  Each committer should be able to vote on
matters that fall within the scope of her commit access, and not on
matters outside that, and votes on procedural questions should default
to the full committers, unless there's some reason (as decided by the
full committers) to widen the electorate.</para>

<para>Regarding enforcement of partial commit access: it's often
best <emphasis>not</emphasis> to have the version control system
enforce partial commit domains, even if it can.  See
<xref linkend="vc-authz"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="technical-infrastructure"/></phrase> for the
reasons why.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="dormant-committers">
<title>Dormant Committers</title>

<para>Some projects automatically remove people's commit access if
they go a certain amount of time (say, a year) without committing
anything.  I think this is usually unhelpful and even
counterproductive, for two reasons.</para>

<para>First, it may tempt some people into committing acceptable but
unnecessary changes, just to prevent their commit access from
expiring.  Second, it doesn't really serve any purpose.  If the
main criterion for granting commit access is good judgement, then why
assume someone's judgement would deteriorate just because he's away
from the project for a while?  Even if he completely vanishes for
years, not looking at the code or following development discussions,
when he reappears he'll <emphasis>know</emphasis> how out of touch
he is, and act accordingly.  You trusted his judgement before, so
why not trust it always?  If high school diplomas do not expire, then
commit access certainly shouldn't.</para>

<para>Sometimes a committer may ask to be removed, or to be explicitly
marked as dormant in the list of committers (see
<xref linkend="commit-access-openness"/><phrase output="printed">
below</phrase> for more about that list).  In these cases, the project
should accede to the person's wishes, of course.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="commit-access-openness">
<title>Avoid Mystery</title>

<para>Although the discussions around adding any particular new
committer must be confidential, the rules and procedures themselves
need not be secret.  In fact, it's best to publish them, so people
realize that the committers are not some mysterious Star Chamber,
closed off to mere mortals, but that anyone can join simply by posting
good patches and knowing how to handle herself in the community.
In the Subversion project, we put this information right in the
developer guidelines document, since the people most likely to be
interested in how commit access is granted are those thinking of
contributing code to the project.</para>

<para>In addition to publishing the procedures, publish the
actual <emphasis>list</emphasis> of committers.  The traditional place
for this is a file called <filename>MAINTAINERS</filename>
or <filename>COMMITTERS</filename> in the top level of the project's
source code tree.  It should list all the full committers first,
followed by the various partial commit domains and the members of each
domain.  Each person should be listed by name and email address,
though the address can be encoded to prevent spam (see
<xref linkend="address-hiding"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="technical-infrastructure"/></phrase>) if the
person prefers that.</para>

<para>Since the distinction between full commit and partial commit
access is obvious and well defined, it is proper for the list to make
that distinction too.  Beyond that, the list should not try to
indicate the informal distinctions that inevitably arise in a project,
such as who is particularly influential and how.  It is a public
record, not an acknowledgments file.  List committers either in
alphabetical order, or in the order in which they arrived.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>


<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="credit">
<title>Credit</title>

<para>Credit is the primary currency of the free software world.
Whatever people may say about their motivations for participating in a
project, I don't know any developers who would be happy doing all
their work anonymously, or under someone else's name.  There are
tangible reasons for this: one's reputation in a project roughly
governs how much influence one has, and participation in an open
source project can also indirectly have monetary value, because
some employers now look for it on resum&eacute;s.  There are also
intangible reasons, perhaps even more powerful: people simply want to
be appreciated, and instinctively look for signs that their work was
recognized by others.  The promise of credit is therefore one of best
motivators the project has.  When small contributions are
acknowledged, people come back to do more.</para>

<para>One of the most important features of collaborative development
software (see <xref linkend="technical-infrastructure"/>) is that
it keeps accurate records of who did what, when.  Wherever possible,
use these existing mechanisms to make sure that credit is distributed
accurately, and be specific about the nature of the contribution.
Don't just write "Thanks to J. Random &lt;jrandom@example.com&gt;" if
instead you can write "Thanks to J. Random &lt;jrandom@example.com&gt;
for the bug report and reproduction recipe" in a log message.</para>

<para>In Subversion, we have an informal but consistent policy of
crediting the reporter of a bug in either the issue filed, if there is
one, or the log message of the commit that fixes the bug, if not.  A
quick survey of Subversion commit logs up to commit number 14525 shows
that about 10% of commits give credit to someone by name and email
address, usually the person who reported or analyzed the bug fixed by
that commit.  Note that this person is different from the developer
who actually made the commit, whose name is already recorded
automatically by the version control system.  Of the 80-odd full and
partial committers Subversion has today, 55 were credited in the
commit logs (usually multiple times) before they became committers
themselves.  This does not, of course, prove that being credited was a
factor in their continued involvement, but it at least sets up an
atmosphere in which people know they can count on their contributions
being acknowledged.</para>

<para>It is important to distinguish between routine acknowledgment
and special thanks.  When discussing a particular piece of code, or
some other contribution someone made, it is fine to acknowledge their
work.  For example, saying "Daniel's recent changes to the delta code
mean we can now implement feature X" simultaneously helps people
identify which changes you're talking about and acknowledges Daniel's
work.  On the other hand, posting solely to thank Daniel for the delta
code changes serves no immediate practical purpose.  It doesn't add
any information, since the version control system and other mechanisms
have already recorded the fact that he made the changes.  Thanking
everyone for everything would be distracting and ultimately
information-free, since thanks are effective largely by how much they
stand out from the default, background level of favorable comment
going on all the time.  This does not mean, of course, that you should
never thank people.  Just make sure to do it in ways that tend not to
lead to credit inflation.  Following these guidelines will
help:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>The more ephemeral the forum, the more free you
            should feel to express thanks there.  For example,
            thanking someone for their bugfix in passing during an IRC
            conversation is fine, as is an aside in an email devoted
            mainly to other topics.  But don't post an email solely to
            thank someone, unless it's for a truly unusual feat.
            Likewise, don't clutter the project's web pages with
            expressions of gratitude.  Once you start that, it'll
            never be clear when or where to stop. And
            <emphasis>never</emphasis> put thanks into comments in the
            code; that would only be a distraction from the primary
            purpose of comments, which is to help the reader
            understand the code.</para> 
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>The less involved someone is in the project, the
            more appropriate it is to thank her for something she
            did.  This may sound counterintuitive, but it fits with
            the attitude that expressing thanks is something you do
            when someone contributes even more than you thought she
            would.  Thus, to constantly thank regular contributors for
            doing what they normally do would be to express a lower
            expectation of them than they have of themselves.  If
            anything, you want to aim for the opposite effect!</para>

            <para>There are occasional exceptions to this rule.  It's
            acceptable to thank someone for fulfilling his expected
            role when that role involves temporary, intense efforts
            from time to time.  The canonical example is the release
            manager, who goes into high gear around the time of each
            release, but otherwise lies dormant (dormant as a release
            manager, in any case&mdash;he may also be an active
            developer, but that's a different matter).
            </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>As with criticism and crediting, gratitude should
            be specific.  Don't thank people just for being great,
            even if they are.  Thank them for something they did that
            was out of the ordinary, and for bonus points, say
            exactly why what they did was so great.</para> 
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>In general, there is always a tension between making sure that
people's individual contributions are recognized, and making sure the
project is a group effort rather than a collection of individual
glories.  Just remain aware of this tension and try to err on the
side of group, and things won't get out of hand.</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="forks">
<title>Forks</title>

<para>In <xref linkend="forkability"/><phrase output="printed">
in <xref linkend="social-infrastructure"/></phrase>, we saw how
the <emphasis>potential</emphasis> to fork has important effects on
how projects are governed.  But what happens when a fork actually
occurs?  How should you handle it, and what effects can you expect it
to have?  Conversely, when should you <emphasis>initiate</emphasis> a
fork?</para>

<para>The answers depend on what kind of fork it is.  Some forks are
due to amicable but irreconcilable disagreements about the direction
of the project; perhaps more are due to both technical disagreements
and interpersonal conflicts.  Of course, it's not always possible to
tell the difference between the two, as technical arguments may
involve personal elements as well.  What all forks have in common is
that one group of developers (or sometimes even just one developer)
has decided that the costs of working with some or all of the others
now outweigh the benefits.</para>

<para>Once a project forks, there is no definitive answer to the
question of which fork is the "true" or "original" project.  People
will colloquially talk of fork F coming out of project P, as though P
is continuing unchanged down some natural path while F diverges into
new territory, but this is, in effect, a declaration of how that
particular observer feels about it.  It is fundamentally a matter of
perception: when a large enough percentage of observers agree, the
assertion starts to become true.  It is not the case that there is an
objective truth from the outset, one that we are only imperfectly able to
perceive at first.  Rather, the perceptions <emphasis>are</emphasis>
the objective truth, since ultimately a project&mdash;or a
fork&mdash;is an entity that exists only in people's minds
anyway.</para>

<para>If those initiating the fork feel that they are
sprouting a new branch off the main project, the perception question
is resolved immediately and easily.  Everyone, both developers and
users, will treat the fork as a new project, with a new name (perhaps
based on the old name, but easily distinguishable from it), a separate
web site, and a separate philosophy or goal.  Things get messier,
however, when both sides feel they are the legitimate guardians of the
original project and therefore have the right to continue using the
original name.  If there is some organization with trademark rights to
the name, or legal control over the domain or web pages, that usually
resolves the issue by fiat: that organization will decide who is the
project and who is the fork, because it holds all the cards in a
public relations war.  Naturally, things rarely get that far: since
everyone already knows what the power dynamics are, they will avoid
fighting a battle whose outcome is known in advance, and just jump
straight to the end.</para>

<para>Fortunately, in most cases there is little doubt as to which is
the project and which is the fork, because a fork is, in essence, a vote
of confidence.  If more than half of the developers are in favor of
whatever course the fork proposes to take, usually there is no need to
fork&mdash;the project can simply go that way itself, unless it is run
as a dictatorship with a particularly stubborn dictator.  On the other
hand, if fewer than half of the developers are in favor, the fork is a
clearly minority rebellion, and both courtesy and common sense
indicate that it should think of itself as the divergent branch rather
than the main line.</para>

<sect2 id="forks-handling">
<title>Handling a Fork</title>

<para>If someone threatens a fork in your project, keep calm and
remember your long-term goals.  The mere
<emphasis>existence</emphasis> of a fork isn't what hurts a project;
rather, it's the loss of developers and users.  Your real aim,
therefore, is not to squelch the fork, but to minimize these harmful
effects.  You may be mad, you may feel that the fork was unjust and
uncalled for, but expressing that publicly can only alienate undecided
developers.  Instead, don't force people to make exclusive choices,
and be as cooperative as is practicable with the fork.  To start with,
don't remove someone's commit access in your project just because he
decided to work on the fork.  Work on the fork doesn't mean that
person has suddenly lost his competence to work on the original
project; committers before should remain committers afterward.  Beyond
that, you should express your desire to remain as compatible as
possible with the fork, and say that you hope developers will port
changes between the two whenever appropriate.  If you have
administrative access to the project's servers, publicly offer the
forkers infrastructure help at startup time.  For example, offer them
a complete, deep-history copy of the version control repository, if
there's no other way for them to get it, so that they don't have to
start off without historical data (this may not be necessary depending
on the version control system).  Ask them if there's anything else
they need, and provide it if you can.  Bend over backward to show
that you are not standing in the way, and that you want the fork to
succeed or fail on its own merits and nothing else.</para>

<para>The reason to do all this&mdash;and do it publicly&mdash;is not
to actually help the fork, but to persuade developers that your side
is a safe bet, by appearing as non-vindictive as possible.  In war it
sometimes makes sense (strategic sense, if not human sense) to force
people to choose sides, but in free software it almost never does.  In
fact, after a fork some developers often openly work on both projects,
and do their best to keep the two compatible.  These developers help
keep the lines of communication open after the fork.  They allow your
project to benefit from interesting new features in the fork (yes, the
fork may have things you want), and also increase the chances of a
merger down the road.</para>

<para>Sometimes a fork becomes so successful that, even though it was
regarded even by its own instigators as a fork at the outset, it
becomes the version everybody prefers, and eventually supplants the
original by popular demand.  A famous instance of this was the
GCC/EGCS fork.  The <firstterm>GNU Compiler Collection</firstterm>
(<firstterm>GCC</firstterm>, formerly the <firstterm>GNU C
Compiler</firstterm>) is the most popular open source native-code
compiler, and also one of the 
most portable compilers in the world.  Due to disagreements between the GCC's
official maintainers and Cygnus Software,<footnote><para>Now part of
RedHat (<ulink url="http://www.redhat.com/"/>).</para></footnote> one
of GCC's most active developer groups, Cygnus created a fork of GCC
called <firstterm>EGCS</firstterm>.  The fork was deliberately
non-adversarial: the EGCS developers did not, at any point, try to
portray their version of GCC as a new official version.  Instead, they
concentrated on making EGCS as good as possible, incorporating patches
at a faster rate than the official GCC maintainers.  EGCS gained in
popularity, and eventually some major operating system distributors
decided to package EGCS as their default compiler instead of GCC.  At
this point, it became clear to the GCC maintainers that holding on to
the "GCC" name while everyone switched to the EGCS fork would burden
everyone with a needless name change, yet do nothing to prevent the
switchover.  So GCC adopted the EGCS codebase, and there is once again
a single GCC, but greatly improved because of the fork.</para>

<para>This example shows why you cannot always regard a fork as an
unadulteratedly bad thing.  A fork may be painful and unwelcome at the
time, but you cannot necessarily know whether it will succeed.
Therefore, you and the rest of the project should keep an eye on it,
and be prepared not only to absorb features and code where possible,
but in the most extreme case to even join the fork if it gains the
bulk of the project's mindshare.  Of course, you will often be able to
predict a fork's likelihood of success by seeing who joins it.  If the
fork is started by the project's biggest complainer and joined by a
handful of disgruntled developers who weren't behaving constructively
anyway, they've essentially solved a problem for you by forking, and
you probably don't need to worry about the fork taking momentum away
from the original project.  But if you see influential and respected
developers supporting the fork, you should ask yourself why.  Perhaps
the project was being overly restrictive, and the best solution is to
adopt into the mainline project some or all of the actions
contemplated by the fork&mdash;in essence, to avoid the fork by
becoming it.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="forks-initiating">
<title>Initiating a Fork</title>

<para>All the advice here assumes that you are forking as a last
resort.  Exhaust all other possibilities before starting a fork.
Forking almost always means losing developers, with only an uncertain
promise of gaining new ones later.  It also means starting out with
competition for users' attention: everyone who's about to download the
software has to ask themselves: "Hmm, do I want that one or the other
one?"  Whichever one you are, the situation is messy, because a
question has been introduced that wasn't there before.  Some people
maintain that forks are healthy for the software ecosystem as a whole,
by a standard natural selection argument: the fittest will survive,
which means that, in the end, everyone gets better software.  This may
be true from the ecosystem's point of view, but it's not true from the
point of view of any individual project.  Most forks do not succeed,
and most projects are not happy to be forked.</para>

<para>A corollary is that you should not use the threat of a fork as
an extremist debating technique&mdash;"Do things my way or I'll fork
the project!"&mdash;because everyone is aware that a fork that fails
to attract developers away from the original project is unlikely to
survive long.  All observers&mdash;not just developers, but users and
operating system packagers too&mdash;will make their own judgement about
which side to choose.  You should therefore appear extremely reluctant
to fork, so that if you finally do it, you can credibly claim it was
the only route left.</para>

<para>Do not neglect to take <emphasis>all</emphasis> factors into
account in evaluating the potential success of your fork.  For
example, if many of the developers on a project have the same
employer, then even if they are disgruntled and privately in favor of
a fork, they are unlikely to say so out loud if they know that their
employer is against it.  Many free software programmers like to think
that having a free license on the code means no one company can
dominate development.  It is true that the license is, in an ultimate
sense, a guarantor of freedom&mdash;if others want badly enough to
fork the project, and have the resources to do so, they can.  But in
practice, some projects' development teams are mostly funded by one
entity, and there is no point pretending that that entity's support
doesn't matter.  If it is opposed to the fork, its developers are
unlikely to take part, even if they secretly want to.</para>

<para>If you still conclude that you must fork, line up support
privately first, then announce the fork in a non-hostile tone.  Even
if you are angry at, or disappointed with, the current maintainers,
don't say that in the message.  Just dispassionately state what led
you to the decision to fork, and that you mean no ill will toward the
project from which you're forking.  Assuming that you do consider it a
fork (as opposed to an emergency preservation of the original
project), emphasize that you're forking the code and not the name, and
choose a name that does not conflict with the project's name.  You can
use a name that contains or refers to the original name, as long as it
does not open the door to identity confusion.  Of course it's fine to
explain prominently on the fork's home page that it descends from the
original program, and even that it hopes to supplant it.  Just don't
make users' lives harder by forcing them to untangle an identity
dispute.</para>

<para>Finally, you can get things started on the right foot by
automatically granting all committers of the original project commit
access to the fork, including even those who openly disagreed with the
need for a fork.  Even if they never use the access, your message is
clear: there are disagreements here, but no enemies, and you welcome
code contributions from any competent source.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
