<chapter id="legal">

<title>Legal Matters: Licenses, Copyrights, Trademarks and Patents</title>

<simplesect>

<para>Legal questions have assumed a somewhat more prominent role in
free software projects over the last decade or so.  It is still the
case that the most important things about your project are its the
quality of its code, its features, and the health of its developer
community.  However, although all open source licenses share the same
basic guarantees of freedom, their terms are not exactly the same in
all details.  The particular license your project uses can affect
which entities decide to get involved in it and how.  You will
therefore need a basic understanding of free software licensing, both
to ensure that the project's license is compatible with its goals, and
to be able to discuss licensing decisions with others.</para>

<para>Please note that I am not a lawyer, and that nothing in this
book should be construed as formal legal advice.  For that, you'll
need to hire a lawyer or be one.</para>

</simplesect>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="licenses-terminology">
<title>Terminology</title>

<para>In any discussion of open source licensing, the first thing that
becomes apparent is that there seem to be many different words for the
same thing: <firstterm>free&nbsp;software</firstterm>,
<firstterm>open&nbsp;source</firstterm>,
<firstterm>FOSS</firstterm>, <firstterm>F/OSS</firstterm>, and
<firstterm>FLOSS</firstterm>.  Let's start by sorting those
out, along with a few other terms.</para>

<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term><firstterm>free software</firstterm></term>
    <listitem><para>Software that can be freely shared and modified,
              including in source code form.  The term was first
              coined by Richard Stallman, who codified it in the GNU
              General Public License (GPL), and who founded the Free
              Software Foundation (<ulink url="http://www.fsf.org/"
              >fsf.org</ulink>) to promote the concept.</para>

              <para>Although "free software" covers the
              same set of software as "open source", the FSF, among
              others, prefers the former term because it emphasizes
              the idea of freedom, and the concept of
              freely redistributable software as primarily a social
              movement rather than a technical one.  The FSF
              acknowledges that the term is ambiguous&mdash;it could
              mean "free" as in "zero-cost", instead of "free" as in
              "freedom"&mdash;but feels that it's still the best term,
              all things considered, and that the other possibilities
              in English have their own ambiguities.  (Throughout this
              book, "free" is used in the "freedom" sense, not the
              "zero-cost" sense.)</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term><firstterm>open source software</firstterm></term>

    <listitem><para>Free software under another name.  The
              different name is sometimes used to indicate a philosophical
              difference, however.  In fact, the term "open source"
              was coined by the group that founded the Open Source 
              Initiative (<ulink url="http://www.opensource.org/"
              >opensource.org</ulink>)
              as a deliberate alternative to "free software".  Their
              goal at the time was largely to make such software a
              more palatable choice for
              corporations, by presenting it as a development
              methodology rather than as a political
              movement.<footnote><para>Disclaimer: Years after these
              events, I served as a member of the Board of Directors
              of the Open Source Initiative for three years, from
              2011-2014.  The ideological gap between the OSI and the
              FSF is much smaller these days than it was when the OSI
              was founded, in my opinion, and lately the two
              organizations have increasingly found common ground on
              which to cooperate.  I remain a happy member of both,
              and urge you to join them too: <ulink
              url="http://opensource.org/join"
              >opensource.org/join</ulink> and <ulink
              url="http://fsf.org/join"
              >fsf.org/join</ulink>.</para></footnote></para>

              <para>While any license that is free is also open
              source, and vice versa (with a few minor exceptions that
              have no practical consequences),
              people tend to pick one term and stick with it.  In
              general, those who prefer "free software" are more
              likely to have a philosophical or moral stance on the
              issue, while those who prefer "open source" either don't
              view it as a matter of freedom, or are not interested in
              advertising the fact that they do.  See
              <xref linkend="free-vs-open-source"/><phrase
              output="printed"> in
              <xref linkend="introduction"/></phrase> for a more
              detailed history of this terminological schism.</para>

              <para>The Free Software Foundation has an
              excellent&mdash;utterly unobjective, but nuanced and
              quite fair&mdash;exegesis of the two terms, at <ulink
              url="http://www.fsf.org/licensing/essays/free-software-for-freedom.html"
              >www.fsf.org/licensing/essays/free-software-for-freedom.html</ulink>.
              The Open Source Initiative's take on it is (or was, in
              2002) spread across two pages: <ulink
              url="http://web.archive.org/web/20021204155022/http://www.opensource.org/advocacy/case_for_hackers.php#marketing"
              >web.archive.org/web/20021204155022/http://www.opensource.org/advocacy/case_for_hackers.php#marketing</ulink>
              and <ulink
              url="http://web.archive.org/web/20021204155022/http://www.opensource.org/advocacy/free-notfree.php"
              >web.archive.org/web/20021204155022/http://www.opensource.org/advocacy/free-notfree.php</ulink>
              [sic].</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term><firstterm>FOSS</firstterm>,
                      <firstterm>F/OSS</firstterm>,
                      <firstterm>FLOSS</firstterm></term>

    <listitem><para>Where there are two of anything, there will soon
              be three, and that is exactly what is happening with
              terms for free software.  The academic world, perhaps
              wanting precision and inclusiveness over elegance, seems
              to have settled on FOSS, or sometimes F/OSS, standing
              for "Free / Open Source Software".  Another variant
              gaining momentum is FLOSS, which
              stands for "Free / Libre Open Source Software"
              (<foreignphrase>libre</foreignphrase> is familiar from
              many Romance languages and does not suffer from the ambiguities
              of "free"; see
              <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FLOSS"
              >en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FLOSS</ulink> for more).</para>

              <para>All these terms mean the same thing:
              software that can be modified and redistributed by
              everyone, sometimes&mdash;but not always&mdash;with the
              requirement that derivative works be freely
              redistributable under the same terms.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term><firstterm>DFSG-compliant</firstterm></term>
    <listitem><para>Compliant with the Debian Free Software Guidelines
              (<ulink
              url="http://www.debian.org/social_contract#guidelines"
              >debian.org/social_contract#guidelines</ulink>).
              This is a widely-used test for whether a given license
              is truly open source
              (free, <foreignphrase>libre</foreignphrase>, etc.).  The
              Debian Project's mission is to maintain an entirely free
              operating system, such that someone installing it need
              never doubt that she has the right to modify and
              redistribute any or all of the system.  The Debian Free
              Software Guidelines are the requirements that a software
              package's license must meet in order to be included in
              Debian.  Because the Debian Project spent a good deal of
              time thinking about how to construct such a test, the
              guidelines they came up with have proven very robust
              (see <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DFSG"
              >en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DFSG</ulink>),
              and as far as I'm aware, no serious objection to them has
              been raised either by the Free Software Foundation or
              the Open Source Initiative.  If you know that a given
              license is DFSG-compliant, you know that it guarantees
              all the important freedoms (such as forkability even
              against the original author's wishes) required to
              sustain the dynamics of an open source project.  Since
              2004, the Debian Project has maintained a list of known
              DFSG-compliant licenses at <ulink
              url="https://wiki.debian.org/DFSGLicenses"
              >wiki.debian.org/DFSGLicenses</ulink>.  All of the licenses
              discussed in this chapter are DFSG-compliant.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term><firstterm>OSI-approved</firstterm></term>
    <listitem><para>Approved by the Open Source Initiative.  This is
              another widely-used test of whether a license permits
              all the necessary freedoms.  The OSI's definition of
              open source software is based on the Debian Free
              Software Guidelines, and any license that meets one
              definition almost always meets the other.  There have
              been a few exceptions over the years, but only involving
              niche licenses and none of any relevance here.  The OSI
              maintains a list of all
              licenses it has ever approved, at
              <ulink url="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/"
              >opensource.org/licenses/</ulink>, so
              that being "OSI-approved" is an unambiguous state: a
              license either is or isn't on the list.</para>

              <para>The Free Software Foundation also maintains a list
              of licenses at <ulink
              url="http://www.fsf.org/licensing/licenses/license-list.html"
              >fsf.org/licensing/licenses/license-list.html</ulink>.
              The FSF categorizes licenses not only by whether they
              are free, but whether they are compatible with the GNU
              General Public License.  GPL compatibility is an
              important topic, covered in
              <xref
              linkend="license-compatibility"/><phrase
              output="printed"> later in this chapter</phrase>.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term><firstterm>proprietary</firstterm>,
                      <firstterm>closed-source</firstterm></term>
    <listitem><para>The opposite of "free" or "open source."  It means
              software distributed under traditional, royalty-based
              licensing terms, where users pay per copy, or under any
              other terms sufficiently restrictive to prevent open
              source dynamics from operating.  Even software
              distributed at no charge can still be proprietary, if
              its license does not permit free redistribution and
              modification.</para>

              <para>Generally "proprietary" and "closed-source" are
              synonyms.  However, "closed-source" additionally implies
              that the source code cannot even be seen.  Since the
              source code cannot be seen with most proprietary
              software, this is normally a distinction without a
              difference.  However, occasionally someone releases
              proprietary software under a license that allows others
              to view the source code.  Confusingly, they sometimes
              call this "open source" or "nearly open source," etc.,
              but that's misleading. The
              <emphasis>visibility</emphasis> of the source code is
              not the issue; the important question is what you're
              allowed to do with it: if you can't copy, modify, and
              redistribute, then it's not open source.  Thus, the
              difference between proprietary and closed-source is
              mostly irrelevant; generally, the two can be treated
              as synonyms.</para>

              <para>Sometimes <firstterm>commercial</firstterm> is
              used as a synonym for "proprietary," but this is
              carelessness: the two are not the same.  Free software
              is always commercial software.  After all, free software
              can be sold, as long as the buyers are not restricted
              from giving away copies themselves.  It can be
              commercialized in other ways as well, for example by
              selling support, services, and certification.  There are
              billion-dollar companies built on free software
              today, so it is clearly neither inherently
              anti-commercial nor anti-corporate.  It is merely
              anti-proprietary, or if you prefer anti-monopolistic,
              and this is the key way in which it differs from
              per-copy license models.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term><firstterm>public domain</firstterm></term>
    <listitem><para>Having no copyright holder, meaning that there is
              no one who has the right to restrict copying of the
              work.  Being in the public domain is not the same as
              having no author.  Everything has an author, and even if a
              work's author or authors choose to put it in the public
              domain, that doesn't change the fact that they wrote
              it.</para>

              <para>When a work is in the public domain, material from
              it can be incorporated into a copyrighted work, and the
              derivative is thus under the same overall copyright as
              the original copyrighted work.  But this does not affect
              the availability of the original public domain wok.
              Thus, releasing something into the public domain is
              technically one way to make it "free," according to the
              guidelines of most free software certifying
              organizations (see <ulink
              url="http://opensource.org/faq#public-domain"
              >opensource.org/faq#public-domain</ulink> for more).
              However, there are usually good reasons to use a license
              instead of just releasing into the public domain: even
              with free software, certain terms and conditions can be
              useful, not only to the copyright holder but to
              recipients as well, as the next section makes clear.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term><firstterm>copyleft</firstterm></term>
    <listitem><para>A license that not only grants the freedoms under
              discussion here but furthermore requires that those
              freedoms apply to any derivative works.</para>

              <para>The canonical example of a copyleft license is
              still the GNU General Public License, which stipulates
              that any derivative works must also be licensed under
              the GPL; see <xref
              linkend="license-compatibility"/><phrase
              output="printed"> later in this chapter</phrase> for
              more.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term><firstterm>non-copyleft</firstterm> or <firstterm>permissive</firstterm></term>
    <listitem><para>A license that grants the freedoms under
              discussion here but that does <emphasis>not</emphasis>
              have a clause requiring that they apply to derivative
              works as well.</para>
              <!-- possv2 todo: make an Apache-2.0 reference,
                   replacing BSD and MIT, and point to it from here.  -->
              <para>Two early and well-known examples of permissive
              licenses are the BSD and MIT licenses, but the more
              recent Apache Software License version 2
              (<ulink
              url="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0"
              >apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0</ulink>) is
              also very popular&mdash;increasingly so&mdash;and
              somewhat better adapted to the legal landscape of modern
              open source software development.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

</variablelist>

<sidebar id="free-open-same">
  <title>"Free Software" and "Open Source" Are the Same Licenses.</title>

<para>Occasionally people will make the mistake of thinking that
copyleft licenses (like the GPL) comprise "free software", while the
permissive licenses comprise "open source".  This is wrong, but it
comes up just often enough to be worth mentioning here.  Both free
software and open source include <emphasis>both</emphasis> the
copyleft and non-copyleft licenses&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;this is something
that all the license-certifying organizations, including the FSF, the
OSI, and the Debian Project, have always agreed on.  If you see
someone, particularly a journalist, making this mistake, please
politely correct them, perhaps by pointing them to this note (
<ulink url="http://producingoss.com/en/terminology.html#free-open-same"
>producingoss.com/en/terminology.html#free-open-same</ulink>).
The last thing we need is yet more terminological confusion in the
free and open source software movement.</para>

</sidebar>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="license-aspects">
<title>Aspects of Licenses</title>

<para>Although there are many different free software licenses
available, in the important respects they all say the same things:
that anyone can modify the code, that anyone can redistribute it both
in original and modified form, and that the copyright holders and
authors provide no warranties whatsoever (avoiding liability is
especially important given that people might run modified versions
without even knowing it).  The differences between licences boil down
to a few oft-recurring issues:</para>

<variablelist>
  <varlistentry><term>compatibility with proprietary licenses</term>
    <listitem><para>Some free licenses allow the covered code to be
              used in proprietary programs.  This does not affect the
              licensing terms of the proprietary program: it is still
              as proprietary as ever, it just happens to contain some
              code from a non-proprietary source.  The Apache License,
              X Consortium License, BSD-style license, and the
              MIT-style license are all examples of
              proprietary-compatible licenses.</para> 
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <!-- possv2 todo: is the below completely true?  Check, and even if
       it is true, update to include AGPL. -->
  <varlistentry><term>compatibility with other types of free licenses</term>
    <listitem><para>Most free licenses are compatible with each other,
              meaning that code under one license can be combined with
              code under another, and the result distributed under
              either license without violating the terms of the
              other.  The major exception to this is the GNU General
              Public License, which requires that any work using GPLed
              code be itself distributed under the GPL, and without
              adding any further restrictions beyond what the GPL
              requires.  The GPL is compatible with some free
              licenses, but not with others.  This is discussed in more
              detail in
              <xref linkend="license-compatibility"/><phrase
              output="printed"> later in this chapter</phrase>.</para> 
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>enforcement of crediting</term>
    <listitem><para>Some free licenses stipulate that any use of the
              covered code be accompanied by a notice, whose placement
              and display is usually specified, giving credit to the
              authors or copyright holders of the code.  These
              licenses are often still proprietary-compatible: they do
              not necessarily demand that the derivative work be free,
              merely that credit be given to the free code.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>protection of trademark</term>
    <listitem><para>A variant of credit enforcement.
              Trademark-protecting licenses specify that the name of
              the original software (or its copyright holders, or
              their institution, etc.) may <emphasis>not</emphasis> be
              used to identify derivative works, at least not without
              prior written permission.  This restriction can be
              implemented purely via trademark law anyway, whether or
              not it is also stipulated by the copyright license, so
              such clauses can be somewhat legally
              redundant&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;in effect, they amplify a
              trademark infringement into a copyright infringement as
              well.</para>

              <para>Although credit enforcement insists that a certain
              name be used, and trademark protection insists that it
              not be used, they are both expressions of the same
              concept: that the original code's reputation be
              preserved, and not tarnished by association.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>patent snapback</term>
    <listitem><para>Certain licenses (e.g., the GNU General Public
              License version 3, the Apache License version 2, the
              Mozilla Public License 2.0, and a few others) contain
              language designed
              to prevent people from using patent law to take away the
              rights granted under copyright law by the
              licenses.  They require contributors to grant patent
              licenses along with their contribution, covering any
              patents licenseable by the contributor that would be
              infringed by their contribution (or by the incorporation
              of their contribution into the work as a whole).  Then
              they go further: if someone using software under the
              license initiates patent litigation against another party,
              claiming that the covered work infringes, the initiator
              automatically <emphasis>loses</emphasis> all the
              patent grants otherwise provided for that work by the
              license, and in the case of the GPL-3.0 loses their right
              to distribute under the license altogether.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry><term>protection of "artistic integrity"</term>
    <listitem><para>Some licenses (the Artistic License, used
              for the most popular implementation of the Perl
              programming language, and Donald Knuth's TeX license,
              for example) require that modification and
              redistribution be done in a manner that distinguishes
              clearly between the pristine original version of the
              code and any modifications.  They permit essentially the
              same freedoms as other free licenses, but impose certain
              requirements that make the integrity of the original
              code easy to verify.  These licenses have not caught on
              much beyond the specific programs they were made for,
              and will not be discussed in this chapter; they are
              mentioned here only for the sake of completeness.  I do
              not recommend licensing new code under them.</para> 
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para>Most of these stipulations are not mutually exclusive, and some
licenses include several.  The common thread among them is that they
place demands on the recipient in exchange for the recipient's right
to use and/or redistribute the code.</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="license-compatibility">
<title>The GPL and License Compatibility</title>

<para>The sharpest dividing line in licensing is that between
proprietary-incompatible and proprietary-compatible licenses, that is,
between the copyleft licenses and everything else.  The canonical
example of a copyleft license is the GNU General Public License (along
with its network-oriented variant, the Affero GNU General Public
License or AGPL, introduced later in this chapter in <xref
linkend="gnu-affero-gpl"/>), and one of the most important
considerations in choosing the GPL or AGPL is the extent to which it
is compatible with other licenses.  For brevity, I'll refer just to
the GPL below, but most of this applies to the AGPL as well.</para>

<para>Because the primary goal of the GPL's authors is the promotion
of free software, they deliberately crafted the license to make it
impossible to mix GPLed code into proprietary programs.  Specifically,
among the GPL's requirements (see <ulink
url="http://www.fsf.org/licensing/licenses/gpl.html"
>fsf.org/licensing/licenses/gpl.html</ulink> for its full text) are
these two:</para>

<orderedlist>
  <listitem><para>Any derivative work&mdash;that is, any work
            containing a nontrivial amount of GPLed code&mdash;must
            itself be distributed under the GPL.</para> 
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>No additional restrictions may be placed on the
            redistribution of either the original work or a derivative
            work.  (The exact language is: "You may not impose any
            further restrictions on the exercise of the rights granted
            or affirmed under this License.")</para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>With these conditions, the GPL succeeds in making freedom
contagious.  Once a program is copyrighted under the GPL, its terms of
redistribution are
<firstterm>reciprocal</firstterm><footnote><para>Some people use the
term <firstterm>viral</firstterm> to describe the GPL's
contagiousness; they do not always mean this pejoratively, but I still
prefer "reciprocal" because it's more descriptive and less connotative
of disease.</para></footnote>&mdash;they are passed
on to anything else the code gets incorporated into, making it
effectively impossible to use GPLed code in closed-source programs.
However, these same clauses also make the GPL incompatible with
certain other free licenses.  The usual way this happens is that the
other license imposes a requirement&mdash;for example, a credit clause
requiring the original authors to be mentioned in some way&mdash;that
is incompatible with the GPL's "You may not impose any further
restrictions..." language.  From the point of view of the Free
Software Foundation, these second-order consequences are desirable, or
at least not regrettable.  The GPL not only keeps your software free,
but effectively makes your software an agent in pushing
<emphasis>other</emphasis> software to enforce freedom as well.</para>

<para>The question of whether or not this is a good way to
promote free software is one of the most persistent holy wars on the
Internet (see <xref linkend="holy-wars"/><phrase output="printed">
in <xref linkend="communications"/></phrase>), and we won't
investigate it here.  What's important for our purposes is that
GPL compatibility is something to consider when choosing a license.  The
GPL is by far the most popular open source license, having more than
twice as many projects released under it as under the next most
popular licenses<footnote><para>This statistic is based on an
aggregation of several license count sources, combined with some
reasonable definitional assumptions.</para></footnote>.
If you want your code to be able to be
mixed freely with GPLed code&mdash;and there's a lot of GPLed code out
there&mdash;then you should pick a GPL-compatible license.  Most of
the GPL-compatible open source licenses are also
proprietary-compatible: that is, code under such a license can be used
in a GPLed program, and it can be used in a proprietary program.  Of
course, the <emphasis>results</emphasis> of these mixings would not be
compatible with each other, since one would be under the GPL and the
other would be under a closed-source license.  But that concern
applies only to the derivative works, not to the code you distribute
in the first place.</para>

<para>Fortunately, the Free Software Foundation maintains a list
showing which licenses are compatible with the GPL and which are not,
at <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/license-list.html"
>gnu.org/licenses/license-list.html</ulink>.  All
of the licenses discussed in this chapter are present on that list, on
one side or the other.</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="legal-diligence">
<title>Legal Diligence: What to Check Before You Release</title>

<para><emphasis>1 Sep 2014: If you're reading this note, then you've
encountered this section while it's still being written; see <ulink
url="http://producingoss.com/v2.html"
>producingoss.com/v2.html</ulink> for details.  possv2 todo: things
that will be mentioned here: the <ulink
url="http://www.h-online.com/open/news/item/Chart-js-available-after-a-false-start-1826669.html"
>Chart.js "apology to open source" event</ulink>, a note about
GPL-compatibility, and some of the things discussed in
<ulink url="http://opentechstrategies.com/resources#oss-licensing"
>opentechstrategies.com/resources#oss-licensing</ulink>.
</emphasis></para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="license-choosing">
<!-- For link compatibility with now-obsolete IDs from older editions. -->
<anchor id="license-choosing-mit-x" />
<anchor id="license-bsd" />
<title>Choosing a License</title>

<para>When choosing a license to apply to your project, use an
existing license instead of making up a new one.  And don't just use
any existing license&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;use one of the widely-used,
well-recognized existing licenses.</para>

<para>Such licenses are familiar to many people already.  If you use
one of them, people won't feel they have to read the legalese in order
to use your code, because they'll have already done so for that
license a long time ago.  Thus, you reduce or remove one possible
barrier to entry for your project.  They are also of a high quality:
they are the products of much thought and experience; indeed most
of them are revisions of previous versions of themselves, and the
modern versions represent a great deal of accumulated legal and
technical wisdom.  Unless your project has truly unusual needs, it is
unlikely you could do better, even with a team of lawyers at your
disposal.</para>

<para>Below is a list of licenses that in my opinion meets these
criteria; in parentheses are the standard formal abbreviation for the
license and an authoritative URL for its full text.  This list is not
in order of preference, but rather in roughly descending order from
strong copyleft at the top to completely non-copyleft at the bottom.
The exact provisions of each license differ in various interesting
ways (except for BSD and MIT, which differ only in uninteresting
ways), and there isn't space here to explore all the possible
ramifications of each for your project.  However, many good
discussions of that sort are available on the Internet; in particular
the Wikipedia pages for these licenses generally give good
overviews.</para>

<para>If you have nothing else to guide you and you want a copyleft
license, then choose either the GPL-3.0 or the
AGPL-3.0&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;the difference between them will be
discussed below&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;and if you want a non-copyleft
license, choose Apache-2.0.  I've put those licenses in boldface to
reflect this.</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><emphasis role="bold" >GNU General Public License version 3</emphasis> (<code>GPL-3.0</code>, <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html" >gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html</ulink>)</listitem>
  <listitem><emphasis role="bold" >GNU Affero General Public License version 3</emphasis> (<code>AGPL-3.0</code>, <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/agpl.html" >gnu.org/licenses/agpl.html</ulink>)</listitem>
  <listitem>Mozilla Public License 2.0 (<code>MPL-2.0</code>, <ulink url="https://www.mozilla.org/MPL/" >mozilla.org/MPL</ulink>)</listitem>
  <listitem>GNU Library or "Lesser" General Public License version 3 (<code>LGPL-3.0</code>, <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl.html" >gnu.org/licenses/lgpl.html</ulink>)</listitem>
  <listitem>Eclipse Public License 1.0 (<code>EPL-1.0</code>, <ulink url="https://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html" >eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html</ulink>) <emphasis>(Note that version 2 of the EPL was almost ready as of mid-2014, and may be out by the time you read this.)</emphasis></listitem>
  <listitem><emphasis role="bold" >Apache License 2.0</emphasis> (<code>Apache-2.0</code>, <ulink url="http://apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0" >apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0</ulink>)</listitem>
  <listitem>BSD 2-Clause ("Simplified" or "FreeBSD") license (<code>BSD-2-Clause</code>, <ulink url="http://opensource.org/licenses/BSD-2-Clause" >opensource.org/licenses/BSD-2-Clause</ulink>)</listitem>
  <listitem>MIT license (<code>MIT</code>, <ulink url="http://opensource.org/licenses/MIT" >opensource.org/licenses/MIT</ulink>)</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>The mechanics of applying a license to your project are
discussed in <xref linkend="license-quickstart-applying"/><phrase
output="printed"> in <xref
linkend="getting-started"/></phrase>.</para>

<sect2 id="license-choosing-gpl">
<title>The GNU General Public License</title>

<para>If you prefer that your project's code not be used in
proprietary programs, or if you at least don't care whether or not it
can be used in proprietary programs, the GNU General Public License is
a good choice.</para>

<para>When writing a code library that is meant mainly to be used as
part of other programs, consider carefully whether the restrictions
imposed by the GPL are in line with your project's goals.  In some
cases&mdash;for example, when you're trying to unseat a competing,
proprietary library that offers the same functionality&mdash;it may
make more strategic sense to license your code in such a way that it
can be mixed into proprietary programs, even though you would
otherwise not wish this.  The Free Software Foundation even fashioned
an alternative to the GPL for such circumstances: the <firstterm>GNU
Lesser GPL</firstterm><footnote><para>Originally named the
<firstterm>GNU Library GPL</firstterm>, and later renamed by the
FSF).</para></footnote> The LGPL has looser restrictions than the GPL,
and can be mixed more easily with non-free code.  The FSF's page about
the LGPL, <ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/lgpl.html"
>gnu.org/licenses/lgpl.html</ulink>, has a good discussion of when to
use it.</para>

<sect3 id="gpl-future-proofing">
<title>The "or any later version" Option: Future-Proofing the GPL.</title>

<para>The GPL has a well-known optional recommendation that you
release software under the current version of the GPL while giving
downstream recipients the option to redistribute it under any
<emphasis>later</emphasis> (i.e., future) version.  The way to offer
this option is to put language like this in the license headers (see
<xref linkend="license-quickstart-applying"/><phrase output="printed">
in <xref linkend="getting-started"/></phrase>) of the actual source
files:</para>

<blockquote>
<para><emphasis>This program is free software: you can redistribute it
and/or modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License as
published by the Free Software Foundation, either version 3 of the
License, <emphasis role="bold">or (at your option) any later
version.</emphasis></emphasis></para>
</blockquote>

<para>(Emphasis added.)</para>

<para>Whether you want to offer that option depends largely on how
likely you think the Free Software Foundation is to make GPL revisions
that you would approve of.  I think the FSF has done a good job of
that so far, and I generally do include that option when I use the
GPL.  That way I don't have to be responsible for updating the
licenses myself forever&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;which is good, since I won't
be around forever.  Others can do it, either just to keep the software
license up-to-date with legal developments, or to solve some future
license compatibility problem that couldn't have been anticipated now
(for example, see the compatibility discussion in <xref
linkend="gnu-affero-gpl"/> below).</para>

<para>Not everyone feels the same way, however; most notably, the
Linux kernel is famously licensed under the GNU GPL version 2
<emphasis>without</emphasis> the "or any later version" clause, and
influential kernel copyright holders, especially Linus Torvalds, have
expressed clearly that they do not intend to move its license to
version 3.0.</para>

<para>This book cannot answer the question of whether you should
include the option or not.  You now know that you have the choice, at
least, and that different people come to different conclusions about
it.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="gnu-affero-gpl">
<title>The GNU Affero GPL: A Version of the GNU GPL for Server-Side Code</title>

<para>In 2007, the Free Software Foundation released a variant of the
GPL called the <firstterm>GNU Affero GPL</firstterm><footnote><para>
The history of the license and its name is a bit complicated.  The
first version of the license was originally released by Affero, Inc,
who based it on the GNU GPL version 2.  At the time, this was commonly
referred to as the AGPL.  Later, the Free Software Foundation decided
to adopt the idea, but by then they had released version 3 of their
GNU GPL, so they based their new Affero-ized license on that and
called it the "GNU AGPL".  The old Affero license is now rarely used
and is more or less deprecated, but to avoid ambiguity, say "AGPL-3.0"
or "GNU AGPL" to make it clear that you're referring to the modern GNU
version of the license.</para></footnote>.  Its purpose is to bring
copyleft-style sharing provisions to the increasing amount of code
being run as hosted services&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;that is, software that
runs "in the cloud" on remote servers, that users interact with only
over the network, and that therefore is never directly distributed to
users as executable or source code.  Many such services use GPL'd
software, often with extensive modifications, yet could avoid
publishing their changes because they weren't actually distributing
code.</para>

<para>The AGPL's solution to this was to take the GPL and add a
"Remote Network Interaction" clause, stating "<emphasis>...if you
modify the Program, your modified version must prominently offer all
users interacting with it remotely through a computer network ... an
opportunity to receive the Corresponding Source of your version ... at
no charge, through some standard or customary means of facilitating
copying of software.</emphasis>" This expanded the GPL's enforcement
powers into the new world of application service providers.  The Free
Software Foundation recommends that the GNU AGPL 3.0 be used for any
software that will commonly be run over a network.</para>

<para>Note that the AGPL-3.0 is not directly compatible with GPL-2.0,
though it is compatible with GPL-3.0.  Since most software licensed
under GPL-2.0 includes the "or any later version" clause anyway, that
software can just be shifted to GPL-3.0 if and when you need to mix it
with AGPL-3.0 code.  However, if you need to mix with programs
licensed strictly under the GPL-2.0 (that is, programs licensed
without the "or any later version" clause), the AGPL3.0 wouldn't be
compatible with that.</para>

<para>Although the history of the AGPL-3.0 is a bit complicated, the
license itself is simple: it's just the GPL-3.0 with one extra clause
about network interaction.  The Wikipedia article on the AGPL is
excellent: <ulink
url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Affero_General_Public_License"
>en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Affero_General_Public_License</ulink></para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="is-the-gpl-free">
<title>Is the GPL free or not free?</title>

<para>One consequence of choosing the GPL (or AGPL) is the
possibility&mdash;small, but not infinitely small&mdash;of finding
yourself or your project embroiled in a dispute about whether or not
the GPL is truly "free", given that it places some restrictions on
how you redistribute the code&mdash;namely, the restriction that the
code cannot be distributed under any other license.  For some people,
the existence of this restriction means the GPL is therefore "less
free" than non-copyleft licenses.  Where this
argument usually goes, of course, is that since "more free" must be
better than "less free" (after all, who's not in favor of freedom?),
it follows that those licenses are better than the GPL.</para>

<para>This debate is another popular holy war (see
<xref linkend="holy-wars"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="communications"/></phrase>).  Avoid participating
in it, at least in project forums.  Don't attempt to prove that the
GPL is less free, as free, or more free than other licenses.  Instead,
emphasize the specific reasons your project chose the GPL.  If the
recognizability of license was a reason, say that.  If the enforcement
of a free license on derivative works was also a reason, say that too,
but refuse to be drawn into discussion about whether this makes the
code more or less "free".  Freedom is a complex topic, and there is
little point talking about it if terminology is going to be used as a
stalking horse for substance.</para>

<para>Since this is a book and not a mailing list thread, however, I
will admit that I've never understood the "GPL is not free" argument.
The only restriction the GPL imposes is that it prevents people from
imposing <emphasis>further</emphasis> restrictions.  To say that this
results in less freedom has always seemed to me like saying that
outlawing slavery reduces freedom, because it prevents some people
from owning slaves.</para>

<para>(Oh, and if you do get drawn into a debate about it, don't raise
the stakes by making inflammatory analogies.)</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="contributor-agreements">
<!-- For link compatibility with the old section ID. -->
<anchor id="copyright-assignment" />
<!-- For link compatibility with a deprecated subsection ID. -->
<anchor id="copyright-assignment-transfer" />
<title>Contributor Agreements</title>

<para><emphasis>possv2 6 Sep 2014: If you're reading this note, then
you've encountered this section while it's undergoing substantial
revision; see <ulink url="http://producingoss.com/v2.html"
>producingoss.com/v2.html</ulink> for details.  possv2 todo: discuss
Developer Certificates of Origin (DCOs) too.</emphasis></para>

<para>There are three ways to handle copyright ownership for free code
and documentation that were contributed to by many people.  The first
is to ignore the issue of copyright entirely (I don't recommend this).
The second is to collect a <firstterm>contributor license
agreement</firstterm> (<firstterm>CLA</firstterm>) from each person
who works on the project, explicitly granting the project the right to
use that person's contributions.  This is usually enough for most
projects, and the nice thing is that in some jurisdictions, CLAs can
be sent in by email.  The third way is to get actual
<firstterm>copyright assignment</firstterm> (<firstterm>CA</firstterm>
from contributors, so that the project (i.e., some legal entity,
usually a nonprofit) is the copyright owner for everything.  This way
is the most burdensome for contributors, and some contributors simply
refuse to do it; only a few projects still ask for assignment, and I don't
recommend that any project require it these days.<footnote><para>Also,
actual copyright transferral is subject to national law, and licenses
designed for the United States may encounter problems elsewhere (e.g.,
in Germany, where it's apparently not possible to transfer
copyright).</para></footnote></para>

<para>Note that even under centralized copyright ownership, the
code<footnote><para>I'll use "code" to refer to both code and
documentation, from now on.</para></footnote> remains free, because
open source licenses do not give the copyright holder the right to
retroactively proprietize all copies of the code.  So even if the
project, as a legal entity, were to suddenly turn around and start
distributing all the code under a restrictive license, that wouldn't
cause a problem for the public community.  The other developers would
simply start a fork based on the latest free copy of the code, and
continue as if nothing had happened.</para>

<sect2 id="copyright-assignment-none">
<title>Doing Nothing</title>

<para><emphasis>possv2 todo 6 Sep 2014: I'm not so sure about the
advice in this section anymore.  The legal landscape has changed, and
I've learned more.  For the moment I'm letting it stand, until I have
a chance to talk to a few more people.</emphasis></para>

<para>Most projects never collect CLAs or CAs from
their contributors.  Instead, they accept code whenever it seems
reasonably clear that the contributor intended it to be incorporated
into the project.</para>

<para>Under normal circumstances, this is okay.  But every now and
then, someone may decide to sue for copyright infringement, alleging
that they are the true owner of the code in question and that they
never agreed to its being distributed by the project under an open
source license.  For example, the SCO Group did something like this to
the Linux project, see
<ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SCO-Linux_controversies"
>en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SCO-Linux_controversies</ulink>
for details.  When this happens, the project will have no
documentation showing that the contributor formally granted the right
to use the code, which could make some legal defenses more
difficult.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="copyright-assignment-cla">
<title>Contributor License Agreements</title>

<para>CLAs probably offer the best tradeoff between safety and
convenience.  A CLA is typically an electronic form that a developer
fills out and sends in to the project.  In many jurisdictions, email
submission or an online form is enough.  A secure digital signature
may or may not be required; consult a lawyer to find out what method
would be best for `your project.</para>

<para>Most projects use two slightly different CLAs, one for
individuals, and one for corporate contributors.  But in both types,
the core language is the same: the contributor grants the
project a <emphasis>"...perpetual, worldwide, non-exclusive, no-charge,
royalty-free, irrevocable copyright license to reproduce, prepare
derivative works of, publicly display, publicly perform, sublicense,
and distribute [the] Contributions and such derivative
works."</emphasis> Again, you should have a lawyer approve any CLA,
but if you get all those adjectives into it, you're off to a good start.</para>

<para>When you request CLAs from contributors, make sure to emphasize
that you are <emphasis>not</emphasis> asking for actual copyright
assignment.  In fact, many CLAs start out by reminding the reader of
this:</para>

<blockquote>
<para><emphasis>This is a license agreement only; it does not transfer
copyright ownership and does not change your rights to use your own
Contributions for any other purpose.</emphasis></para>
</blockquote>

<para>Here are some examples:</para>

<!-- possv2 todo 6 Sep 2014: Ask Karen, James, Bradley, Aaron for
     their advice on what CLAs to use as examples? -->

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>Individual contributor CLAs:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><ulink
        url="http://apache.org/licenses/icla.txt"
        >apache.org/licenses/icla.txt</ulink>
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink
        url="http://code.google.com/legal/individual-cla-v1.0.html"
        >code.google.com/legal/individual-cla-v1.0.html</ulink>
      </para></listitem>
<!--  <listitem><para><ulink
 url="http://svn.collab.net/repos/svn-org/trunk/documents/individual-cla.txt"/>
      </para></listitem>  -->
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>Corporate contributor CLAs:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><ulink
        url="http://apache.org/licenses/cla-corporate.txt"
        >apache.org/licenses/cla-corporate.txt</ulink>
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><ulink
        url="http://code.google.com/legal/corporate-cla-v1.0.html"
        >code.google.com/legal/corporate-cla-v1.0.html</ulink>
      </para></listitem>
<!--  <listitem><para><ulink
 url="http://svn.collab.net/repos/svn-org/trunk/documents/corporate-cla.txt"/>
      </para></listitem>  -->
    </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<!-- TODO Include a government CLA too? -->

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="proprietary-relicensing">
<!-- For link compatibility with a deprecated section ID. -->
<anchor id="dual-licensing" />
<title>Proprietary Relicensing Schemes</title>

<para>Some companies offer open source code with a
<firstterm>proprietary relicensing</firstterm>
scheme<footnote><para>This is sometimes also called <firstterm>dual
licensing</firstterm>, but that term is ambiguous, as it has
historically also referred to releasing open source software under two
or more open source licenses simultaneously.  I am grateful to Bradley
Kuhn for pointing out this ambiguity and suggesting the more accurate
term.</para></footnote>, in which an open source version of the
software is available under the usual open source terms, while a
proprietary version is available for a fee.</para>

<para>Why would anyone want a proprietary version, when an open source
version is already out there?  There are two separate answers,
reflecting the two different types of proprietary relicensing.</para>

<para>The first kind is about <firstterm>selling
exceptions</firstterm> to copyleft requirements, and is typically used
with code libraries rather than with standalone applications.  The way
it works is that the library's owner (i.e., copyright holder), seeing
that some of the library's users want to incorporate it into their own
proprietary applications, sells them a promise to
<emphasis>not</emphasis> enforce the redistribution requirements of
the open source version's license.  This only works when the open
source code is under a copyleft-style license, of
course&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;in practice it is usually the GPL or
AGPL.</para>

<para>With this promise in hand, the downstream users can use the
library in their proprietary product without worry that they might be
forced to share the source code to the full product under the copyleft
license.  One well-known example of "selling exceptions" is the MySQL
database engine, which is distributed under the GPL version 2, but
with a proprietary license offering available for many years, first
from the Swedish company MySQL AB, and later from Oracle, Inc, which
purchased MySQL AB in 2008.</para>

<para>The second kind of proprietary relicensing, sometimes called the
<firstterm>freemium</firstterm> model, uses an open source version to
drive sales of a presumably fancier proprietary version.  Usually the
company offering the proprietary version is also the primary
maintainer of the open source version, in the sense of supplying most
of the developer attention (this is usually inevitable, for reasons
we'll get to in a moment).  Furthermore, although in theory the
company <emphasis>could</emphasis> offer paid support for both the
open source and proprietary versions, in practice they almost
always offer it only for the proprietary version, because then they
can charge two fees: a subscription fee for the software itself and a
fee for the support services, with only the latter having any marginal
cost to the supplier.</para>

<para>You might be wondering: how can the copyright holder offer the
software under a proprietary license if the terms of the GNU GPL
stipulate that the code must be available under less restrictive
terms?  The answer is that the GPL's terms are something the copyright
holder imposes on everyone else; the owner is therefore free to decide
<emphasis>not</emphasis> to apply those terms to itself.  In other
words, one always has the right to not sue one's self for copyright
infringement.  This right is not tied to the GPL or any other open
source license; it is simply in the nature of copyright law.</para>

<sect2 id="proprietary-relicensing-problems" >
<title>Problems with Proprietary Relicensing</title>

<para>Proprietary relicensing, of both varieties, tends to suffer from
several problems.</para>

<para>First, it discourages the normal dynamics of open source
projects, because any code contributors from outside the company are
now effectively contributing to two distinct entities: the free
version of the code and the proprietary version.  While the
contributor will be comfortable helping the free version, since that's
the norm in open source projects, she may feel less enthusiastic about
her contributions being useable in a monopolized proprietary product.
That is, unlike a straight non-copyleft license by which anyone has
the right to use the code as part of a proprietary work, here only
<emphasis>one</emphasis> party has that right, and other participants
in the project are thus being asked to contribute to an asymmetric
result.  This awkwardness is reflected and in some ways amplified by
the fact that in a proprietary relicensing scheme, the copyright owner
must collect some kind of formal agreement from each contributor (see
<xref linkend="contributor-agreements"/> earlier in this chapter), in
order to have the right to redistribute that contributor's code under
a proprietary license.  Because such an agreement needs to give the
collecting entity special, one-sided rights that a typical open source
contributor agreement doesn't include, the process of collecting
agreements starkly confronts contributors with the imbalance of the
situation, and some of them may decline to sign.  (Remember, they
don't need to sign a contribution agreement in order to distribute
their own changes along with the original code; rather, the
<emphasis>company</emphasis> needs the agreement in order to
redistribute the contributor's changes, especially under a proprietary
license.  Asymmetry cuts both ways.)</para>

<para>Historically, many companies that have started out offering a
seemingly clear proprietary relicensing option&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;use
our product under open source terms, or buy a proprietary license so
you can use it under proprietary terms&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;eventually
graduated to something closer to a "shakedown" model instead, in which
anyone who makes commercially significant use of the code ends up
being pressured to purchase a proprietary license as a way of
protecting their commercial revenue stream from harassment.  The
precise legal bases on which this pressure rests differ from case to
case, but the overall pattern of behavior has been remarkably
consistent.</para>

<para>Naturally, neither the companies initiating these shakedowns nor
the parties who are its targets, most of whom eventually capitulate,
have anything to gain from going on the record about it, so I can only
tell you that I have heard of it informally and off-the-record from
multiple developers, at different projects and different companies.
One reason I generally advise companies who are serious about open
source development to stay away from proprietary relicensing is that,
if history is a reliable guide, the temptation to undermine the open
source license will be overwhelming to the point of being impossible
to resist.</para>

<para>Finally, there is a deep motivational problem for open source
projects that operate in the shadow of a proprietarily relicensed
version: the sense that most of the salaried development attention is
going to the proprietary version anyway, and that therefore spending
time contributing to the open source version is a fool's
game&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;that one is just helping a commercial entity
free up its own developers to work on features that the open source
community will never see.  This fear is reasonable on its face, but it
also becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy: as more outside developers
stay away, the company sees less reason to invest in the open source
code base, because they're not getting a community multiplier effect
anyway.  Their disengagement in turn discourages outside developers,
and so on.</para>

<para>What seems to happen in practice is that companies that offer
proprietarily relicensed software do not get truly active development
communities with external participants.  They get occasional
small-scale bug fixes and cleanup patches from the outside, but end up
doing most of the hard work with internal resources.  Since this book
is about running free software projects, I will just say that in my
experience, proprietary relicensing schemes inevitably have a negative
effect on the level of community engagement and the level of technical
quality on the open source side.  If you conclude that for business
reasons you want to try it anyway, then I hope this section will at
least help you mitigate some of those effects.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="trademarks">
<title>Trademarks</title>

<para>Trademark law as applied to open source projects does not differ
significantly from trademark law as applied elsewhere.  This sometimes
surprises people: they think that if the code can be copied freely,
then that can't possibly be consistent with some entity controlling a
trademark on the project's name or logo.  It is consistent, however,
and below I'll explain why, furnishing some examples.</para>

<para>First, understand what trademarks are about: they are about
truth in labeling and, to some degree, endorsement.  A trademarked
name or symbol is a way for an entity&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;the entity who
owns or controls that trademark&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;to signal, in an
easily recognizeable way, that they approve of a particular product.
Often they are signaling their approval because they are the source of
the product, and purchases of that product provide a revenue stream
for them.  But that is not the only circumstance under which someone
might want to enforce accurate attribution.  For example,
certification marks are trademarked names or symbols that an entity
applies to <emphasis>someone else's</emphasis> product, in order to
signal that the product meets the certifying entity's
standards.</para>

<para>Importantly, <emphasis>trademarks do not restrict copying,
modification, or redistribution</emphasis>.  I cannot emphasize this
enough: trademark is unrelated to copyright, and does not govern the
same actions that copyright governs.  Trademark is about what you may
publicly call things, not about what you may do with those things nor
with whom you may share them.</para>

<para>One famous example of trademark enforcement in free and open
source software demonstrates these distinctions clearly.</para>

<sect2 id="mozilla-firefox-debian-iceweasel">
<title>Case study: Mozilla Firefox, the Debian Project, and Iceweasel</title>

<para>The Mozilla Foundation owns the trademarked name "Firefox",
which it uses to refer to its popular free software web browser of the
same name.  The Debian Project, which maintains a long-running and
also quite popular GNU/Linux distribution, wanted to package Firefox
for users of Debian GNU/Linux.</para>

<para>So far, so good: Debian does not need Mozilla's permission to
package Firefox, since Firefox is open source software.  However,
Debian does need Mozilla's permission to <emphasis>call</emphasis> the
packaged browser "Firefox" and to use the widely-recognized Firefox
logo (you've probably seen it: a long reddish fox curling its body and
tail around a blue globe) as the icon for the program, because those
are trademarks owned by Mozilla.</para>

<para>Normally, Mozilla would have happily given its permission.
After all, having Firefox distributed in Debian is good for Mozilla's
mission of promoting openness on the Web.  However, various technical
and policy effects of the Debian packaging process left Debian unable
to fully comply with Mozilla's trademark usage requirements, and as a
result, Mozilla informed Debian that their Firefox package could not
use the Firefox name or branding.  No doubt Mozilla did so with some
reluctance, as it is not ideal for them to have their software used
without clear attribution.  However, they could have given Debian a
trademark license and yet chose not to; presumably, this is because
Debian was doing something with the code that Mozilla did not want
accruing to their own reputation.<footnote><para>In fact, that was
indeed the reason, though we do not need to go into the details here
of exactly what changes Debian makes to the Firefox code that Mozilla
disagrees with strongly enough to want to dissociate their name from
the result.  The entire saga is recounted in more detail at <ulink
url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozilla_Corporation_software_rebranded_by_the_Debian_project"
>en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozilla_Corporation_software_rebranded_by_the_Debian_project</ulink>.
Coincidentally, I'm writing these words on a Debian GNU/Linux system,
where Iceweasel has long been my default browser&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;I
just used it to check that URL.</para></footnote></para>

<para>This decision by Mozilla did not mean that Debian had to remove
Firefox from their package system, of course.  Debian simply changed
the name to "Iceweasel" and used a different logo.  The underlying
code is still the Mozilla Firefox code, except for the minor bits
Debian had to change to integrate the different name and
logo&nbsp;&mdash;&nbsp;changes they were perfectly free to make, of
course, because of the code's open source license.</para>

</sect2>

<para>It is even consistent to license your project's logo artwork
files under a fully free license while still retaining a trademark on
the logo, as the following story of the GNOME logo and the fish
pedicure shop (I'm not making this up) illustrates.</para>

<sect2 id="gnome-fish-pedicure">
<title>Case study: The GNOME Logo and the Fish Pedicure Shop</title>

<para>The <ulink url="http://gnome.org/" >GNOME Project</ulink>, which
produces one of the major free software desktop environments, is
represented legally by the <ulink
url="http://www.gnome.org/foundation/" >GNOME Foundation</ulink>,
which owns and enforces trademarks on behalf of the project.  Their
best-known trademark is the GNOME logo: a curved, stylized foot with
four toes floating close above it.<footnote><para>You can see examples
at <ulink url="http://www.gnome.org/foundation/legal-and-trademarks/"
>gnome.org/foundation/legal-and-trademarks</ulink>.</para></footnote></para>

<para>One day, Karen Sandler, then the Executive Director of the GNOME
Foundation, heard from a GNOME contributor that a mobile fish-pedicure
van (fish pedicure is a technique in which one places one's feet in
water so that small fish can nibble away dead skin) was using a
modified version of the GNOME logo.  The central foot part of the
image had been slightly modified to look like a fish, and a fifth toe
had been added above, so that the overall logo looked even more like a
human foot but cleverly made reference to fish as well.  You can see
it, along with discussion of other trademark issues GNOME has dealt
with, in the Linux Weekly News article where this story is told in
full: <ulink url="http://lwn.net/Articles/491639/"
>lwn.net/Articles/491639</ulink>.</para>

<para>Although GNOME does actively enforce its trademarks, Sandler did
not see any infringement in this case: the fish-pedicure business is
so distant from what the GNOME Project does that there was no
possibility of confusion in the mind of the public or dilution (if
you'll pardon the expression) of the mark.  Furthermore, because the
<emphasis>copyright</emphasis> license on GNOME's images is an open
source license, the fish pedicure company was free to make their
modifications to the graphic and display the results.  There was no
trademark violation, because there was no infringement within GNOME's
domain of activity, and there was no copyright violation, because
GNOME's materials are released under free licenses.</para>

</sect2>

<para>The point of these examples is to merely show that there is no
inherent contradiction in registering and maintaining trademarks
related to open source projects.  This does not mean that a trademark
owner should do whatever they want with the marks, ignoring what other
participants in the project have to say.  Trademarks are like any
other centrally-controlled resource: if you use them in a way that
harms a significant portion of the project's community, then expect
complaints and pushback in return; if you use them in a way that
supports the goals of the project, then most participants will be glad
and will consider that use to be itself a form of contribution.</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="patents">
<title>Patents</title>

<para>Software patents have long been a lightning rod issue in
free software, because they pose the only real threat against which
the free software community cannot defend itself.  Copyright and
trademark problems can always be gotten around.  If part of your code
looks like it may infringe on someone else's copyright, you can just
rewrite that part while continuing to use the same underlying
algorithm.  If it turns out someone has a trademark on your
project's name, at the very worst you can just rename the project.
Although changing names would be a temporary inconvenience, it
wouldn't matter in the long run, since the code itself would still do
what it always did.</para>

<para>But a patent is a blanket injunction against implementing a
certain idea.  It doesn't matter who writes the code, nor even what
programming language is used.  Once someone has accused a free
software project of infringing a patent, the project must either stop
implementing that particular feature, or expose the project
<emphasis>and its users</emphasis> to expensive and
time-consuming lawsuits.  Since the instigators of such lawsuits are
usually corporations with deep pockets&mdash;that's who has the
resources and inclination to acquire patents in the first
place&mdash;most free software projects cannot afford either to defend
themselves nor to indemnify their users, and must capitulate
immediately even if they think it
highly likely that the patent would be unenforceable in court.  To
avoid getting into such a situation in the first place, free software
projects have sometimes had to code defensively, avoiding patented
algorithms in advance even when they are the best or only available
solution to a programming problem.</para>

<para>Surveys and anecdotal evidence show that not only the vast
majority of open source programmers, but a majority
of <emphasis>all</emphasis> programmers, think that software patents
should be abolished entirely.<footnote><para>See
<ulink
url="http://groups.csail.mit.edu/mac/projects/lpf/Whatsnew/survey.html"
>groups.csail.mit.edu/mac/projects/lpf/Whatsnew/survey.html</ulink>
for one such survey.</para></footnote> Open source programmers tend to feel
particularly strongly about it, and may refuse to work on projects
that are too closely associated with the collection or enforcement of
software patents.  If your organization collects software patents,
then make it clear, in a public and irrevocable way, that the patents
would never be enforced when the infringement comes from open source
code, and that the patents are 
only to be used as a defense in case some other party initiates an
infringement suit against your organization.  This is not only the
right thing to do, it's also good open source public relations.<footnote>
<para>For example, RedHat has pledged that open source projects are
safe from its patents, see
<ulink url="http://www.redhat.com/legal/patent_policy.html"
>redhat.com/legal/patent_policy.html</ulink>.</para>
</footnote></para>

<para>Unfortunately, collecting patents purely for defensive purposes
is rational.  The current patent system, at least in the United
States, is by its nature an arms race: if your competitors have
acquired a lot of patents, then your best defense is to acquire a lot
of patents yourself, so that if you're ever hit with a patent
infringement suit you can respond with a similar threat&mdash;then the
two parties usually sit down and work out a cross-licensing deal so
that neither of them has to pay anything, except to their patent 
lawyers of course.</para>

<para>The harm done to free software by software patents is more
insidious than just direct threats to code development, however.
Software patents encourage an atmosphere of secrecy among firmware
designers, who justifiably worry that by publishing details of their
interfaces they will be making it easier for competitors to find ways
to slap them with patent infringement suits.  This is not just a
theoretical danger; it has apparently been happening for a long time
in the video card industry, for example.  Many video card
manufacturers are reluctant to release the detailed programming
specifications needed to produce high-performance open source drivers
for their cards, thus making it impossible for free operating systems
to support those cards to their full potential.  Why would the
manufacturers withold these specs?  It doesn't make sense for them to
work <emphasis>against</emphasis> software support; after all,
compatibility with more operating systems can only mean more card
sales.  But it turns out that, behind the design room door, these
shops are all violating one another's patents, sometimes knowingly and
sometimes accidentally.  The patents are so unpredictable and so
potentially broad that no card manufacturer can ever be certain it's
safe, even after doing a patent search.  Thus, manufacturers dare not
publish their full interface specifications, since that would make it
much easier for competitors to figure out whether any patents are
being infringed.  (Of course, the nature of this situation is such
that you will not find a written admission from a primary source that
it is going on; I learned it through a personal communication.)</para>

<para>Modern free software licenses generally have clauses to combat,
or at least mitigate, the dangers arising from software patents.
Usually these clauses work by automatically revoking the overall open
source license for any party who makes a patent infringement claim
based on either the work as a whole<footnote><para>Remember that a
patent may cover, or "read on" in patent jargon, code that the patent
owner did not themselves write.  It is thus not necessary for a party
to have contributed code to an open source in order to claim patent
infringement <emphasis>by</emphasis> that project.</para></footnote>,
or based on the claimant's code contributions to the project.  But
though it is useful, both legally and politically, to build patent
defenses into free software licenses in this way, in the end these
protections are not be enough to dispel the chilling effect that the
threat of patent lawsuits has on free software.  Only changes in the
substance or interpretation of international patent law will do
that.</para>

<para>Recent developments, such as the 2014 decision by the
U.S. Supreme Court against the patentability of abstract ideas, in
<citetitle>Alice Corp. v. CLS Bank</citetitle> (<ulink
url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alice_Corp._v._CLS_Bank_International"
>en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alice_Corp._v._CLS_Bank_International</ulink>),
have made the future of software patents unpredictable.  But there is
so much money to be extracted via infringement claims, in particular
by <ulink url="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patent_troll" >patent
trolls</ulink> but in general by any entity with a large patent
portfolio and a lack of other revenue sources, that I am not
optimistic this fight will be over any time soon.  If you want to
learn more about the problem, there are good links at <ulink
url="http://endsoftpatents.org/" >endsoftpatents.org/</ulink> and in
the Wikipedia article <ulink
url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_patent"
>en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_patent</ulink>.  I've also written
some blog posts summarizing the arguments against software patents,
collected at <ulink url="http://www.rants.org/patent-posts/"
>www.rants.org/patent-posts</ulink>.  As of this writing it's been
about six years since the main posts there were published, but all the
reasons why software patents are a bad idea are just as true now as
they were then.</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="licensing-further-resources">
<title>Further Resources</title>

<para>This chapter has only been an introduction to free software
licensing, trademark, and patent issues.  Although I hope it contains
enough information to get you started on your own open source project,
any serious investigation of legal issues will quickly exhaust what
this book can provide.  Here are some other resources:</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para><ulink url="http://opensource.org/licenses"
                         >opensource.org/licenses</ulink></para>

            <para>The OSI license introduction page is a
            well-maintained source of information about widely used
            open source licenses, and offers answers to frequently
            asked questions.  It's a good place to start if you have a
            general idea of what open source licenses do, but now need
            more information, for example to choose a license for your
            project.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para><citetitle> Intellectual Property and Open Source:
            A Practical Guide to Protecting Code</citetitle> by Van
            Lindberg.  Published by O'Reilly Media, first edition
            July 2008, ISBN:&nbsp;978-0-596-51796-0</para>

            <para>This is a full-length book on open source licensing,
            trademarks, patents, contracting, and more.  It goes into
            much deeper detail than I could in this chapter.
            <ulink url="http://shop.oreilly.com/product/9780596517960.do"
            >shop.oreilly.com/product/9780596517960.do</ulink>
            for details.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para><citetitle>Make Your Open Source Software
            GPL-Compatible.  Or Else.</citetitle> by David
            A. Wheeler, at
            <ulink
            url="http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/gpl-compatible.html"
            >dwheeler.com/essays/gpl-compatible.html</ulink>.</para>

            <para>This is a detailed and well-written article on why
            it is important to use a GPL-compatible license even if
            you don't use the GPL itself.  The article also touches on
            many other licensing questions, and has a high density of
            excellent links.</para>
  </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->

