<chapter id="money">

<title>金钱</title>

<simplesect>

<para>本章仔细检查了如何为自由软件环境带来资金，这不仅仅是在自由软件中被支付工资的开发者的目标，也是那些需要理解开发环境社会动态性的人的目标。在接下来的小节中，假定收件人（你）是被付费的开发者，或者是管理这类开发者的人。对于二者的建议基本相同；如果不同，有意的读者可以从上下文中分清。</para>

<para>对自由软件开发来说，法人投资已经不是一个新的现象，许多开发被非正式的资助。当一个系统管理员写了一个网络分析工具来辅助她的工作，然后把它发布到网络，接受来自其他系统管理员的bug修正和特性贡献，这就产生了一种非正式的合作组织。这个合作组织的资金来自系统管理员的薪水，而它的办公室空间和网络贷款是捐助的，即使是通过其所工作的默默无闻的组织。这个组织从投资中获益，当然，尽管开始时他们不会意识到这一点。</para>

<para>现在的一些变化是这种力量已经更加正式，公司已经观察到开源软件的好处，在他们自己的开发中直接参与其中。开发者也更能预期真正重要的项目至少能获取到捐助，甚至可能是长期的赞助。而金钱的出现并没有改变自由软件开发的基本动力学，它已经极大地改变了发生事情的范围，无论是从开发者的数量来说，还是每个开发者贡献的时间。对于项目的组织，以及参与者的交互也有影响，这个问题不仅关于金钱如何花费，也关于如何测量投资回报。他们也关于管理和过程：公司层级指挥结构和自由软件项目中半集中的志愿者社区能够以相近的生产率工作？他们认可“生产率”的含义？</para>

<para>财政支持通常会受到开源开发社区的欢迎，它可以减少项目面对混乱势力的弱点，这一点经常让项目在起飞之前就被清除，因此它可以让人们更希望给软件一个机会&mdash;他们感到正在一项至少会再干6个月的工作上花费时间。毕竟，可靠性从来都是最有感染力的因素。当说IBM支持了一个开源项目时，人们就会更容易设想这个项目不会失败，而他们的因此所自发的投入反而会去实现这个会成为事实的预言。</para>

<para>然而，资金也会带来控制的想法。如果处理不好，金钱会让项目分裂为圈内和圈外开发者。如果未付费的志愿者感到设计决策或特性添加仅仅是由出价最高者决定的，他们会转而投向那些感觉更像是由知识精英管理的，不象是为了某个其他人利益进行未付酬劳动的项目。他们绝不会在邮件列表中公开抱怨，相反，随着志愿者逐渐不再努力被重视，来自外部的声音也会越来越少。小规模活动的吵闹还会继续，会以bug报告和偶尔的小修订形式出现，但是再也不会有任何大规模的代码贡献和设计讨论中来自外部的参与。人们意识到他们是如何被期望的，而且也会按照这个预期行事。</para>

<para>尽管需要小心的使用金钱，并不意味着不能购买影响力，大多数应该是可以的。技巧是不能直接购买，在一个直接的商业交易中，你使用金钱交换你所需要的。如果你需要添加一个特性，你签署一个协议，为此付款，然后它就会被实现。在开源项目，不会如此简单。你可以与某些开发者签署协议，但是他们需要欺骗自己&mdash;和你&mdash;如果他们保证你付费的工作会被开发社区接受，仅仅因为你为此付了费。这个工作只应该根据事实，以及与社区对于此软件的长远规划的符合程度来完成，你可以对这个长远规划发表意见，但你不应该是唯一的声音。</para>

<para>所以金钱不能购买影响力，但是可以购买<emphasis>导致</emphasis>影响力的东西，最明显的例子是程序员。如果雇佣了好的程序员，他们逗留了足够长的时间，以获取社区中的软件经验和信誉，那么他们就可以使用其他成员一样的方式影响项目。他们会有一个投票，或者如果人数太多，他们会有投票集团。如果他们在项目中受到尊重，他们会有超越投票的影响力。被支付的开发者没有必要掩盖他们的动机，毕竟，每个希望修改软件的人都有自己的目的。你公司的原因并不比其他人的缺乏道理，只是给与公司目标的砝码取决于代理人在项目中的状态，而不是公司的规模、经费或商业计划。</para>

</simplesect>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="types-of-involvement">
<title>参与的类型</title>

<para>开源项目被资助有许多不同的原因，这个列表中的条目并不互斥；通常一个项目的财政支持会出自多个，甚至这里所有的动机：</para>

<variablelist>

   <varlistentry><term>分担负担</term>
     <listitem>
     <para>拥有相关软件需要的不同组织经常会发现他们在重复投入，包括在内部重复编写类似的代码，以及从私有供货商购买类似的产品。当他们意识到事实真相后，这些组织会集中他们的资源，并创建（或加入）到一个开源项目，并为他们的需要调整。好处是明显的：开发的代价被分担了，而对所有人利益则增长了。尽管这个场景凭直觉应该大多数是非盈利组织所做的，但是即使对于盈利竞争者也具有战略意义。</para>
     <para>例如：<ulink url="http://www.openadapter.org/"/>和<ulink url="http://www.koha.org/"/></para>
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry><term>提高服务</term>
     <listitem>
     <para>当一个公司出售的服务依赖于某个开源程序，或因为某个开源程序而更加具有吸引力，很自然这个公司会有兴趣保证程序能够活跃的维护着。</para>
     <para>例如：<ulink
     url="http://www.collab.net/">CollabNet</ulink>对于<ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org/"/>的支持（免责声明：是我的日常工作，但是也是这个模型的完美实例）。</para>
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry><term>支持硬件销售</term>
     <listitem>
     <para>计算机和计算机组件的价值和之上的软件直接关联，硬件销售商&mdash;不仅是整机销售商，还包括外围设备和芯片制造商&mdash;都发现让高质量的自由软件运行在他们的硬件上对客户来说非常重要。</para>
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry><term>暗中削弱竞争者</term>
     <listitem>
     <para>有时候公司支持特定的开源项目作为对竞争者产品的暗中破坏，无论竞争产品本身是否开源。争夺竞争者的市场份额通常不是参与开源项目的唯一原因，但却是一个因素。</para>
     <para>例如：<ulink url="http://www.openoffice.org/"/>（不，这不是OpenOffice存在的唯一理由，但是这个软件至少部分的回应了微软的Office）。</para> 
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry><term>市场营销</term>
     <listitem>
     <para>让你的公司与流行的开源应用联系在一起，是简单而且好的品牌管理。</para>
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry><term>双重许可证</term>
     <listitem>
     <para><firstterm>双重许可证</firstterm>会为希望将软件作为自己私有软件的一部分进行销售的客户提供传统私有许可证，同时为开源范围使用的客户提供自由许可证（见<phrase output="printed"><xref linkend="legal"/>的</phrase><xref
           linkend="dual-licensing"/>）。如果开源开发者社区是活跃的，软件可以广泛领域获得调试和开发的好处，尽管公司仍然保持支持一些全职程序员的特许权流。</para> 
     <para>两个著名的例子是<ulink
           url="http://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</ulink>，相同名称数据库软件的制造商，以及<ulink
           url="http://www.sleepycat.com/">Sleepycat</ulink>，提供Berkeley数据库的发布和支持。他们都是数据库公司并不是巧合，数据库软件通常会集成到应用中，而不会直接交给用户，所以非常适合双重许可证模型。</para> 
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry><term>捐赠</term>
     <listitem>
     <para>一个广泛使用的项目有时可以获得可观的捐助，包括来自个人和组织的，只需要有一个在线的捐赠按钮，或者有时通过销售诸如咖啡杯、体恤和鼠标垫之类的品牌商品。小心一点：如果你的项目接受捐赠，在得到之前要计划好如何使用这些钱，并在项目网站中注明。在实际花费之前保留，可以让关于如何分配钱的讨论变得十分顺利；但不管怎样，如果有明显的分歧，最好把它找出来，这还是很学术的东西。</para>
     </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

</variablelist>

<para>投资者的商业模型不是它与开源社区如何联系的唯一因素，二者的历史关系也很重要：这个公司开始了这个项目，或者它联合了现有的开发力量？在两种情况下，投资者都需要赢得信誉，但是，不令人意外，在后一种情况下需要得更多。组织需要对项目的未来有清晰的目标，公司希望保持领导地位，或仅仅是成为社区的一个声音，从而能够引导而不必控制项目的方向？或者它只是希望有一些提交者，能够修复客户的bug并能够不费吹灰之力的将变更置入公共版本？</para>

<para>当你阅读后面的指导方针时要牢记这些问题，他们可以应用到自由软件项目中的此类组织参与，但每个项目都是一个人类环境，因此没有完全相同的。在某种程度上，你需要跟着感觉演奏，但是遵从这些原理会增大结果符合你想法的可能性。</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect1 id="long-term-developers">
<title>长期雇佣</title>

<para>如果你正在管理开源项目中的程序员，要尽量保持足够的时间，这样他们才能获得足够的技术和政治技能&mdash;最少也需要几年时间。当然，没有项目，无论是开源还是闭源，都可以从轮换程序员中获益。新来者搞清楚窍门需要的时间在不同环境下各不相同，但是在开源项目中的代价更加巨大，因为离开的开发者不仅带走了他们的知识，也带走了社区中的他们的地位和其中建立的人际关系。</para>

<para>开发者已经积累的信誉不能够传递，一个新来的开发者不能继承来自离开者的提交权限（可以本章后面的<xref linkend="money-vs-love"/>），如果新的开发者还没有提交权限，在获得这个权限之前它只能提交补丁。但是提交权限只是所失去的影响中最容易度量的表现，一个长期的开发者也知道邮件列表中所有以前达成和未达成一致的讨论，一个新的开发者，没有这些对话的记忆，也许会再次发起某些讨论，这会损失在组织中的信誉；其他人会奇怪为什么“他们什么也记不住？”新的开发者也对项目特性没有太多政治感觉，所以也不能象老手一样迅速和平滑的影响开发方向。</para>

<para>通过监督的预约程序来训练新手，新的开发者第一天就可以与公共开发社区直接交流，从bug修正和清理任务开始，这样他们可以逐渐熟悉代码基并在社区获取声誉，尽管此时他们还不能在设计讨论中蹦出火花。一个或多个有经验的开发者应当一直负责解惑的任务，阅读新手在开发列表中的每一篇帖子，即使是经验丰富的开发者通常不会注意的内容。这可以帮助团队在新手搁浅之前定位潜在的暗礁，私下的幕后鼓励和忠告也会非常有益，特别是当新手不习惯大量的代码平行同级评审的时候。
</para>

<para>当CollabNet雇佣新的开发者为Subversion工作时，我们会坐在一起为新人找一些打开的bug来练练手。我们会讨论解决方案的技术要点，并让至少一个有经验的开发者来评审（公开的）新开发者的补丁（也是公开的）。我们通常不会在主开发列表公开之前查看这个补丁，虽然，如果情况特殊，我们可以如此。重要的是，新开发者经历公开评审的过程中，在熟悉代码基的同时，也需要习惯于接受来自完全是陌生人的批评。但是我们会调整时机，保证我们的评审会在补丁发出之后立刻出现，这样列表中出现的第一个评审就是我们的，这可以帮助我们确立其他评审的基调。它也可以加强一个概念，也就是这个新人需要认真对待：如果其他人看到我们花时间提供详细的评审，并包含完整的解释和归档中合适的参考，他们会意识到正在进行一种培训，并意味着一个长期的投资。这可以帮助他们对那个开发者保持正面的态度，至少会花费更多的时间回答问题和评审补丁。
</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect1 id="appear-as-many">
<title>作为一些个体出现，而不是一个整体</title>

<para>你的开发者必须力求在项目的公共论坛中以一个单独的参与者出现，而不是一个单独的法人。这不是因为作为一个法人出现本身固有的一些负面含义（好的，或许有一些，但是那不是本书所讨论的），而是因为开源项目的结构配备只能处理个人实体。一个单独的贡献者可以讨论、提交补丁、获取信誉、表决等等，而一个公司不能。
</para>

<para>此外，因为分布式的行为方式，你避免了对于刺激性中央集权的敌对。让你的开发者在邮件列表中意见并不一致，鼓励他们经常评审他人的代码，尽可能的公开，就象他们是任何其他的人。阻止他们象一个集团一样表决，因为如果你这样做，其他人就会感觉到，根据一般的原理，一定有一个有组织的力量在控制他们。</para>

<para>实际的非中央集权和假装的是有区别的，在特定环境下，让你的开发者协同一致会非常有用，而且如果必要还必须在幕后进行协调。例如，当发出提议时，让许多人尽早跳出来表示认可，得出正在达成共识的印象会有助于提议的进展。其他人会感到提议的动量，如果他们反对，他们需要停止这个动量。因此，人们只会在有好的原因时才会提出反对。如果能够慎重对待反对意见，这样的精心安排也没有错。私下协议的公众表现不会因为经过预先的协调而变得不够诚实，只要他们没有用这个方法来扼杀反对意见就不会有太多害处。他们的目的仅仅是阻止那些喜欢保持个性的人提出反对意见；更多相关内容可以看<phrase output="printed"><xref linkend="communications"/>的</phrase><xref linkend="bikeshed"/>。
</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect1 id="open-motives">
<title>公开你的动机</title>

<para>尽可能公开你的组织的目标，不要因此而让商业秘密妥协。如果你希望项目能够获得某个特定的特性，例如你的客户要求这个特性，那么就应该在邮件列表中坦率的说出来。如果客户希望保持匿名，实践中这种情况很多，至少要询问一下客户是否愿意以未命名的方式使用他们的实例。开发社区对于你为什么这样做的<emphasis>原因</emphasis>了解越多，就会对你提议的事情越感到舒服。
</para>

<para>这与直觉背道而驰&mdash;得到容易甩掉难&mdash;知识就是力量，你的目标别人知道的越多，他们就越有可能超越你的控制能力。但是那种直觉在这里并没有错，通过公开支持这个特性（或是bug修正或其他任何东西），你<emphasis>已经</emphasis>亮出了底牌，现在唯一的问题是你能否成功的引导社区来分享你的目标。如果你仅仅是表明你需要它，而不能提供任何表明原因的切实例子，你的论点就会很脆弱，而人们会开始猜疑其隐藏的动机。但是如果你能够提供现实的场景来展示为什么提议的特性是重要的，就可以有力的影响辩论的效果。</para>

<para>为了看清楚这样做为什么有效，考虑另外一种选择。关于新特性或新方向的讨论会非常耗时和烦人，人们提出的论点经常会变成“我个人希望X，”或曾经流行的“根据我多年作为软件设计师的经验，对用户来说，X是极端重要的/一个无用的花边功能不会让任何人满意。”可以预料到，现实用例的缺乏不仅不会缩短或缓和这种辩论，而会扯得离实际用户体验越来越远。如果没有一些增补的力量，那么最终的结果很可能需要由口才最好、坚持最久或地位最高的人决定。</para>

<para>对于有许多客户数据的组织，你有机会提供这种增补的力量。你可以作为无法达到开发者社区的数据的信息管道，不必因为那些支持你愿望的信息事实而感到窘迫，大多数开发者个人没有他们所写软件如何使用的广泛经验。每个开发者都会按照自己的怪异方式使用软件；只要有其他的使用模式，她就会凭直觉和臆断之，而且事实上，她们知道这一点。通过提供包含可观用户数量的可信数据，你就象为整个公共开发社区提供了氧气，只要你提供的例子是正确的，他们就会狂热的欢迎它，就会推动事情往你希望的方向发展。
</para>

<para>关键是提供正确的例子。不要因为你要应付大量需要某特性（或以为他们需要）的用户，就坚决要求你的特性，也就是你的解决方案必须实现。相反，你必须将你最初的帖子关注于问题，而不是一个特定的解决方案。详细描述你的客户遇到问题的细节，尽可能提供你已经完成的分析，以及你能想到的可行性方案。当人们开始考虑不同方案的效果时，你可以继续通过提供数据来支持或反对她们的意见。你在心里可以有一个特定的解决方案，但是不要在开始单独提出来以期望获得特殊的考虑。这不是欺骗，这只是标准的“诚实代理人”的行为。毕竟，你的真正目标是解决问题；一个解决方案只是达到目标的一种方法。如果你选中的解决方案确实更好，其他开发者最终会识别出来&mdash;她们会出于自愿的跟进，肯定比你通过威逼她们实现更好。（当然，也有可能她们找到了更好的方案。）
</para>

<para>这不是说你不能说出你看好某个方案，但是你必须耐心的查看你所做的分析反复成为公共开发列表的中心。不要在列表中说“是的，我们试过这种方式，但是因为原因A、B和C，它是行不通的。当你彻底了解它后，解决它的唯一办法是...”问题不是它听起来很傲慢，而是让人觉得你对此问题<emphasis>已经</emphasis>研究了许多未知的（但是，人们会假设有很多）分析资源，只是一切都在门后面。它让人觉投入的精力白费了，或许已经做出了决定，而公众都不是有利害关系的人，这是招致怨恨的好方法。
</para>

<para>自然，<emphasis>你</emphasis>知道你自己在某个问题上所投入的力量，而这些知识从某种意义上来说是一种劣势。它让你的开发者处于和邮件列表中的其他人些许不同的心理空间，减弱了开发者从那些普通人的视角看待这个问题的能力，这些普通人没有像开发者那样考虑过这个问题。你越早能够让所有人用与你相同的术语考虑问题，这种差距就会越小。这种逻辑不仅适于个人技术情形，而且适用于更广泛的让你的目标尽可能清晰的授权。未知总比已知的更不稳定，如果人们理解了为什么你希望你所希望的，即使他们不认可，也会感到舒服的与你交谈。如果他们不能指出何事让他们愤怒，他们会假定最坏的情况，至少有时候。
</para>

<para>你不能宣传所有的事情，当然，人们也不会期望你如此。所有的组织都有秘密；或许会因为利益，但是没有利益也会如此。如果你必须发起这样一个过程，而无法揭示任何原因，那就提供你在这种不利条件下最好的论点，并接受你将不会在讨论中获得你期望影响力的后果。这是让你不必为开发社区支付工资的一个折中手段。</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect1 id="money-vs-love">
<title>钱不能让你可爱</title>

<para>如果你的项目有付费的开发者，一定要尽早设置钱可以购买什么东西的指导方针。这并不意味着你需要每天在邮件列表中说明两次来重申你的高尚和不腐的本性，你只需要在恰当的时机放松由钱导致的紧张。你不需要从一开始就假设存在这种紧张；你只需要说明有这种可能性。</para>

<para>一个完美的例子就是Subversion项目，<ulink
url="http://www.collab.net/">CollabNet</ulink>在2000年开始了Subversion，从一开始它便是项目主要的投资者，为多个开发者提供薪水（免责声明：包括我），项目开始后不久，我们雇佣了另一个开发者Mike Pilato，参与开发工作。此时，编码工作已经开始，尽管Subversion还处于早期阶段，但已经有了一个开发者社区和许多基本的规则。</para>

<para>Mike的到来突现了一个有趣的问题，Subversion已经有了开发者如何获得提交权的政策，首先，他需要在开发邮件列表中提交一些补丁，当有了足够的补丁后，其他提交者看到新贡献者知道自己所做的事情，某人就会提议他直接提交（这个提议是私下的，就像<xref
linkend="committers"/>所描述的）。如果提交者们同意，其中的某人就会邮件通知新的开发者，并为他设置直接提交访问项目版本库的权限。</para>

<para>CollabNet是专门为Subversion项目雇佣了Mike，他们已经对他足够了解，对于他的编码技巧和在此项目所作的准备毫无疑问。此外，志愿者开发者已经与CollabNet雇员有了非常好的关系，看起来如果我们直接在雇用Mike当天就赋予他权限也不会有什么反对意见。但是我们知道我们正在设置一个先例，如果我们按条例给Mike提交权利，我们会说CollabNet有权无视项目的指导方针，因为它是主要的投资者。这种行为的害处不必立刻显现出来，它会导致非付费开发者逐渐感到被剥夺了投票权。其他人自己赢得他们的提交权利&mdash;而CollabNet只需要花钱买。</para>

<para>所以Mike赞成象其他志愿开发者一样，在没有提交权限的情况下开始了在CollabNet的雇佣工作。他在公共列表中发布补丁，在其中可能会受到，实际上也确实受到了所有人的评审。我们在列表中也说过我们是故意这样做的，经过Mike数周的扎实活动，某人（我不记得是否是CollabNet开发者）提议给他提交权限，而他被接受了，当然，我们知道他会被接受。
</para>

<!--

The relevant dates for Mike Pilato are:

   http://subversion.tigris.org/servlets/ReadMsg?list=dev&msgNo=2943

   From: "C. Michael Pilato" <cmpilato@collab.net>
   To: "dev@subversion.tigris.org" <dev@subversion.tigris.org>
   Subject: Introducing...me.
   Message-ID: <Pine.LNX.4.21.0101121604240.1653-100000@pascal>
   Date: Fri, 12 Jan 2001 16:04:44 -0800 (PST)

followed by:

   2001-01-30 15:35  C. Michael Pilato <cmpilato@collab.net>

        * configure.in (1.49), subversion/clients/win32/svn_com/svn_com.dsp
        (1.3), subversion/include/svn_path.h (1.26),
        subversion/libsvn_subr/path.c (1.29):

        Fixes path inconsistencies on Windows.  More generally, actually
        makes use of the "style" parameter passed to the path library
        functions to choose the right path delimeter ('/' or '\' at this
        time).  
        
        * config.hw (SVN_PATH_LOCAL_SEPARATOR): 
          Added this #define for Windows usage.  
        
        * configure.in (SVN_PATH_LOCAL_SEPARATOR): 
          Added this #define for those systems that use autoconf.  
        
        * svn_com.dsp: 
          Added the subversion root directory to the include path so
          config.h can be found by the inclusion of the path headers.  
        
        * svn_path.h (SVN_PATH_REPOS_SEPARATOR, SVN_PATH_URL_SEPARATOR): 
          Added url separator define, and changed naming of repos to be an
          exported symbol.  
        
        * path.c (get_separator_from_style): 
          Added new function for choosing an appropriate path separator,
          given a subversion path style.  Also changed a variety of
          functions in this module to make use of this new function instead of
          simply using SVN_PATH_REPOS_SEPARATOR.  

   2001-01-30 12:23   Karl Fogel <kfogel@collab.net>

        * AUTHORS (1.9):

        Added Mark Murphy, Bill Tutt, C. Michael Pilato.  
-->

<para>那种类型的一致性会让你确信钱不可以买到一切，这种确信是技术讨论中珍贵的流通货币：可以免于以后让某人的动机被怀疑。在辩论最激烈时，人们有时会寻找非技术的方式来赢得战斗。项目的主要投资者，因为涉足较深并且显然会对项目采取的方向十分关注，会展示出比大多数人更广的目标，通过从一开始就一丝不苟的遵守项目方针，投资者就可以获得和所有人一样的影响力。</para>

<para>（Danese Cooper的blog <ulink url="http://blogs.sun.com/roller/page/DaneseCooper/20040916"/>有关于提交权限的类似故事，Cooper是Sun
Microsystem的“开源Diva”&mdash;我相信这是她的官方头衔&mdash;在她的blog中，她描述了Tomcat开发社区让Sun在控制提交权限时对Sun的人员和非Sun的人员一视同仁。）</para>

<para>创始人对所有人使用相同规则的需要意味着慈善独裁统治模型（见<phrase output="printed"><xref linkend="social-infrastructure"/>的</phrase><xref linkend="benevolent-dictator"/>）再投资面前有一点难于实施，特别是独裁者为主要的投资方工作的情况。因为独裁有一些规则，投资者很难证明遵守了社区标准，即使事实如此。这确实不是不可能；只是需要项目领导者既能够从投资方也能够从外围开发者的视角看待事物，并依此行动。即使那样，也最好能在后口袋有一个非独裁管理的提议，准备好在社区的不满扩散时掏出来。</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect1 id="contracting">
<title>契约</title>

<para>在自由软件项目中的契约需要小心处理，理想状况下，你希望一个承包者的工作被社区接受并打包进入公共发布版本。在理论上，谁是承包者并不重要，只要他的作品足够好并满足项目的指导方针。理论和实践一般也是一致的：一个通过贡献好的补丁展示自己的完全陌生人通常能将代码置入软件当中。问题是，一个完全的陌生人很难为非琐碎的改进或新的特性贡献好的补丁；一个人必须首先和项目的其他人进行讨论。讨论的时间不能精确预测，如果承包者根据小时付费，你最终可能会付出超过预期的费用；如果他是通过总费用支付，那么他最终会做出超过承受能力的工作。</para>

<para>这里有两种方式。较好的一个方法是根据以前的经验，对讨论过程的长度做出一个有根据的推测，并要考虑到出错的延误，并根据这些信息完成契约。这也有利于尽可能的将问题分离为许多小的独立的区块，增加每个区块的可预测能力。另一个方法是为每一个发布的补丁单独契约，然后将补丁的被接受当作公共项目一个独立的事件。这样编写契约就可以很容易，但是只要你依赖这个软件，或至少在这个补丁或对应功能进入主线的这些时间里，你必须承担维护单个补丁的责任。当然，即使是你中意的方法，契约本身不能要求代码必须可以接受补丁，因为那会包含出售一些不能销售的东西。（如果项目的余下部分以外的不能决定支持这个特性？）然而，契约可以要求<foreignphrase>真诚地</foreignphrase>投入以获得社区接受的机会，也就是社区接受的话提交到版本库。例如，如果项目编写了代码变更的标准，契约可以参考这个标准并指明作品必须达标。在实践中，这通常会超过了每个人的期望。</para>

<para>The best tactic for successful contracting is to hire one of the
project's developers&mdash;preferably a committer&mdash;as the
contractor.  This may seem like a form of purchasing influence, and,
well, it is.  But it's not as corrupt as it might seem.  A developer's
influence in the project is due mainly to the quality of his code and
to his interactions with other developers.  The fact that he has a
contract to get certain things done doesn't raise his status in any
way, and doesn't lower it either, though it may make people scrutinize
him more carefully.  Most developers would not risk their long-term
position in the project by backing an inappropriate or widely disliked
new feature.  In fact, part of what you get, or should get, when you
hire such a contractor is advice about what sorts of changes are
likely to be accepted by the community.  You also get a slight shift
in the project's priorities.  Because prioritization is just a matter
of who has time to work on what, when you pay for someone's time, you
cause their work to move up in the priority queue a bit.  This is a
well-understood fact of life among experienced open source developers,
and at least some of them will devote attention to the contractor's
work simply because it looks like it's going to <emphasis>get
done</emphasis>, so they want to help it get done right.  Perhaps they
won't write any of the code, but they'll still discuss the design and
review the code, both of which can be very useful.  For all these
reasons, the contractor is best drawn from the ranks of those already
involved with the project.</para>

<para>This immediately raises two questions: Should contracts ever be
private?  And when they're not, should you worry about creating
tensions in the community by the fact that you've contracted with some
developers and not others?</para>

<para>It's best to be open about contracts, when you can.  Otherwise,
the contractor's behavior may seem strange to others in the
community&mdash;perhaps he's suddenly giving inexplicably high
priority to features he's never shown interest in in the past.  When
people ask him why he wants them now, how can he answer convincingly
if he can't talk about the fact that he's been contracted to write
them?</para>

<para>At the same time, neither you nor the contractor should act as
though others should treat your arrangement as a big deal.  Too often
I've seen contractors waltz onto a development list with the attitude
that their posts should be taken more seriously simply because they're
being paid.  That kind of attitude signals to the rest of the project
that the contractor regards the fact of the contract&mdash;as opposed
to the code <emphasis>resulting</emphasis> from the contract&mdash;to
be the important thing.  But from the other developers' point of view,
only the code matters.  At all times, the focus of attention should be
kept on technical issues, not on the details of who is paying whom.
For example, one of the developers in the Subversion community handles
contracting in a particularly graceful way.  While discussing his code
changes in IRC, he'll mention as an aside (often in a private remark,
an IRC <firstterm>privmsg</firstterm>, to one of the other committers)
that he's being paid for his work on this particular bug or feature.
But he also consistently gives the impression that he'd want to be
working on that change anyway, and that he's happy the money is making
it possible for him to do that.  He may or may not reveal his
customer's identity, but in any case he doesn't dwell on the contract.
His remarks about it are just an ornament to an otherwise technical
discussion about how to get something done.</para>

<para>That example shows another reason why it's good to be open about
contracts.  There may be multiple organizations sponsoring contracts
on a given open source project, and if each knows what the others are
trying to do, they may be able to pool their resources.  In the above
case, the project's largest funder (CollabNet) is not involved in any
way with these piecework contracts, but knowing that someone else is
sponsoring certain bug fixes allows CollabNet to redirect its
resources to other bugs, resulting in greater efficiency for the
project as a whole.</para>

<para>Will other developers resent that some are paid for working on
the project?  In general, no, particularly when those who are paid are
established, well-respected members of the community anyway.  No one
expects contract work to be distributed equally among all the
committers.  People understand the importance of long-term
relationships: the uncertainties involved in contracting are such that
once you find someone you can work reliably with, you would be
reluctant to switch to a different person just for the sake of
evenhandedness.  Think of it this way: the first time you hire, there
will be no complaints, because clearly you had to pick
<emphasis>someone</emphasis>&mdash;it's not your fault you can't hire
everyone.  Later, when you hire the same person a second time, that's
just common sense: you already know him, the last time was
successful, so why take unnecessary risks?  Thus, it's perfectly
natural to have one or two go-to people in the community, instead of
spreading the work around evenly.</para>

<sect2 id="community-review-acceptance">
<title>Review and Acceptance of Changes</title>

<para>The community is still important to the success of contract
work.  Their involvement in the design and review process for sizeable
changes cannot be an afterthought.  It must be considered part of the
work, and fully embraced by the contractor.  Don't think of community
scrutiny as an obstacle to be overcome&mdash;think of it as a free
design board and QA department.  It is a benefit to be aggressively
pursued, not merely endured.</para>

<sect3 id="cvs-pserver">
<title>Case study: the CVS password-authentication protocol</title>

<para>In 1995, I was one half of a partnership that provided support
and enhancements for CVS (the Concurrent Versions System; see <ulink
url="http://www.cvshome.org/"/>).  My partner Jim and I were,
informally, the maintainers of CVS by that point.  But we'd never
thought carefully about how we ought to relate to the existing, mostly
volunteer CVS development community.  We just assumed that they'd send
in patches, and we'd apply them, and that was pretty much how it
worked.</para>

<para>Back then, networked CVS could be done only over a remote login
program such as <literal>rsh</literal>.  Using the same password for
CVS access as for login access was an obvious security risk, and many
organizations were put off by it.  A major investment bank hired us to
add a new authentication mechanism, so they could safely use networked
CVS with their remote offices.</para>

<para>Jim and I took the contract and sat down to design the new
authentication system.  What we came up with was pretty simple (the
United States had export controls on cryptographic code at the time,
so the customer understood that we couldn't implement strong
authentication), but as we were not experienced in designing such
protocols, we still made a few gaffes that would have been obvious to
an expert.  These mistakes would easily have been caught had we taken
the time to write up a proposal and run it by the other developers for
review.  But we never did so, because it didn't occur to us to think
of the development list as a resource to be used.  We knew that people
were probably going to accept whatever we committed, and&mdash;because
we didn't know what we didn't know&mdash;we didn't bother to do the
work in a visible way, e.g., posting patches frequently, making small,
easily digestible commits to a special branch, etc.  The resulting
authentication protocol was not very good, and of course, once it
became established, it was difficult to improve, because of
compatibility concerns.</para>

<para>The root of the problem was not lack of experience; we could
easily have learned what we needed to know.  The problem was our
attitude toward the volunteer development community.  We regarded
acceptance of the changes as a hurdle to leap, rather than as a
process by which the quality of the changes could be improved.  Since
we were confident that almost anything we did would be accepted (as it
was), we made little effort to get others involved.</para>

</sect3>

<para>Obviously, when you're choosing a contractor, you want someone
with the right technical skills and experience for the job.  But it's
also important to choose someone with a track record of constructive
interaction with the other developers in the community.  That way
you're getting more than just a single person; you're getting an agent
who will be able to draw on a network of expertise to make sure the
work is done in a robust and maintainable way.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- 
<para><remark>Contractors as the route to expansion of services and
support.  Businesses who are deeply involved in the development of an
open source program, and who also sell support and customization
services, are in a resource bind.  The more their business grows, the
more strain they are under, trying to stay involved in the open
source side while using those same developers for in-house work.
Contracting with volunteer developers is one way out of this bind,
but it has to managed carefully (and openly, as far as
possible).</remark></para>
-->

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="funding-non-programming">
<title>Funding Non-Programming Activities</title>

<para>Programming is only part of the work that goes on in an open
source project.  From the point of view of the project's volunteers,
it's the most visible and glamorous part.  This unfortunately means
that other activities, such as documentation, formal testing, etc., can
sometimes be neglected, at least compared to the amount of attention
they often receive in proprietary software.  Corporate organizations
are sometimes able to make up for this, by devoting some of their
internal software development infrastructure to open source
projects.</para>

<para>The key to doing this successfully is to translate between the
company's internal processes and those of the public development
community.  Such translation is not effortless: often the two are not
a close match, and the differences can only be bridged via human
intervention.  For example, the company may use a different bug
tracker than the public project.  Even if they use the same tracking
software, the data stored in it will be very different, because the
bug-tracking needs of a company are very different from those of a
free software community.  A piece of information that starts in one
tracker may need to be reflected in the other, with confidential
portions removed or, in the other direction, added.</para>

<para>The sections that follow are about how to build and maintain
such bridges.  The end result should be that the open source project
runs more smoothly, the community recognizes the company's investment
of resources, and yet does not feel that the company is
inappropriately steering things toward its own goals.</para>

<!-- integrate the internal into the development community.  If you
     have salaried developers, for example, use them as a liason.
     Don't just have the marketing department send out papers, get
     them fact-checked and also *politics*-checked first.  Make sure
     the QA people know how to use the project's public bug tracker,
     and make sure the community sees that these resources are being
     devoted to the project. -->

<!-- ======================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="subsidize-qa">
<title>Quality Assurance (i.e., Professional Testing)</title>

<para>In proprietary software development, it is normal to have teams
of people dedicated solely to quality assurance: bug hunting,
performance and scalability testing, interface and documentation
checking, etc.  As a rule, these activities are not pursued as
vigorously by the volunteer community on a free software project.
This is partly because it's hard to get volunteer labor for
unglamorous work like testing, partly because people tend to assume
that having a large user community gives the project good testing
coverage, and, in the case of performance and scalability testing,
partly because volunteers often don't have access to the necessary
hardware resources anyway.</para>

<para>The assumption that having many users is equivalent to having
many testers is not entirely baseless.  Certainly there's little point
assigning testers for basic functionality in common environments: bugs
there will quickly be found by users in the natural course of things.
But because users are just trying to get work done, they do not
consciously set out to explore uncharted edge cases in the program's
functionality, and are likely to leave certain classes of bugs
unfound.  Furthermore, when they discover a bug with an easy
workaround, they often silently implement the workaround without
bothering to report the bug.  Most insidiously, the usage patterns of
your customers (the people who drive <emphasis>your</emphasis>
interest in the software) may differ in statistically significant ways
from the usage patterns of the Average User In The Street.</para>

<para>A professional testing team can uncover these sorts of bugs, and
can do so as easily with free software as with proprietary software.
The challenge is to convey the testing team's results back to the
public in a useful form.  In-house testing departments usually have
their own way of reporting test results, involving company-specific
jargon, or specialized knowledge about particular customers and their
data sets.  Such reports would be inappropriate for the public bug
tracker, both because of their form and because of confidentiality
concerns.  Even if your company's internal bug tracking software
were the same as that used by the public project, management might
need to make company-specific comments and metadata changes to the
issues (for example, to raise an issue's internal priority, or
schedule its resolution for a particular customer).  Usually such
notes are confidential&mdash;sometimes they're not even shown to the
customer.  But even when they're not confidential, they're of no
concern to the public project, and therefore the public should not be
distracted with them.</para>

<para>Yet the core bug report itself <emphasis>is</emphasis> important
to the public.  In fact, a bug report from your testing department is
in some ways more valuable than one received from users at large,
since the testing department probes for things that other users won't.
Given that you're unlikely to get that particular bug report from any
other source, you definitely want to preserve it and make it
available to the public project.</para>

<para>To do this, either the QA department can file issues directly in
the public issue tracker, if they're comfortable with that, or an
intermediary (usually one of the developers) can "translate" the
testing department's internal reports into new issues in the public
tracker.  Translation simply means describing the bug in a way that
makes no reference to customer-specific information (the reproduction
recipe may use customer data, assuming the customer approves it, of
course).</para>

<para>It is somewhat preferable to have the QA department filing
issues in the public tracker directly.  That gives the public a more
direct appreciation of your company's involvement with the project:
useful bug reports add to your organization's credibility just as any
technical contribution would.  It also gives developers a direct line
of communication to the testing team.  For example, if the internal QA
team is monitoring the public issue tracker, a developer can commit a
fix for a scalability bug (which the developer may not have the
resources to test herself), and then add a note to the issue asking
the QA team to see if the fix had the desired effect.  Expect a bit of
resistance from some of the developers; programmers have a tendency to
regard QA as, at best, a necessary evil.  The QA team can easily
overcome this by finding significant bugs and filing comprehensible
reports; on the other hand, if their reports are not at least as good
as those coming from the regular user community, then there's no point
having them interact directly with the development team.</para>

<para>Either way, once a public issue exists, the original internal
issue should simply reference the public issue for technical content.
Management and paid developers may continue to annotate the internal
issue with company-specific comments as necessary, but use the public
issue for information that should be available to everyone.</para>

<para>You should go into this process expecting extra overhead.
Maintaining two issues for one bug is, naturally, more work than
maintaining one issue.  The benefit is that many more coders will see
the report and be able to contribute to a solution.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="subsidize-legal">
<title>Legal Advice and Protection</title>

<para>Corporations, for-profit or nonprofit, are almost the only
entities that ever pay attention to complex legal issues in free
software.  Individual developers often understand the nuances of
various open source licenses, but they generally do not have the time
or resources to follow copyright, trademark, and patent law in detail.
If your company has a legal department, it can help a project by
vetting the copyright status of the code, and helping developers
understand possible patent and trademark issues.  The exact forms this
help could take are discussed in <xref linkend="legal"/>.  The
main thing is to make sure that communications between the legal
department and the development community, if they happen at all,
happen with a mutual appreciation of the very different universes the
parties are coming from.  On occasion, these two groups talk past each
other, each side assuming domain-specific knowledge that the other
does not have.  A good strategy is to have a liaison (usually a
developer, or else a lawyer with technical expertise) stand in the
middle and translate for as long as needed.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="subsidize-documentation-usability">
<title>Documentation and Usability</title>

<para>Documentation and usability are both famous weak spots in open
source projects, although I think, at least in the case of
documentation, that the difference between free and proprietary
software is frequently exaggerated.  Nevertheless, it is empirically
true that much open source software lacks first-class documentation
and usability research.</para>

<para>If your organization wants to help fill these gaps for a
project, probably the best thing it can do is hire people who
are <emphasis>not</emphasis> regular developers on the project, but
who will be able to interact productively with the developers.
Not hiring regular developers is good for two reasons: one, that way
you don't take development time away from the project; two, those
closest to the software are usually the wrong people to write
documentation or investigate usability anyway, because they have
trouble seeing the software from an outsider's point of view.</para>

<para>However, it will still be necessary for whoever works on these
problems to communicate with the developers.  Find people who are
technical enough to talk to the coding team, but not so expert in the
software that they can't empathize with regular users anymore.</para>

<para>A medium-level user is probably the right person to write good
documentation.  In fact, after the first edition of this book was
published, I received the following email from an open source
developer named Dirk Reiners:</para>

<screen>
One comment on Money::Documentation and Usability: when we had some 
money to spend and decided that a beginner's tutorial was the most 
critical piece that we needed we hired a medium-level user to write it. 
He had gone through the induction to the system recently enough to 
remember the problems, but he had gotten past them so he knew how to 
describe them. That allowed him to write something that needed only 
minor fixes by the core developers for the things that he hadn't gotten 
right, but still covering the 'obvious' stuff devs would have missed.

His case was even better, as it had been his job to introduce a bunch of 
other people (students) to the system, so he combined the experience of 
many people, which is something that was just a lucky occurrence and is 
probably hard to get in most cases.
</screen>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection =========================== -->
<sect2 id="subsidize-hosting">
<title>Providing Hosting/Bandwidth</title>

<para>For a project that's not using one of the free canned hosting
sites (see
<xref linkend="canned-hosting"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="technical-infrastructure"/></phrase>), providing a
server and network connection&mdash;and most importantly, system
administration help&mdash;can be of significant assistance.  Even if
this is all your organization does for the project, it can be a
moderately effective way to obtain good public relations karma, though
it will not bring any influence over the direction of the
project.</para>

<para>You can probably expect a banner ad or an acknowledgment on the
project's home page, thanking your company for providing hosting.  If
you set up the hosting so that the project's web address is under your
company's domain name, then you will get some additional association
just through the URL.  This will cause most users to think of the
software as having <emphasis>something</emphasis> to do with your
company, even if you don't contribute to development at all.  The
problem is, the developers are aware of this associative tendency too,
and may not be very comfortable with having the project in your domain
unless you're contributing more resources than just bandwidth.  After
all, there are a lot of places to host these days.  The community may
eventually feel that the implied misallocation of credit is not worth
the convenience brought by hosting, and take the project elsewhere.
So if you want to provide hosting, do so&mdash;but either plan to get
even more involved soon, or be circumspect about how much involvement
you claim.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="marketing">
<title>Marketing</title>

<para>Although most open source developers would probably hate to
admit it, marketing works.  A good marketing campaign
<emphasis>can</emphasis> create buzz around an open source product,
even to the point where hardheaded coders find themselves having
vaguely positive thoughts about the software for reasons they can't
quite put their finger on.  It is not my place here to dissect the
arms-race dynamics of marketing in general.  Any corporation involved
in free software will eventually find itself considering how to market
themselves, the software, or their relationship to the
software.  The advice below is about how to avoid common pitfalls in
such an effort; see also
<xref linkend="publicity"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="communications"/></phrase>.</para>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="goldfish-bowl">
<title>Remember That You Are Being Watched</title>

<para>For the sake of keeping the volunteer developer community on
your side, it is <emphasis>very</emphasis> important not to say
anything that isn't demonstrably true.  Audit all claims carefully
before making them, and give the public the means to check your claims
on their own.  Independent fact checking is a major part of open
source, and it applies to more than just the code.</para>

<para>Naturally no one would advise companies to make unverifiable
claims anyway.  But with open source activities, there is an unusually
high quantity of people with the expertise to verify
claims&mdash;people who are also likely to have high-bandwidth
Internet access and the right social contacts to publicize their
findings in a damaging way, should they choose to.  When Global
Megacorp Chemical Industries pollutes a stream, that's verifiable, but
only by trained scientists, who can then be refuted by Global
Megacorp's scientists, leaving the public scratching their heads and
wondering what to think.  On the other hand, your behavior in the open
source world is not only visible and recorded; it is also easy for many
people to check it independently, come to their own conclusions, and
spread those conclusions by word of mouth.  These communications
networks are already in place; they are the essence of how open source
operates, and they can be used to transmit any sort of information.
Refutation is usually difficult, if not impossible, especially when
what people are saying is true.</para>

<para>For example, it's okay to refer to your organization as having
"founded project X" if you really did.  But don't refer to yourself as
the "makers of X" if most of the code was written by outsiders.
Conversely, don't claim to have a deeply involved volunteer developer
community if anyone can look at your repository and see that there are
few or no code changes coming from outside your organization.</para>

<para>Not too long ago, I saw an announcement by a very well-known
computer company, stating that they were releasing an important
software package under an open source license.  When the initial
announcement came out, I took a look at their now-public version
control repository and saw that it contained only three revisions.  In
other words, they had done an initial import of the source code, but
hardly anything had happened since then.  That in itself was not
worrying&mdash;they'd just made the announcement, after all.  There
was no reason to expect a lot of development activity right
away.</para>

<para>Some time later, they made another announcement.  Here is what
it said, with the name and release number replaced by pseudonyms:</para>

  <blockquote>
    <para><emphasis>We are pleased to announce that following
    rigorous testing by the Singer Community, Singer&nbsp;5 for Linux
    and Windows are now ready for production use.</emphasis></para>
  </blockquote>

<para>Curious to know what the community had uncovered in "rigorous
testing," I went back to the repository to look at its recent change
history.  The project was still on revision 3.  Apparently, they
hadn't found a <emphasis>single</emphasis> bug worth fixing before the
release!  Thinking that the results of the community testing must have
been recorded elsewhere, I next examined the bug tracker.  There were
exactly six open issues, four of which had been open for several months
already.</para>

<para>This beggars belief, of course.  When testers pound on a large
and complex piece of software for any length of time, they will find
bugs.  Even if the fixes for those bugs don't make it into the
upcoming release, one would still expect some version control activity
as a result of the testing process, or at least some new issues.  Yet
to all appearances, nothing had happened between the announcement of
the open source license and the first open source release.</para>

<para>The point is not that the company was lying about the community
testing.  I have no idea if they were or not.  But they were oblivious
to how much it <emphasis>looked</emphasis> like they were lying.
Since neither the version control repository nor the issue tracker
gave any indication that the alleged rigorous testing had occurred,
the company should either not have made the claim in the first place,
or provided a clear link to some tangible result of that testing ("We
found 278 bugs; click here for details").  The latter would have
allowed anyone to get a handle on the level of community activity very
quickly.  As it was, it only took me a few minutes to determine that
whatever this community testing was, it had not left traces in any of
the usual places.  That's not a lot of effort, and I'm sure I'm not
the only one who took the trouble.</para>

<para>Transparency and verifiability are also an important part of
accurate crediting, of course.  See
<xref linkend="credit"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="managing-volunteers"/></phrase> for more on this.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="competing-products">
<title>Don't Bash Competing Open Source Products</title>

<para>Refrain from giving negative opinions about competing open
source software.  It's perfectly okay to give negative
<emphasis>facts</emphasis>&mdash;that is, easily confirmable
assertions of the sort often seen in good comparison charts.  But
negative characterizations of a less rigorous nature are best avoided,
for two reasons.  First, they are liable to start flame wars that
detract from productive discussion.  Second, and more importantly,
some of the volunteer developers in <emphasis>your</emphasis> project
may turn out to work on the competing project as well.  This is more
likely than it at first might seem: the projects are already in the
same domain (that's why they're in competition), and developers with
expertise in that domain may make contributions wherever their
expertise is applicable.  Even when there is no direct developer
overlap, it is likely that developers on your project are at least
acquainted with developers on related projects.  Their ability to
maintain constructive personal ties could be hampered by
overly negative marketing messages.</para>

<para>Bashing competing closed-source products seems to be more widely
accepted in the open source world, especially when those products are
made by Microsoft.  Personally, I deplore this tendency (though again,
there's nothing wrong with straightforward factual comparisons), not
merely because it's rude, but also because it's dangerous for a
project to start believing its own hype and thereby ignore the ways in
which the competition may actually be superior.  In general, watch out
for the effect that marketing statements can have on your own
development community.  People may be so excited at being backed by
marketing dollars that they lose objectivity about their software's
true strengths and weaknesses.  It is normal, and even expected, for a
company's developers to exhibit a certain detachment toward marketing
statements, even in public forums.  Clearly, they should not come out
and contradict the marketing message directly (unless it's actually
wrong, though one hopes that sort of thing would have been caught
earlier).  But they may poke fun at it from time to time, as a way of
bringing the rest of the development community back down to
earth.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
