<chapter id="communications">

<title>Communications</title>

<simplesect>

<para>The ability to write clearly is perhaps the most important skill
one can have in an open source environment.  In the long run it
matters more than programming talent.  A great programmer with lousy
communications skills can get only one thing done at a time, and even
then may have trouble convincing others to pay attention.  But a lousy
programmer with good communications skills can coordinate and persuade
many people to do many different things, and thereby have a
significant effect on a project's direction and momentum.</para>

<para>There does not seem to be much correlation, in either direction,
between the ability to write good code and the ability to communicate
with one's fellow human beings.  There is some correlation between
programming well and describing technical issues well, but describing
technical issues is only a tiny part of the communications in a
project.  Much more important is the ability to empathize with one's
audience, to see one's own posts and comments as others see them, and
to cause others to see their own posts with similar objectivity.
Equally important is noticing when a given medium or communications
method is no longer working well, perhaps because it doesn't scale as
the number of users increases, and taking the time to do something
about it.</para>

<para>All of which is obvious in theory&mdash;what makes it hard in
practice is that free software development environments are
bewilderingly diverse both in audiences and in communications
mechanisms.  Should a given thought be expressed in a post to the
mailing list, as an annotation in the bug tracker, or as a comment
in the code?  When answering a question in a public forum, how much
knowledge can you assume on the part of the reader, given that "the
reader" is not only the one who asked the question in the first place,
but all those who might see your response?  How can the developers
stay in constructive contact with the users, without getting swamped
by feature requests, spurious bug reports, and general chatter?  How
do you tell when a medium has reached the limits of its capacity, and
what do you do about it?</para>

<para>Solutions to these problems are usually partial, because any
particular solution is eventually made obsolete by project growth or
changes in project structure.  They are also often <foreignphrase>ad
hoc</foreignphrase>, because they're improvised responses to dynamic
situations.  All participants need to be aware of when and how
communications can become bogged down, and be involved in
solutions.  Helping people do this is a big part of managing an open
source project.  The sections that follow discuss both how to conduct
your own communications, and how to make maintenance of communications
mechanisms a priority for everyone in the project.<footnote><para>There
has been some interesting academic research on this topic; for example,
see <citetitle>Group Awareness in Distributed Software
Development</citetitle> by Gutwin, Penner, and Schneider.  This paper
was online for a while, then unavailable, then online again at <ulink
url="http://www.st.cs.uni-sb.de/edu/empirical-se/2006/PDFs/gutwin04.pdf"/>.
So try there first, but be prepared to use a search engine if it moves
again.</para></footnote></para>

</simplesect>


<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="you-are-what-you-write">
<title>You Are What You Write</title>

<para>Consider this: the only thing anyone knows about you on the
Internet comes from what you write, or what others write about you.
You may be brilliant, perceptive, and charismatic in person&mdash;but
if your emails are rambling and unstructured, people will assume
that's the real you.  Or perhaps you really are rambling and
unstructured in person, but no one need ever know it, if your posts
are lucid and informative.</para>

<para>Devoting some care to your writing will pay off hugely.
Long-time free software hacker Jim Blandy tells the following
story:</para>

<blockquote>
  <para>Back in 1993, I was working for the Free Software Foundation,
  and we were beta-testing version 19 of GNU Emacs.  We'd make a beta
  release every week or so, and people would try it out and send us
  bug reports.  There was this one guy whom none of us had met in
  person but who did great work: his bug reports were always clear and
  led us straight to the problem, and when he provided a fix himself,
  it was almost always right.  He was top-notch.</para>

  <para>Now, before the FSF can use code written by someone else, we
  have them do some legal paperwork to assign their copyright interest
  to that code to the FSF.  Just taking code from complete strangers
  and dropping it in is a recipe for legal disaster.</para>

  <para>So I emailed the guy the forms, saying, "Here's some paperwork
  we need, here's what it means, you sign this one, have your employer
  sign that one, and then we can start putting in your fixes.  Thanks
  very much."</para>

  <para>He sent me back a message saying, "I don't have an
  employer."</para>

  <para>So I said, "Okay, that's fine, just have your university sign
  it and send it back."</para>

  <para>After a bit, he wrote me back again, and said, "Well,
  actually...  I'm thirteen years old and I live with my
  parents."</para>
</blockquote>

<para>Because that kid didn't write like a thirteen-year-old, no one
knew that's what he was.  Following are some ways to make your writing
give a good impression too.</para>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="structure-and-formatting">
<title>Structure and Formatting</title>

<para>Don't fall into the trap of writing everything as though it were
a cell phone text message.  Write in complete sentences, capitalizing
the first word of each sentence, and use paragraph breaks where
needed.  This is most important in emails and other composed writings.
In IRC or similarly ephemeral forums, it's generally okay to leave out
capitalization, use compressed forms of common expressions, etc.  Just
don't carry those habits over into more formal, persistent forums.
Emails, documentation, bug reports, and other pieces of writing that
are intended to have a permanent life should be written using standard
grammar and spelling, and have a coherent narrative structure.  This
is not because there's anything inherently good about following
arbitrary rules, but rather that these rules are
<emphasis>not</emphasis> arbitrary: they evolved into their present
forms because they make text more readable, and you should adhere to
them for that reason.  Readability is desirable not only because it
means more people will understand what you write, but because it makes
you look like the sort of person who takes the time to communicate
clearly: that is, someone worth paying attention to.</para>

<para>For email in particular, experienced open source developers have
settled on certain conventions:</para>

<para>Send plain text mails only, not HTML, RichText, or other formats
that might be opaque to text-only mail readers.  Format your lines to
be around 72 columns long.  Don't exceed 80 columns, which has become
the <foreignphrase>de facto</foreignphrase> standard terminal width
(that is, some people may use wider terminals, but no one uses a
narrower one).  By making your lines a little
<emphasis>less</emphasis> than 80 columns, you leave room for a few
levels of quoting characters to be added in others' replies without
forcing a rewrapping of your text.</para>

<para><emphasis>Use real line breaks.</emphasis> Some mailers do a
kind of fake line wrapping, whereby when you're composing an email,
the display shows line breaks that aren't actually there.  When the
mail goes out, it may not have the line breaks you thought it had, and
it will wrap awkwardly on some people's screens.  If your mailer might
use fake line breaks, look for a setting you can tweak to make it show
the true line breaks as you compose.</para>

<para>When including screen output, snippets of code, or other
preformatted text, offset it clearly, so that even a lazy eye can
easily see the boundaries between your prose and the material you're
quoting.  (I never expected to write that advice when I started this
book, but on a number of open source mailing lists lately, I've seen
people mix texts from different sources without making it clear which
is which.  The effect is very frustrating.  It makes their posts
significantly harder to understand, and frankly makes those people
look a little bit disorganized.)</para>

<para>When quoting someone else's mail, insert your responses where
they're most appropriate, at several different places if necessary,
and trim off the parts of their mail you didn't use.  If you're
writing a quick comment that applies to their entire post, it's okay
to <firstterm>top-post</firstterm> (that is, to put your response
above the quoted text of their mail); otherwise, you should quote
the relevant portion of the original text first, followed by your
response.</para>

<para>Construct the subject lines of new mails carefully.  It's the
most important line in your mail, because it allows each other person
in the project to decide whether or not to read more.  Modern
mail reading software organizes groups of related messages into
threads, which can be defined not only by a common subject, but by
various other headers (which are sometimes not displayed).  It follows
that if a thread starts to drift to a new topic, you can&mdash;and
should&mdash;adjust the subject line accordingly when replying.  The
thread's integrity will be preserved, due to those other headers, but
the new subject will help people looking at an overview of the thread
know that the topic has drifted.  Likewise, if you really want to
start a new topic, do it by posting a fresh mail, not by replying to
an existing mail and changing the subject.  Otherwise, your mail would
still be grouped in to the same thread as what you're replying to, and
thus fool people into thinking it's about something it's not.  Again,
the penalty would not only be the waste of their time, but the slight
dent in your credibility as someone fluent in using communications
tools.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="writing-content">
<title>Content</title>

<para>Well-formatted mails attract readers, but content keeps them.
No set of fixed rules can guarantee good content, of course, but there
are some principles that make it more likely.</para>

<para>Make things easy for your readers.  There's a ton of information
floating around in any active open source project, and readers cannot
be expected to be familiar with most of it&mdash;indeed, they cannot
always be expected to know how to become familiar.  Wherever possible,
your posts should provide information in the form most convenient for
readers.  If you have to spend an extra two minutes to dig up the URL
to a particular thread in the mailing list archives, in order to save
your readers the trouble of doing so, it's worth it.  If you have to
spend an extra 5 or 10 minutes summarizing the conclusions so far
of a complex thread, in order to give people context in which to
understand your post, then do so.  Think of it this way: the more
successful a project, the higher the reader-to-writer ratio in any
given forum.  If every post you make is seen by <emphasis>n</emphasis>
people, then as <emphasis>n</emphasis> rises, the worthwhileness of
expending extra effort to save those people time rises with it.  And
as people see you imposing this standard on yourself, they will work
to match it in their own communications.  The result is, ideally, an
increase in the global efficiency of the project: when there is a
choice between <emphasis>n</emphasis> people making an effort and one
person doing so, the project prefers the latter.</para>

<para>Don't engage in hyperbole.  Exaggerating in online posts is a
classic arms race.  For example, a person reporting a bug may worry
that the developers will not pay sufficient attention, so he'll
describe it as a severe, showstopper problem that is preventing him
(and all his friends/coworkers/cousins) from using the software
productively, when it's actually only a mild annoyance.  But
exaggeration is not limited to users&mdash;programmers often do the
same thing during technical debates, particularly when the
disagreement is over a matter of taste rather than correctness:</para>

  <blockquote>
     <para>"Doing it that way would make the code totally
     unreadable.  It'd be a maintenance nightmare, compared to
     J. Random's proposal..."</para>
  </blockquote>

<para>The same sentiment actually becomes
<emphasis>stronger</emphasis> when phrased less sharply:</para>

  <blockquote>
     <para>"That works, but it's less than ideal in terms of
     readability and maintainability, I think.  J. Random's proposal
     avoids those problems because it..."</para>
  </blockquote>

<para>You will not be able to get rid of hyperbole completely, and in
general it's not necessary to do so.  Compared to other forms of
miscommunication, hyperbole is not globally damaging&mdash;it hurts
mainly the perpetrator.  The recipients can compensate, it's just that
the sender loses a little more credibility each time.  Therefore, for
the sake of your own influence in the project, try to err on the side
of moderation.  That way, when you <emphasis>do</emphasis> need to
make a strong point, people will take you seriously.</para>

<para>Edit twice.  For any message longer than a medium-sized
paragraph, reread it from top to bottom before sending it but after
you think it's done the first time.  This is familiar advice to anyone
who's taken a composition class, but it's especially important in
online discussion.  Because the process of online composition tends to
be highly discontinuous (in the course of writing a message, you may
need to go back and check other mails, visit certain web pages, run a
command to capture its debugging output, etc.), it's especially easy to
lose your sense of narrative place.  Messages that were composed
discontinuously and not checked before being sent are often
recognizable as such, much to the chagrin (or so one would hope) of
their authors.  Take the time to review what you send.  The more your
posts hold together structurally, the more they will be read.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="writing-tone">
<title>Tone</title>

<para>After writing thousands of messages, you will probably find your
style tending toward the terse.  This seems to be the norm in most
technical forums, and there's nothing wrong with it per se.  A degree
of terseness that would be unacceptable in normal social interactions
is simply the default for free software hackers.  Here's a response I
once drew on a mailing list about some free content management
software, quoted in full:</para>

<screen>
Can you possibly elaborate a bit more on exactly what problems
you ran into, etc?

Also:

What version of Slash are you using? I couldn't tell from your
original message.

Exactly how did you build the apache/mod_perl source?

Did you try the Apache 2.0 patch that was posted about on
slashcode.com?

  Shane
</screen>

<para>Now <emphasis>that's</emphasis> terse!  No greeting, no sign-off
other than his name, and the message itself is just a series of
questions phrased as compactly as possible.  His one declarative
sentence was an implicit criticism of my original message.  And yet, I
was happy to see Shane's mail, and didn't take his terseness as a sign
of anything other than him being a busy person.  The mere fact that he
was asking questions, instead of ignoring my post, meant that he was
willing to spend some time on my problem.</para>

<para>Will all readers react positively to this style?  Not
necessarily; it depends on the person and the context.  For example,
if someone has just posted acknowledging that she made a mistake
(perhaps she wrote a bug), and you know from past experience that
this person tends to be a bit insecure, then while you may still write
a compact response, you should make sure to leaven it with some sort
of acknowledgment of her feelings.  The bulk of your response might
be a brief, engineer's-eye analysis of the situation, as terse as you
want.  But at the end, sign off with something indicating that your
terseness is not to be taken as coldness.  For example, if you've just
given reams of advice about exactly how the person should fix the bug,
then sign off with "Good luck, &lt;your name here&gt;" to indicate
that you wish them well and are not mad.  A strategically placed
smiley face or other emoticlue can often be enough to reassure an
interlocutor, too.</para>

<para>It may seem odd to focus as much on the participant's feelings
as on the surface of what they say, but to put it baldly, feelings
affect productivity.  Feelings are important for other reasons too,
but even confining ourselves to purely utilitarian grounds, we may
note that unhappy people write worse software, and less of it.  Given
the restricted nature of most electronic media, though, there will
often be no overt clue as to how a person is feeling.  You will have
to make an educated guess based on a) how most people would feel in
that situation, and b) what you know of this particular person from
past interactions.  Some people prefer a more hands-off attitude, and
simply deal with everyone at face value, the idea being that if a
participant doesn't say outright that she feels a particular way, then
one has no business treating her as though she does.  I don't buy this
approach, for a couple of reasons.  One, people don't behave that way
in real life, so why would they online?  Two, since most interactions
take place in public forums, people tend to be even more restrained in
expressing emotions than they might be in private.  To be more
precise, they are often willing to express emotions directed at
others, such as gratitude or outrage, but not emotions directed
inwardly, such as insecurity or pride.  Yet most humans work better
when they know that others are aware of their state of mind.  By
paying attention to small clues, you can usually guess right most of
the time, and motivate people to stay involved to a greater degree
than they otherwise might.</para>

<para>I don't mean, of course, that your role is to be a group
therapist, constantly helping everyone to get in touch with their
feelings.  But by paying careful attention to long-term patterns in
people's behavior, you will begin to get a sense of them as
individuals even if you never meet them face-to-face.  And by being
sensitive to the tone of your own writing, you can have a surprising
amount of influence over how others feel, to the ultimate benefit of
the project.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="rudeness">
<title>Recognizing Rudeness</title>

<para>One of the defining characteristics of open source culture is
its distinctive notions of what does and does not constitute rudeness.
While the conventions described below are not unique to free software
development, nor even to software in general&mdash;they would be
familiar to anyone working in mathematics, the hard sciences, or
engineering disciplines&mdash;free software, with its porous
boundaries and constant influx of newcomers, is an environment where
these conventions are especially likely to be encountered by people
unfamiliar with them.</para>

<para>Let's start with the things that are <emphasis>not</emphasis>
rude:</para>

<para>Technical criticism, even when direct and unpadded, is not rude.
Indeed, it can be a form of flattery: the critic is saying, by
implication, that the target is worth taking seriously, and is worth
spending some time on.  That is, the more viable it would have been to
simply ignore someone's post, the more of a compliment it becomes to
take the time to criticize it (unless the critique descends into an
<foreignphrase>ad hominem</foreignphrase> attack or some other form of
obvious rudeness, of course).</para>

<para>Blunt, unadorned questions, such as Shane's questions to me in
the previously quoted email, are not rude either.  Questions that in
other contexts might seem cold, rhetorical, or even mocking, are often
intended seriously, and have no hidden agenda other than eliciting
information as quickly as possible.  The famous technical support
question "Is your computer plugged in?" is a classic example of this.
The support person really does need to know if your computer is
plugged in, and after the first few days on the job, has gotten tired
of prefixing her question with polite blandishments ("I beg your
pardon, I just want to ask a few simple questions to rule out some
possibilities.  Some of these might seem pretty basic, but bear with
me...").  At this point, she doesn't bother with the padding anymore,
she just asks straight out: is it plugged in or not?  Equivalent
questions are asked all the time on free software mailing lists.  The
intent is not to insult the recipient, but to quickly rule out the
most obvious (and perhaps most common) explanations.  Recipients who
understand this and react accordingly win points for taking a
broad-minded view without prompting.  But recipients who react badly
should not be reprimanded, either.  It's just a collision of cultures,
not anyone's fault.  Explain amiably that your question (or criticism)
had no hidden meanings; it was just meant to get (or transmit)
information as efficiently as possible, nothing more.</para>

<para>So what is rude?</para>

<para>By the same principle under which detailed technical criticism
is a form of flattery, failure to provide quality criticism can be a
kind of insult.  I don't mean simply ignoring someone's work, be it
proposal, code change, new issue filing, or whatever.  Unless you
explicitly promised a detailed reaction in advance, it's usually okay
to simply not react at all.  People will assume you just didn't have
time to say anything.  But if you <emphasis>do</emphasis> react, don't
skimp: take the time to really analyze things, provide concrete
examples where appropriate, dig around in the archives to find related
posts from the past, etc.  Or if you don't have time to put in that
kind of effort, but still need to write some sort of brief response,
then state the shortcoming openly in your message ("I think there's an
issue filed for this, but unfortunately didn't have time to search for
it, sorry").  The main thing is to recognize the existence of the
cultural norm, either by fulfilling it or by openly acknowledging
that one has fallen short this time.  Either way, the norm is
strengthened.  But failing to meet that norm, while at the same time
not explaining <emphasis>why</emphasis> you failed to meet it, is like
saying the topic (and those participating in it) was not worth much
of your time.  Better to show that your time is valuable by being
terse than by being lazy.</para>

<para>There are many other forms of rudeness, of course, but most of
them are not specific to free software development, and common sense
is a good enough guide to avoid them.  See also
<xref linkend="prevent-rudeness"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="getting-started"/></phrase>, if you haven't
already.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="face">
<title>Face</title>

<para>There is a region in the human brain devoted specifically to
recognizing faces.  It is known informally as the "fusiform face
area," and its capabilities are mostly inborn, not learned.  It turns
out that recognizing individual people is such a crucial survival
skill that we have evolved specialized hardware to do it.</para>

<para>Internet-based collaboration is therefore psychologically odd,
because it involves tight cooperation between human beings who almost
never get to identify each other by the most natural, intuitive
methods: facial recognition first of all, but also sound of voice,
posture, etc.  To compensate for this, try to use a consistent
<firstterm>screen name</firstterm> everywhere.  It should be the front
part of your email address (the part before the @-sign), your IRC
username, your repository committer name, your issue tracker username,
and so on.  This name is your online "face": a short identifying
string that serves some of the same purpose as your real face,
although it does not, unfortunately, stimulate the same built-in
hardware in the brain.</para>

<para>The screen name should be some intuitive permutation of your
real name (mine, for example, is "kfogel").  In some situations it
will be accompanied by your full name anyway, for example in mail
headers:</para>

<screen>
From: "Karl Fogel" &lt;kfogel@whateverdomain.com&gt;
</screen>

<para>Actually, there are two things going on in that example.  As
mentioned earlier, the screen name matches the real name in an
intuitive way.  But also, the real name is <emphasis>real</emphasis>.
That is, it's not some made-up appellation like:</para>

<screen>
From: "Wonder Hacker" &lt;wonderhacker@whateverdomain.com&gt;
</screen>

<para>There's a famous cartoon by Paul Steiner, from the July 5, 1993
issue of <citetitle>The New Yorker</citetitle>, that shows one dog
logged into a computer terminal, looking down and telling another
conspiratorially: "On the Internet, nobody knows you're a dog."  This
kind of thought probably lies behind a lot of the self-aggrandizing,
meant-to-be-hip online identities people give themselves&mdash;as if
calling oneself "Wonder Hacker" will actually cause people to believe
one <emphasis>is</emphasis> a wonderful hacker.  But the fact remains:
even if no one knows you're a dog, you're still a dog.  A fantastical
online identity never impresses readers.  Instead, it makes them think
you're more into image than substance, or that you're simply insecure.
Use your real name for all interactions, or if for some reason you
require anonymity, then make up a name that sounds like a perfectly
normal real name, and use it consistently.</para>

<para>In addition to keeping your online face consistent, there are
some things you can do to make it more attractive.  If you have an
official title (e.g., "doctor", "professor", "director"), don't flaunt
it, nor even mention it except when it's directly relevant to the
conversation.  Hackerdom in general, and free software culture in
particular, tends to view title displays as exclusionary and a sign of
insecurity.  It's okay if your title appears as part of a standard
signature block at the end of every mail you send, just don't ever use
it as a tool to bolster your position in a discussion&mdash;the
attempt is guaranteed to backfire.  You want folks to respect the
person, not the title.</para>

<para>Speaking of signature blocks: keep them small and tasteful, or
better yet, nonexistent.  Avoid large legal disclaimers tacked on to
the end of every mail, especially when they express sentiments
incompatible with participation in a free software project.  For
example, the following classic of the genre appears at the end of
every post a particular user makes to a public mailing list I'm
on:</para>

<screen>
IMPORTANT NOTICE

If you have received this e-mail in error or wish to read our e-mail
disclaimer statement and monitoring policy, please refer to the
statement below or contact the sender.

This communication is from Deloitte &amp; Touche LLP.  Deloitte &amp;
Touche LLP is a limited liability partnership registered in England
and Wales with registered number OC303675.  A list of members' names
is available for inspection at Stonecutter Court, 1 Stonecutter
Street, London EC4A 4TR, United Kingdom, the firm's principal place of
business and registered office.  Deloitte &amp; Touche LLP is
authorised and regulated by the Financial Services Authority.

This communication and any attachments contain information which is
confidential and may also be privileged.  It is for the exclusive use
of the intended recipient(s).  If you are not the intended
recipient(s) please note that any form of disclosure, distribution,
copying or use of this communication or the information in it or in
any attachments is strictly prohibited and may be unlawful.  If you
have received this communication in error, please return it with the
title "received in error" to IT.SECURITY.UK@deloitte.co.uk then delete
the email and destroy any copies of it.

E-mail communications cannot be guaranteed to be secure or error free,
as information could be intercepted, corrupted, amended, lost,
destroyed, arrive late or incomplete, or contain viruses.  We do not
accept liability for any such matters or their consequences.  Anyone
who communicates with us by e-mail is taken to accept the risks in
doing so.

When addressed to our clients, any opinions or advice contained in
this e-mail and any attachments are subject to the terms and
conditions expressed in the governing Deloitte &amp; Touche LLP client
engagement letter.

Opinions, conclusions and other information in this e-mail and any
attachments which do not relate to the official business of the firm
are neither given nor endorsed by it.
</screen>

<para>For someone who's just showing up to ask a question now and
then, that huge disclaimer looks a bit silly but probably doesn't do
any lasting harm.  However, if this person wanted to participate
actively in the project, that legal boilerplate would start to have a
more insidious effect.  It would send at least two potentially
destructive signals: first, that this person doesn't have full control
over his tools&mdash;he's trapped inside some corporate mailer that
tacks an annoying message to the end of every email, and he hasn't got
any way to route around it&mdash;and second, that he has little or no
organizational support for his free software activities.  True, the
organization has clearly not banned him outright from posting to
public lists, but it has made his posts look distinctly unwelcoming,
as though the risk of letting out confidential information must trump
all other priorities.</para>

<para>If you work for an organization that insists on adding such
signature blocks to all outgoing mail, then consider getting a free
email account from, for example, <ulink url="http://gmail.google.com/"
>gmail.google.com</ulink>, <ulink url="http://www.hotmail.com/"
>www.hotmail.com</ulink>, or <ulink url="http://www.yahoo.com/"
>www.yahoo.com</ulink>, and using that as your address for the
project.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->

<sect1 id="common-pitfalls">
<title>Avoiding Common Pitfalls</title>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->

<sect2 id="post-with-purpose">
<title>Don't Post Without a Purpose</title>

<para>A common pitfall in online project participation is to think
that you have to respond to everything.  You don't.  First of all,
there will usually be more threads going on than you can keep track
of, at least after the project is past its first few months.  Second,
even in the threads that you have decided to engage in, much of what
people say will not require a response.  Development forums in
particular tend to be dominated by three kinds of messages:</para>

<orderedlist>
  <listitem><para>Messages proposing something non-trivial</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Messages expressing support or opposition to
                  something someone else has said</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Summing-up messages</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>None of these <emphasis>inherently</emphasis> requires a
response, particularly if you can be fairly sure, based on watching
the thread so far, that someone else is likely to say what you would
have said anyway.  (If you're worried that you'll be caught in a
wait-wait loop because all the others are using this tactic too, don't
be; there's almost always <emphasis>someone</emphasis> out there
who'll feel like jumping into the fray.)  A response should be
motivated by a definite purpose.  Ask yourself first: do you know what
you want to accomplish?  And second: will it not get accomplished
unless you say something?</para>

<para>Two good reasons to add your voice to a thread are a) when you
see a flaw in a proposal and suspect that you're the only one who sees
it, and b) when you see that miscommunication is happening between
others, and know that you can fix it with a clarifying post.  It's
also generally fine to post just to thank someone for doing something,
or to say "Me too!", because a reader can tell right away that such
posts do not require any response or further action, and therefore the
mental effort demanded by the post ends cleanly when the reader
reaches the last line of the mail.  But even then, think twice before
saying something; it's always better to leave people wishing you'd
post more than wishing you'd post less.  (See the second half of <xref
linkend="bikeshed-full"/> for more thoughts about how to behave on
a busy mailing list.)</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->

<sect2 id="productive-threads">
<title>Productive vs Unproductive Threads</title>

<para>On a busy mailing list, you have two imperatives.  One,
obviously, is to figure out what you need to pay attention to and what
you can ignore.  The other is to behave in a way that
avoids <emphasis>causing</emphasis> noise: not only do you want your
own posts to have a high signal/noise ratio, you also want them to be
the sorts of messages that stimulate <emphasis>other</emphasis> people
to either post with a similarly high signal/noise ratio, or not post
at all.</para>

<para>To see how to do that, let's consider the context in which it is
done.  What are some of the hallmarks of an unproductive thread?</para>

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>Arguments that have been made already start being
            repeated, as though the poster thinks no one heard them
            the first time.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>Increasing levels of hyperbole and involvement as
            the stakes get smaller and smaller.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>A majority of comments coming from people who do
            little or nothing, while the people who tend to get things
            done are silent.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>Many ideas discussed without clear proposals ever
            being made.  (Of course, any interesting idea starts out
            as an imprecise vision; the important question is what
            direction it goes from there.  Does the thread seem to be
            turning the vision into something more concrete, or is it
            spinning off into sub-visions, side-visions, and
            ontological disputes?)</para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Just because a thread is not productive at first doesn't mean
it's a waste of time.  It might be about an important topic, in which
case the fact that it's not making any headway is all the more
troublesome.</para>

<para>Guiding a thread toward usefulness without being pushy is an
art.  It won't work to simply admonish people to stop wasting their
time, or to ask them not to post unless they have something constructive
to say.  You may, of course, think these things privately, but if you
say them out loud then you will be offensive.  Instead, you have to
suggest conditions for further progress&mdash;give people a route, a
path to follow that leads to the results you want, yet without
sounding like you're dictating conduct.  The distinction is largely
one of tone.  For example, this is bad:</para>

  <blockquote>
     <para><emphasis>This discussion is going nowhere.  Can we please
     drop this topic until someone has a patch to implement one of
     these proposals?  There's no reason to keep going around and
     around saying the same things.  Code speaks louder than
     words, folks.</emphasis></para>
  </blockquote>

<para>Whereas this is good:</para>

  <blockquote>
     <para><emphasis>Several proposals have been floated in this
     thread, but none have had all the details fleshed out, at least
     not enough for an up-or-down vote.  Yet we're also not saying
     anything new now; we're just reiterating what has been said
     before.  So the best thing at this point would probably be for
     further posts to contain either a complete specification for the
     proposed behavior, or a patch.  Then at least we'd have a
     definite action to take (i.e., get consensus on the
     specification, or apply and test the patch).</emphasis></para>
  </blockquote>

<para>Contrast the second approach with the first.  The second way
does not draw a line between you and the others, or accuse them of
taking the discussion into a spiral.  It talks about "we", which is
important whether or not you actually participated in the thread
before now, because it reminds everyone that even those who have been
silent thus far still have a stake in the thread's outcome.  It
describes why the thread is going nowhere, but does so without
pejoratives or judgements&mdash;it just dispassionately states
some facts.  Most importantly, it offers a positive course of action,
so that instead of people feeling like discussion is being closed off
(a restriction against which they can only be tempted to rebel), they
will feel as if they're being offered a way to take the conversation
to a more constructive level.  This is a standard people will
naturally want to meet.</para>

<para>You won't always want a thread to make it to the next level of
constructiveness&mdash;sometimes you'll want it to just go away.  The
purpose of your post, then, is to make it do one or the other.  If you
can tell from the way the thread has gone so far that no one is
actually <emphasis>going</emphasis> to take the steps you suggested,
then your post effectively shuts down the thread without seeming to do
so.  Of course, there isn't any foolproof way to shut down a thread,
and even if there were, you wouldn't want to use it.  But asking
participants to either make visible progress or stop posting is
perfectly defensible, if done diplomatically.  Be wary of quashing
threads prematurely, however.  Some amount of speculative chatter can
be productive, depending on the topic, and asking for it to be
resolved too quickly will stifle the creative process, as well as make
you look impatient.</para>

<para>Don't expect any thread to stop on a dime.  There will probably
still be a few posts after yours, either because mails got crossed in
the pipe, or because people want to have the last word.  This is
nothing to worry about, and you don't need to post again.  Just let
the thread peter out, or not peter out, as the case may be.  You can't
have complete control; on the other hand, you can expect to have a
statistically significant effect across many threads.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="bikeshed">
<title>The Softer the Topic, the Longer the Debate</title>

<para>Although discussion can meander in any topic, the probability of
meandering goes up as the technical difficulty of the topic goes down.
After all, the greater the technical difficulty, the fewer
participants can really follow what's going on.  Those who can are
likely to be the most experienced developers, who have already taken
part in such discussions thousands of times before, and know what sort
of behavior is likely to lead to a consensus everyone can live
with.</para>

<para>Thus, consensus is hardest to achieve in technical questions
that are simple to understand and easy to have an opinion about, and
in "soft" topics such as organization, publicity, funding, etc.
People can participate in those arguments forever, because there are
no qualifications necessary for doing so, no clear ways to decide (even
afterward) if a decision was right or wrong, and because simply
outwaiting other discussants is sometimes a successful tactic.</para>

<para>The principle that the amount of discussion is inversely
proportional to the complexity of the topic has been around for a long
time, and is known informally as the <firstterm>Bikeshed
Effect</firstterm>.  Here is Poul-Henning Kamp's explanation of it,
from a now-famous post made to BSD developers:</para>

<blockquote>

<para>It's a long story, or rather it's an old story, but it is quite
short actually.  C. Northcote Parkinson wrote a book in the early
1960'ies, called "Parkinson's Law", which contains a lot of insight
into the dynamics of management.</para>

<para>[...]</para>

<para>In the specific example involving the bike shed, the other vital
component is an atomic power-plant, I guess that illustrates the age
of the book.</para>

<para>Parkinson shows how you can go in to the board of directors and
get approval for building a multi-million or even billion dollar
atomic power plant, but if you want to build a bike shed you will be
tangled up in endless discussions.</para>

<para>Parkinson explains that this is because an atomic plant is so
vast, so expensive and so complicated that people cannot grasp it, and
rather than try, they fall back on the assumption that somebody else
checked all the details before it got this far.  Richard P.  Feynmann
gives a couple of interesting, and very much to the point, examples
relating to Los Alamos in his books.</para>

<para>A bike shed on the other hand.  Anyone can build one of those
over a weekend, and still have time to watch the game on TV.  So no
matter how well prepared, no matter how reasonable you are with your
proposal, somebody will seize the chance to show that he is doing his
job, that he is paying attention, that he
is <emphasis>here</emphasis>.</para>

<para>In Denmark we call it "setting your fingerprint".  It is about
personal pride and prestige, it is about being able to point somewhere
and say "There!  <emphasis>I</emphasis> did that."  It is a strong
trait in politicians, but present in most people given the chance.
Just think about footsteps in wet cement.</para>

</blockquote>

<para>(His complete post is very much worth reading, too.  See <xref
linkend="bikeshed-full"/>; see also
<ulink url="http://bikeshed.com"/>.)</para>

<para>Anyone who's ever taken regular part in group decision-making
will recognize what Kamp is talking about.  However, it is usually
impossible to persuade <emphasis>everyone</emphasis> to avoid painting
bikesheds.  The best you can do is point out that the phenomenon
exists, when you see it happening, and persuade the senior
developers&mdash;the people whose posts carry the most weight&mdash;to
drop their paintbrushes early, so at least they're not contributing to
the noise.  Bikeshed painting parties will never go away entirely, but
you can make them shorter and less frequent by spreading an awareness
of the phenomenon in the project's culture.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect2 id="holy-wars">
<title>Avoid Holy Wars</title>

<para>A <firstterm>holy war</firstterm> is a dispute, often but not
always over a relatively minor issue, which is not resolvable on the
merits of the arguments, but where people feel passionate enough to
continue arguing anyway in the hope that their side will prevail.
Holy wars are not quite the same as bikeshed paintings.  People
painting bikesheds are usually quick to jump in with an opinion
(because they can), but they won't necessarily feel strongly about it,
and indeed will sometimes express other, incompatible opinions, to
show that they understand all sides of the issue.  In a holy war, on
the other hand, understanding the other sides is a sign of weakness.
In a holy war, everyone knows there is One Right Answer; they just
don't agree on what it is.</para>

<para>Once a holy war has started, it generally cannot be resolved to
everyone's satisfaction.  It does no good to point out, in the midst
of a holy war, that a holy war is going on.  Everyone knows that
already.  Unfortunately, a common feature of holy wars is disagreement
on the very question of <emphasis>whether</emphasis> the dispute is
resolvable by continued discussion.  Viewed from outside, it is clear
that neither side is changing the other's mind.  Viewed from inside,
the other side is being obtuse and not thinking clearly, but they
might come around if browbeaten enough.  Now, I am
<emphasis>not</emphasis> saying there's never a right side in a holy
war.  Sometimes there is&mdash;in the holy wars I've participated
in, it's always been my side, of course.  But it doesn't matter,
because there's no algorithm for convincingly demonstrating that one
side or the other is right.</para>

<para>A common, but unsatisfactory, way people try to resolve holy
wars is to say "We've already spent far more time and energy
discussing this than it's worth!  Can we please just drop it?"  There
are two problems with this.  First, that time and energy has already
been spent and can never be recovered&mdash;the only question now is,
how much <emphasis>more</emphasis> effort remains?  If some people
feel that just a little more discussion will bring the issue to a
close, then it still makes sense (from their point of view) to
continue.</para>

<para>The other problem with asking for the matter to be dropped is
that this is often equivalent to allowing one side, the status quo, to
declare victory by inaction.  And in some cases, the status quo is
known to be unacceptable anyway: everyone agrees that some decision
must be made, some action taken.  Dropping the subject would be worse
for everyone than simply giving up the argument would be for anyone.
But since that dilemma applies to all equally, it's still possible to
end up arguing forever about what to do.</para>

<para>So how should you handle holy wars?</para>

<para>The first answer is, try to set things up so they don't happen.
This is not as hopeless as it sounds:</para>

<para>You can anticipate certain standard holy wars: they tend to come
up over programming languages, licenses (see
<xref linkend="license-compatibility"/><phrase output="printed">
in <xref linkend="legal"/></phrase>), reply-to munging (see
<xref linkend="reply-to"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="technical-infrastructure"/></phrase>), and a few
other topics.  Each project 
usually has a holy war or two all its own, as well, which longtime
developers will quickly become familiar with.  The techniques for
stopping holy wars, or at least limiting their damage, are pretty much
the same everywhere.  Even if you are positive your side is right, try
to find <emphasis>some</emphasis> way to express sympathy and
understanding for the points the other side is making.  Often the
problem in a holy war is that because each side has built its walls
as high as possible, and made it clear that any other opinion is sheer
foolishness, the act of surrendering or changing one's mind becomes
psychologically unbearable: it would be an admission not just of being
wrong, but of having been <emphasis>certain</emphasis> and still being
wrong.  The way you can make this admission palatable for the other
side is to express some uncertainty yourself&mdash;precisely by
showing that you understand the arguments they are making and find
them at least sensible, if not finally persuasive.  Make a gesture
that provides space for a reciprocal gesture, and usually the
situation will improve.  You are no more or less likely to get the
technical result you wanted, but at least you can avoid unnecessary
collateral damage to the project's morale.</para>

<para>When a holy war can't be avoided, decide early how much you
care, and then be willing to publicly give up.  When you do so, you
can say that you're backing out because the holy war isn't worth it,
but don't express any bitterness and <emphasis>don't</emphasis> take
the opportunity for a last parting shot at the opposing side's
arguments.  Giving up is effective only when done gracefully.</para>

<para>Programming language holy wars are a bit of a special case,
because they are often highly technical, yet many people feel
qualified to take part in them, and the stakes are very high, since
the result may determine what language a good portion of the project's
code is written in.  The best solution is to choose the language
early, with buy-in from influential initial developers, and then
defend it on the grounds that it's what you are all comfortable
writing in, <emphasis>not</emphasis> on the grounds that it's better
than some other language that could have been used instead.  Never let
the conversation degenerate into an academic comparison of programming
languages (this seems to happen especially often when someone brings
up Perl, for some reason); that's a death topic that you must simply
refuse to be drawn into.</para>

<para>For more historical background on holy wars, see <ulink
url="http://catb.org/~esr/jargon/html/H/holy-wars.html"/>, and the
paper by Danny Cohen that popularized the term, <ulink
url="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/ien/ien137.txt"/>.</para>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->

<sect2 id="noisy-minority">
<title>The "Noisy Minority" Effect</title>

<para>In any mailing list discussion, it's easy for a small minority
to give the impression that there is a great deal of dissent, by
flooding the list with numerous lengthy emails.  It's a bit like a
filibuster, except that the illusion of widespread dissent is even
more powerful, because it's divided across an arbitrary number of
discrete posts and most people won't bother to keep track of who said
what, when.  They'll just have an instinctive impression that the topic
is very controversial, and wait for the fuss to die down.</para>

<para>The best way to counteract this effect is to point it out very
clearly and provide supporting evidence showing how small the actual
number of dissenters is, compared to those in agreement.  In order to
increase the disparity, you may want to privately poll people who have
been mostly silent, but who you suspect would agree with the majority.
Don't say anything that suggests the dissenters were deliberately
trying to inflate the impression they were making.  Chances are they
weren't, and even if they were, there would be no strategic advantage
to pointing it out.  All you need do is show the actual numbers in a
side-by-side comparison, and people will realize that their intuition
of the situation does not match reality.</para>

<para>This advice doesn't just apply to issues with clear
for-and-against positions.  It applies to any discussion where a fuss
is being made, but it's not clear that most people consider the issue
under discussion to be a real problem.  After a while, if you agree that
the issue is not worthy of action, and can see that it has failed to
get much traction (even if it has generated a lot of mails), you can
just observe publicly that it's not getting traction.  If the "Noisy
Minority" effect has been at work, your post will seem like a breath of
fresh air.  Most people's impression of the discussion up to that
point will have been somewhat murky: "Huh, it sure feels like there's
some big deal here, because there sure are a lot of posts, but I can't
see any clear progress happening."  By explaining how the form of the
discussion made it appear more turbulent than it really was, you
retrospectively give it a new shape, through which people can recast
their understanding of what transpired.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="difficult-people">
<title>Difficult People</title>

<para>Difficult people are no easier to deal with in electronic forums
than they are in person.  By "difficult" I don't mean "rude".  Rude
people are annoying, but they're not necessarily difficult.  This book
has already discussed how to handle them: comment on the rudeness the
first time, and from then on, either ignore them or treat them the same
as anyone else.  If they continue being rude, they will usually make
themselves so unpopular as to have no influence on others in the
project, so they are a self-containing problem.</para>

<para>The really difficult cases are people who are not overtly rude,
but who manipulate or abuse the project's processes in a way that ends
up costing other people time and energy, yet do not bring any benefit
to the project.  Such people often look for wedgepoints in the
project's procedures, to give themselves more influence than they
might otherwise have.  This is much more insidious than mere rudeness,
because neither the behavior nor the damage it causes is apparent to
casual observers.  A classic example is the filibuster, in which
someone (always sounding as reasonable as possible, of course) keeps
claiming that the matter under discussion is not ready for resolution,
and offers more and more possible solutions, or new viewpoints on old
solutions, when what is really going on is that he senses that a
consensus or a ballot is about to form, and doesn't like where it is
probably headed.  Another example is when there's a debate that won't
converge on consensus, but the group tries to at least clarify the
points of disagreement and produce a summary for everyone to refer to
from then on.  The obstructionist, who knows the summary may lead to a
result he doesn't like, will often try to delay even the summary, by
relentlessly complicating the question of what should be in it, either
by objecting to reasonable suggestions or by introducing unexpected
new items.</para>

<sect2 id="handling-difficult-people">
<title>Handling Difficult People</title>

<para>To counteract such behavior, it helps to understand the
mentality of those who engage in it.  People generally do not do it
consciously.  No one wakes up in the morning and says to himself:
"Today I'm going to cynically manipulate procedural forms in order to
be an irritating obstructionist."  Instead, such actions are often
preceded by a semi-paranoid feeling of being shut out of group
interactions and decisions.  The person feels he is not being taken
seriously, or (in the more severe cases) that there is almost a
conspiracy against him&mdash;that the other project members have decided to
form an exclusive club, of which he is not a member.  This then
justifies, in his mind, taking rules literally and engaging in a
formal manipulation of the project's procedures, in order
to <emphasis>make</emphasis> everyone else take him seriously.  In
extreme cases, the person can even believe that he is fighting a
lonely battle to save the project from itself.</para>

<para>It is the nature of such an attack from within that not everyone
will notice it at the same time, and some people may not see it at all
unless presented with very strong evidence.  This means that
neutralizing it can be quite a bit of work.  It's not enough to
persuade yourself that it's happening; you have to marshal enough
evidence to persuade others too, and then you have to distribute that
evidence in a thoughtful way.</para>

<para>Given that it's so much work to fight, it's often better just to
tolerate it for a while.  Think of it like a parasitic but mild
disease: if it's not too debilitating, the project can afford to
remain infected, and medicine might have harmful side effects.
However, if it gets too damaging to tolerate, then it's time for
action.  Start gathering notes on the patterns you see.  Make sure to
include references to public archives&mdash;this is one of the reasons
the project keeps records, so you might as well use them.  Once you've
got a good case built, start having private conversations with other
project participants.  Don't tell them what you've observed; instead,
first ask them what they've observed.  This may be your last chance to
get unfiltered feedback about how others see the troublemaker's
behavior; once you start openly talking about it, opinion will
become polarized and no one will be able to remember what he
formerly thought about the matter.</para>

<para>If private discussions indicate that at least some others see
the problem too, then it's time to do something.  That's when you
have to get <emphasis>really</emphasis> cautious, because it's very
easy for this sort of person to try to make it appear as though you're
picking on them unfairly.  Whatever you do, never accuse them of
maliciously abusing the project's procedures, of being paranoid, or, in
general, of any of the other things that you suspect are probably
true.  Your strategy should be to look both more reasonable and more
concerned with the overall welfare of the project, with the goal of
either reforming the person's behavior, or getting them to go away
permanently.  Depending on the other developers, and your relationship
with them, it may be advantageous to gather allies privately first.
Or it may not; that might just create ill will behind the scenes, if
people think you're engaging in an improper whispering
campaign.</para>

<para>Remember that although the other person may be the one behaving
destructively, <emphasis>you</emphasis> will be the one who appears
destructive if you make a public charge that you can't back up.  Be
sure to have plenty of examples to demonstrate what you're saying, and
say it as gently as possible while still being direct.  You may not
persuade the person in question, but that's okay as long as you
persuade everyone else.</para>

</sect2>

<sect2 id="difficult-people-case-study">
<title>Case study</title>

<para>I remember only one situation, in more than 10 years of working
in free software, where things got so bad that we actually had to ask
someone to stop posting altogether.  As is so often the case, he was
not rude, and sincerely wanted only to be helpful.  He just didn't
know when to post and when not to post.  Our lists were open to the
public, and he was posting so often, and asking questions on so many
different topics, that it was getting to be a noise problem for the
community.  We'd already tried asking him nicely to do a little more
research for answers before posting, but that had no effect.</para>

<para>The strategy that finally worked is a perfect example of how to
build a strong case on neutral, quantitative data.  One of our
developers did some digging in the archives, and then sent the
following message privately to a few developers.  The offender (the
third name on the list below, shown here as "J. Random") had very
little history with the project, and had contributed no code or
documentation.  Yet he was the third most active poster on the mailing
lists:</para>

<screen>
From: "Brian W. Fitzpatrick" &lt;fitz@collab.net&gt;
To: [... recipient list omitted for anonymity ...]
Subject: The Subversion Energy Sink
Date: Wed, 12 Nov 2003 23:37:47 -0600

In the last 25 days, the top 6 posters to the svn [dev|users] list have
been:

    294  kfogel@collab.net
    236  "C. Michael Pilato" &lt;cmpilato@collab.net&gt;
    220  "J. Random" &lt;jrandom@problematic-poster.com&gt;
    176  Branko &Ccaron;ibej &lt;brane@xbc.nu&gt;
    130  Philip Martin &lt;philip@codematters.co.uk&gt;
    126  Ben Collins-Sussman &lt;sussman@collab.net&gt;

I would say that five of these people are contributing to Subversion
hitting 1.0 in the near future.

I would also say that one of these people is consistently drawing time
and energy from the other 5, not to mention the list as a whole, thus
(albeit unintentionally) slowing the development of Subversion.  I did
not do a threaded analysis, but vgrepping my Subversion mail spool tells
me that every mail from this person is responded to at least once by at
least 2 of the other 5 people on the above list.

I think some sort of radical intervention is necessary here, even if we
do scare the aforementioned person away.  Niceties and kindness have
already proven to have no effect.

dev@subversion is a mailing list to facilitate development of a version
control system, not a group therapy session.

-Fitz, attempting to wade through three days of svn mail that he let
 pile up
</screen>

<para>Though it might not seem so at first, J. Random's behavior was a
classic case of abusing project procedures.  He wasn't doing something
obvious like trying to filibuster a vote, but he was taking advantage
of the mailing list's policy of relying on self-moderation by its
members.  We left it to each individual's judgement when to post and
on what topics.  Thus, we had no procedural recourse for dealing with
someone who either did not have, or would not exercise, such judgement.
There was no rule one could point to and say the fellow was violating
it, yet everyone knew that his frequent posting was getting to be a
serious problem.</para>

<para>Fitz's strategy was, in retrospect, masterful.  He gathered
damning quantitative evidence, but then distributed it discreetly,
sending it first to a few people whose support would be key in any
drastic action.  They agreed that some sort of action was necessary,
and in the end we called J. Random on the phone, described the problem
to him directly, and asked him to simply stop posting.  He never
really did understand the reasons why; if he had been capable
of understanding, he probably would have exercised appropriate
judgement in the first place.  But he agreed to stop posting, and the
mailing lists became useable again.  Part of the reason this strategy
worked was, perhaps, the implicit threat that we could start
restricting his posts via the moderation software normally used for
preventing spam (see
<xref linkend="spam-prevention"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="technical-infrastructure"/></phrase>).  But the
reason we were able to have that option in reserve was that Fitz had
gathered the necessary support from key people first.</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="growth">
<title>Handling Growth</title>

<para>The price of success is heavy in the open source world.  As your
software gets more popular, the number of people who show up looking
for information increases dramatically, while the number of people
able to provide information increases much more slowly.  Furthermore,
even if the ratio were evenly balanced, there is still a fundamental
scalability problem with the way most open source projects handle
communications.  Consider mailing lists, for example.  Most projects
have a mailing list for general user questions&mdash;sometimes the
list's name is "users", "discuss", "help", or something else.
Whatever its name, the purpose of the list is always the same: to
provide a place where people can get their questions answered, while
others watch and (presumably) absorb knowledge from observing these
exchanges.</para>

<para>These mailing lists work very well up to a few thousand users
and/or a couple of hundred posts a day.  But somewhere after that, the
system starts to break down, because every subscriber sees every post;
if the number of posts to the list begins to exceed what any
individual reader can process in a day, the list becomes a burden to
its members.  Imagine, for instance, if Microsoft had such a mailing
list for Windows XP.  Windows XP has hundreds of millions of users; if
even one-tenth of one percent of them had questions in a given
twenty-four hour period, then this hypothetical list would get
hundreds of thousands of posts per day!  Such a list could never
exist, of course, because no one would stay subscribed to it.
This problem is not limited to mailing lists; the same logic applies
to IRC channels, online discussion forums, indeed to any system in
which a group hears questions from individuals.  The implications are
ominous: the usual open source model of massively parallelized support
simply does not scale to the levels needed for world
domination.</para>

<para>There will be no explosion when forums reach the breaking point.
There is just a quiet negative feedback effect: people unsubscribe
from the lists, or leave the IRC channel, or at any rate stop
bothering to ask questions, because they can see they won't be heard
in all the noise.  As more and more people make this highly rational
choice, the forum's activity will seem to stay at a manageable level.
But it is staying manageable precisely because the rational (or at
least experienced) people have started looking elsewhere for
information&mdash;while the inexperienced people stay behind and
continue posting.  In other words, one side effect of continuing to
use unscalable communications models as the project grows is that the
average quality of both questions and answers tends to go down, which
makes it look like new users are dumber than they used to be, when in
fact they're probably not.  It's just that the benefit/cost ratio of
using those high-population forums goes down, so naturally those with
the experience to do so start to look elsewhere for answers first.
Adjusting communications mechanisms to cope with project growth
therefore involves two related strategies:</para>

<orderedlist>
  <listitem><para>Recognizing when particular parts of a forum are
            <emphasis>not</emphasis> suffering unbounded growth, even
            if the forum as a whole is, and separating those parts
            off into new, more specialized forums (i.e., don't let
            the good be dragged down by the bad).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>Making sure there are many automated sources
            of information available, and that they are kept
            organized, up-to-date, and easy to find.</para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>Strategy (1) is usually not too hard.  Most projects start out
with one main forum: a general discussion mailing list, on which
feature ideas, design questions, and coding problems can all be hashed
out.  Everyone involved with the project is on the list.  After a
while, it usually becomes clear that the list has evolved into several
distinct topic-based sublists.  For example, some threads are clearly
about development and design; others are user questions of the "How do
I do X?" variety; maybe there's a third topic family centered around
processing bug reports and enhancement requests; and so on.  A given
individual, of course, might participate in many different thread
types, but the important thing is that there is not a lot of overlap
between the types themselves.  They could be divided into separate
lists without causing any harmful balkanization, because the threads
rarely cross topic boundaries.</para>

<para>Actually doing this division is a two-step process.  You create
the new list (or IRC channel, or whatever it is to be), and then you
spend whatever time is necessary gently nagging and reminding people
to <emphasis>use</emphasis> the new forums appropriately.  That latter
step can last for weeks, but eventually people will get the idea.  You
simply have to make a point of always telling the sender when a post
is sent to the wrong destination, and do so visibly, so that other
people are encouraged to help out with routing.  It's also useful to
have a web page providing a guide to all the lists available; your
responses can simply reference that web page and, as a bonus, the
recipient may learn something about looking for guidelines before
posting.</para>

<para>Strategy (2) is an ongoing process, lasting the lifetime of the
project and involving many participants.  Of course it is partly a
matter of having up-to-date documentation (see
<xref linkend="documentation"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="getting-started"/></phrase>) and making sure to
point people there.  But it is also much more than that; the sections
that follow discuss this strategy in detail.</para>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect2 id="using-archives">
<title>Conspicuous Use of Archives</title>

<para>Typically, all communications in an open source project (except
sometimes IRC conversations) are archived.  The archives are public
and searchable, and have referential stability: that is, once a given
piece of information is recorded at a particular address, it stays at
that address forever.</para>

<para>Use those archives as much as possible, and as conspicuously as
possible.  Even when you know the answer to some question off the top
of your head, if you think there's a reference in the archives that
contains the answer, spend the time to dig it up and present it.
Every time you do that in a publicly visible way, some people learn
for the first time that the archives are there, and that searching in
them can produce answers.  Also, by referring to the archives instead
of rewriting the advice, you reinforce the social norm against
duplicating information.  Why have the same answer in two different
places?  When the number of places it can be found is kept to a
minimum, people who have found it before are more likely to remember
what to search for to find it again.  Well-placed references also
contribute to the quality of search results in general, because they
strengthen the targeted resource's ranking in Internet search
engines.</para>

<para>There are times when duplicating information makes sense,
however.  For example, suppose there's a response already in the
archives, not from you, saying:</para>

<screen>
It appears that your Scanley indexes have become frobnicated.  To
unfrobnicate them, run these steps:

1. Shut down the Scanley server.
2. Run the 'defrobnicate' program that ships with Scanley.
3. Start up the server.
</screen>

<para>Then, months later, you see another post indicating that
someone's indexes have become frobnicated.  You search the archives
and come up with the old response above, but you realize it's missing
some steps (perhaps by mistake, or perhaps because the software has
changed since that post was written).  The classiest way to handle
this is to post a new, more complete set of instructions, and
explicitly obsolete the old post by mentioning it:</para>

<screen>
It appears that your Scanley indexes have become frobnicated.  We
saw this problem back in July, and J. Random posted a solution at
http://blahblahblah/blah.  Below is a more complete description of
how to unfrobnicate your indexes, based on J. Random's instructions
but extending them a bit:

1. Shut down the Scanley server.
2. Become the user the Scanley server normally runs as.
3. As that user, run the 'defrobnicate' program on the indexes.
4. Run Scanley by hand to see if the indexes work now.
5. Restart the server.
</screen>

<para>(In an ideal world, it would be possible to attach a note to the
old post, saying that there is newer information available and
pointing to the new post.  However, I don't know of any archiving
software that offers an "obsoleted by" feature, perhaps because it
would be mildly tricky to implement in a way that doesn't violate the
archives' integrity as a verbatim record.  This is another reason why
creating dedicated web pages with answers to common questions is a
good idea.)</para>

<para>Archives are probably most often searched for answers to
technical questions, but their importance to the project goes well
beyond that.  If a project's formal guidelines are its statutory law,
the archives are its common law: a record of all decisions made and
how they were arrived at.  In any recurring discussion, it's pretty
much obligatory nowadays to start with an archive search.  This allows
you to begin the discussion with a summary of the current state of
things, anticipate objections, prepare rebuttals, and possibly
discover angles you hadn't thought of.  Also, the other participants
will <emphasis>expect</emphasis> you to have done an archive search.
Even if the previous discussions went nowhere, you should include
pointers to them when you re-raise the topic, so people can see for
themselves a) that they went nowhere, and b) that you did your
homework, and therefore are probably saying something now that has not
been said before.</para>

<sect3 id="all-as-archives">
<title>Treat all resources like archives</title>

<para>All of the preceding advice applies to more than just mailing
list archives.  Having particular pieces of information at stable,
conveniently findable addresses should be an organizing principle for
all of the project's information.  Let's take the project FAQ as a
case study.</para>

<para>How do people use a FAQ?</para>

<orderedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>They want to search in it for specific words and phrases.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>They want to browse it, soaking up information without
          necessarily looking for answers to specific questions.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>They expect search engines such as Google to know about the
          FAQ's content, so that searches can result in FAQ entries.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>They want to be able to refer other people directly to specific
          items in the FAQ.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>They want to be able to add new material to the FAQ, but
          note that this happens much less often than answers are
          looked up&mdash;FAQs are far more often read from than
          written to.</para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>Point 1 implies that the FAQ should be available in some sort of
textual format.  Points 2 and 3 imply that the FAQ should be available
as an HTML page, with point 2 additionally indicating that the HTML
should be designed for readability (i.e., you'll want some control
over its look and feel), and should have a table of contents.  Point 4
means that each individual entry in the FAQ should be assigned an HTML
<firstterm>named anchor</firstterm>, a tag that allows people to reach
a particular location on the page.  Point 5 means the source files for
the FAQ should be available in a convenient way (see <xref
linkend="version-everything"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="technical-infrastructure"/></phrase>), in a format
that's easy to edit.</para>

  <sidebar id="html-named-anchors-and-ids">
  <title>Named Anchors and ID Attributes</title>

  <para>There are two ways to get a browser to jump to a specific
  location within a web page: named anchors and id attributes.</para>

  <para>A <firstterm>named anchor</firstterm> is just a normal HTML
  anchor element (<literal>&lt;a&gt;...&lt;/a&gt;</literal>), but with
  a "name" attribute:</para>

  <screen>&lt;a&nbsp;name="mylabel"&gt;...&lt;/a&gt;</screen>

  <para>More recent versions of HTML support a generic <firstterm>id
  attribute</firstterm>, which can be attached to any HTML element,
  not just to <literal>&lt;a&gt;</literal>.  For example:</para>

  <screen>&lt;p&nbsp;id="mylabel"&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;</screen>

  <para>Both named anchors and id attributes are used in the same
  way.  One appends a hash mark and the label to a URL, to cause the
  browser to jump straight to that spot in the page:</para>

  <screen>http://myproject.example.com/faq.html#mylabel</screen>

  <para>Virtually all browsers support named anchors; most modern
  browsers support the id attribute.  To play it safe, I would
  recommend using either named anchors alone, or named anchors
  <emphasis>and</emphasis> id attributes together (with the same label
  for both in a given pair, of course).  Named anchors cannot be
  self-closing&mdash;even if there's no text inside the element, you
  must still write it in two-sided form:</para>

  <screen>&lt;a&nbsp;name="mylabel"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;</screen>

  <para>...though normally there would be some text, such as the title
  of a section.</para>

  <para>Whether you use a named anchor, or an id attribute, or both,
  remember that the label will not be visible to someone who browses
  to that location without using the label.  But such a person might
  want to discover the label for a particular location, so they can
  mail the URL for a FAQ answer to a friend, for example.  To help
  them do this, add a <firstterm>title attribute</firstterm> to the
  same element(s) where you added the "name" and/or "id" attribute,
  for example:</para>

  <screen>&lt;a&nbsp;name="mylabel"&nbsp;title="#mylabel"&gt;...&lt;/a&gt;</screen>

  <para>When the mouse pointer is held over the text inside the
  title-attributed element, most browsers will pop up a tiny box
  showing the title.  I usually include the hash-sign, to remind the
  user that this is what she would put at the end of the URL to jump
  straight to this location next time.</para>

  </sidebar>

<para>Formatting the FAQ like this is just one example of how to make
a resource presentable.  The same properties&mdash;direct
searchability, availability to major Internet search engines,
browsability, referential stability, and (where applicable)
editability&mdash;apply to other web pages, the source code tree, the
bug tracker, etc.  It just happens that most mailing list archiving
software long ago recognized the importance of these properties, which
is why mailing lists tend to have this functionality natively, while
other formats may require some extra effort on the maintainer's part
(<xref linkend="managing-volunteers"/> discusses how to spread
that maintenance burden across many volunteers).</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="codifying-tradition">
<title>Codifying Tradition</title>

<para>As a project acquires history and complexity, the amount of data
each incoming participant must absorb increases.  Those who have been
with the project a long time were able to learn, and invent, the
project's conventions as they went along.  They will often not be
consciously aware of what a huge body of tradition has accumulated, and
may be surprised at how many missteps recent newcomers seem to make.
Of course, the issue is not that the newcomers are of any lower
quality than before; it's that they face a bigger acculturation burden
than newcomers did in the past.</para>

<para>The traditions a project accumulates are as much about how to
communicate and preserve information as they are about coding
standards and other technical minutae.  We've already looked at both
sorts of standards, in
<xref linkend="developer-documentation"/><phrase output="printed"> 
in <xref linkend="getting-started"/></phrase> and
<xref linkend="written-rules"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="social-infrastructure"/></phrase> respectively, and
examples are given there.  What this section is about is how to keep
such guidelines up-to-date as the project evolves, especially
guidelines about how communications are managed, because those are the
ones that change the most as the project grows in size and
complexity.</para>

<para>First, watch for patterns in how people get confused.  If you
see the same situations coming up over and over, especially with new
participants, chances are there is a guideline that needs to be
documented but isn't.  Second, don't get tired of saying the same
things over and over again, and don't <emphasis>sound</emphasis> like
you're tired of saying them.  You and other project veterans will have
to repeat yourselves often; this is an inevitable side effect of the
arrival of newcomers.</para>

<para>Every web page, every mailing list message, and every IRC channel
should be considered advertising space&mdash;not for commercial
advertisements, but for ads about your project's own resources.  What
you put in that space depends on the demographics of those likely to
read it.  An IRC channel for user questions, for example, is likely to
get people who have never interacted with the project
before&mdash;often someone who has just installed the software, and
has a question he'd like answered immediately (after all, if it
could wait, he'd have sent it to a mailing list instead, which would
probably use less of his total time, although it would take longer
for an answer to come back).  People usually don't make a permanent
investment in the IRC channel; they'll show up, ask their question,
and leave.</para>

<para>Therefore, the channel topic should be aimed at people looking
for technical answers about the software <emphasis>right
now</emphasis>, rather than at, say, people who might get involved
with the project in a long term way and for whom community interaction
guidelines might be more appropriate.  Here's how a really busy
channel handles it (compare this with the earlier example in
<xref linkend="irc"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="technical-infrastructure"/></phrase>):</para>

<screen>
You are now talking on #linuxhelp

Topic for #linuxhelp is Please READ
http://www.catb.org/~esr/faqs/smart-questions.html &amp;&amp;
http://www.tldp.org/docs.html#howto BEFORE asking questions | Channel
rules are at http://www.nerdfest.org/lh_rules.html | Please consult
http://kerneltrap.org/node/view/799 before asking about upgrading to a
2.6.x kernel | memory read possible: http://tinyurl.com/4s6mc -&gt;
update to 2.6.8.1 or 2.4.27 | hash algo disaster: http://tinyurl.com/6w8rf
| reiser4 out
</screen>

<para>With mailing lists, the "ad space" is a tiny footer appended to
every message.  Most projects put subscription/unsubscription
instructions there, and perhaps a pointer to the project's home page
or FAQ page as well.  You might think that anyone subscribed to the
list would know where to find those things, and they probably
do&mdash;but many more people than just subscribers see those mailing
list messages.  An archived post may be linked to from many places;
indeed, some posts become so widely known that they eventually have
more readers off the list than on it.</para>

<para>Formatting can make a big difference.  For example, in the
Subversion project, we were having limited success using the
bug-filtering technique described in
<xref linkend="bug-filtering"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="technical-infrastructure"/></phrase>.  Many bogus
bug reports were still being filed by inexperienced people, and each
time it happened, the filer had to be educated in exactly the same way
as the 500 people before him.  One day, after one of our developers had
finally gotten to the end of his rope and flamed some poor user who
didn't read the issue tracker guidelines carefully enough, another
developer decided this pattern had gone on long enough.  He suggested
that we reformat the issue tracker front page so that the most
important part, the injunction to discuss the bug on the mailing lists
or IRC channels before filing, would stand out in huge, bold red
letters, on a bright yellow background, centered prominently above
everything else on the page.  We did so (you can see the results at
<ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org/project_issues.html"/>), and
the result was a noticeable drop in the rate of bogus issue filings.
We still get them, of course&mdash;we always will&mdash;but the rate
has slowed considerably, even as the number of users increases.  The
outcome is not only that the bug database contains less junk, but that
those who respond to issue filings stay in a better mood, and are more
likely to remain friendly when responding to one of the now-rare bogus
filings.  This improves both the project's image and the mental health
of its volunteers.</para>

<para>The lesson for us was that merely writing up the guidelines was
not enough.  We also had to put them where they'd be seen by those who
need them most, and format them in such a way that their status as
introductory material would be immediately clear to people unfamiliar
with the project.</para>

<para>Static web pages are not the only venue for advertising the
project's customs.  A certain amount of interactive policing (in the
friendly-reminder sense, not the handcuffs-and-jail sense) is also
required.  All peer review, even the commit reviews described in
<xref linkend="code-review"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="getting-started"/></phrase>, should include review
of people's conformance or non-conformance with project norms,
especially with regard to communications conventions.</para>

<para>Another example from the Subversion project: we settled on a
convention of "r12908" to mean "revision 12908 in the version control
repository."  The lower-case "r" prefix is easy to type, and because
it's half the height of the digits, it makes an easily-recognizable
block of text when combined with the digits.  Of course, settling on
the convention doesn't mean that everyone will begin using it
consistently right away.  Thus, when a commit mail comes in with a log
message like this:</para>

<screen>
------------------------------------------------------------------------
r12908 | qsimon | 2005-02-02 14:15:06 -0600 (Wed, 02 Feb 2005) | 4 lines

Patch from J. Random Contributor &lt;jrcontrib@gmail.com&gt;

* trunk/contrib/client-side/psvn/psvn.el:
  Fixed some typos from revision 12828.
------------------------------------------------------------------------
</screen>

<para>...part of reviewing that commit is to say "By the way, please
use 'r12828', not 'revision 12828' when referring to past changes."
This isn't just pedantry; it's important as much for automatic
parsability as for human readership.</para>

<para>By following the general principle that there should be
canonical referral methods for common entities, and that these
referral methods should be used consistently everywhere, the project
in effect exports certain standards.  Those standards enable people to
write tools that present the project's communications in more useable
ways&mdash;for example, a revision formatted as "r12828" could be
transformed into a live link into the repository browsing system.
This would be harder to do if the revision were written as "revision
12828", both because that form could be divided across a line break,
and because it's less distinct (the word "revision" will often appear
alone, and groups of numbers will often appear alone, whereas the
combination "r12828" can only mean a revision number).  Similar
concerns apply to issue numbers, FAQ items (hint: use a URL with a
named anchor, as described in
<xref linkend="html-named-anchors-and-ids"/>), etc.</para>

<para>Even for entities where there is not an obvious short, canonical
form, people should still be encouraged to provide key pieces of
information consistently.  For example, when referring to a mailing
list message, don't just give the sender and subject; also give the
archive URL <emphasis>and</emphasis> the Message-ID header.  The last
allows people who have their own copy of the mailing list (people
sometimes keep offline copies, for example to use on a laptop while
traveling) to unambiguously identify the right message even if they
don't have access to the archives.  The sender and subject wouldn't be
enough, because the same person might make several posts in the same
thread, even on the same day.</para>

<para>The more a project grows, the more important this sort of
consistency becomes.  Consistency means that everywhere people look,
they see the same patterns being followed, so they know to follow
those patterns themselves.  This, in turn, reduces the number of
questions they need to ask.  The burden of having a million readers is
no greater than that of having one; scalability problems start to
arise only when a certain percentage of those readers ask questions.
As a project grows, therefore, it must reduce that percentage by
increasing the density and accessibility of information, so that any
given person is more likely to find what he needs without having to
ask.</para>

<!--

<para><remark>See
<ulink
url="http://subversion.tigris.org/mailing-list-guidelines.html"/> for
an example of mailing list guidelines, talk about which problems such
guidelines can solve and which they can't.  Also, log message
guidelines (if that gets its own section, remember to adjust the xrefs
in Version Control Vocabulary and elsewhere in Chapter 3).  Mention
the parseability concern; point out that it can overdone, too.
Formatting of bug tracker numbers in log messages is an excellent
example of where parseability is an appropriate concern.  Log message
templates.  Make sure that commit reviews apply to log messages and
other "meta" aspects of the commit as well as to the code
itself.</remark></para>

-->

</sect2>

<!-- todo: A lot of projects have designated summarizers, like the
Zack Brown (?) for the Linux kernel, and I think I've seen similar
stuff at DebianPlanet as well.  That's another thing to talk about in
this discussion of "Strategy (2)", and maybe something to add to the
Project Roles examples in <xref linkend="share-management"/>.
-->

</sect1>

<sect1 id="bug-tracker-usage">
<title>No Conversations in the Bug Tracker</title>

<para>In any project that's making active use of its bug tracker,
there is always a danger of the tracker turning into a discussion
forum itself, even though the mailing lists would really be better.
Usually it starts off innocently enough: someone annotates an issue
with, say, a proposed solution, or a partial patch.  Someone else sees
this, realizes there are problems with the solution, and attaches
another annotation pointing out the problems.  The first person
responds, again by appending to the issue...and so it goes.</para>

<para>The problem with this is, first, that the bug tracker is a
pretty cumbersome place to have a discussion, and second, that other
people may not be paying attention&mdash;after all, they expect
development discussion to happen on the development mailing list, so
that's where they look for it.  They may not be subscribed to the
issue changes list at all, and even if they are, they may not follow it
very closely.</para>

<para>But exactly where in the process did something go wrong?  Was it
when the original person attached her solution to the
issue&mdash;should she have posted it to the list instead?  Or was it
when the second person responded in the issue, instead of on the
list?</para>

<para>There isn't one right answer, but there is a general principle:
if you're just adding data to an issue, then do it in the tracker, but
if you're starting a <emphasis>conversation</emphasis>, then do it on
the mailing list.  You may not always be able to tell which is the
case, but just use your best judgement.  For example, when attaching a
patch that contains a potentially controversial solution, you might be
able to anticipate that people are going to have questions about it.
So even though you would normally attach the patch to the issue
(assuming you don't want to or can't commit the change directly), in
this case you might choose to post it to a mailing list instead.  At
any rate, there eventually will come a point in the exchange where one
party or the other can tell that it is about to go from mere appending
of data to an actual conversation&mdash;in the example that started
this section, that would be the second respondent, who on realizing
that there were problems with the patch, could predict that a real
conversation is about to ensue, and therefore that it should be held
in the appropriate medium.</para>

<para>To use a mathematical analogy, if the information looks like it
will be quickly convergent, then put it directly in the bug tracker;
if it looks like it will be divergent, then a mailing list or IRC
channel would be a better place.</para>

<para>This doesn't mean there should never be any exchanges in the
bug tracker.  Asking for more details of the reproduction recipe
from the original reporter tends to be a highly convergent process,
for instance.  The person's response is unlikely to raise new issues;
it's simply going to flesh out information already filed.  There's no
need to distract the mailing list with that process; by all means,
take care of it with a series of comments in the tracker.  Likewise,
if you're fairly sure that the bug has been misreported (i.e., is not
a bug), then you can simply say so right in the issue.  Even pointing
out a minor problem with a proposed solution is fine, assuming the
problem is not a showstopper for the entire solution.</para>

<para>On the other hand, if you're raising philosophical issues about
the bug's scope or the software's proper behavior, you can be pretty
sure other developers will want to be involved.  The discussion is
likely to diverge for a while before it converges, so do it on the
mailing list.</para>

<para>Always link to the mailing list thread from the issue, when you
choose to post to the mailing list.  It's still important for someone
following the issue to be able to reach the discussion, even if the
issue itself isn't the forum of discussion.  The person who starts the
thread may find this laborious, but open source is fundamentally a
writer-responsible culture: it's much more important to make things
easy for the tens or hundreds of people who may read the bug than for
the three or five people writing about it.</para>

<para>It's fine to take important conclusions or summaries from the
list discussion and paste them into the issue, if that will make
things convenient for readers.  A common idiom is to start a list
discussion, put a link to the thread in the issue, and then when the
discussion finishes, paste the final summary into the issue (along
with a link to the message containing that summary), so someone
browsing the issue can easily see what conclusion was reached without
having to click to somewhere else.  Note that the usual "two masters"
data duplication problem does not exist here, because both archives
and issue comments are usually static, unchangeable data
anyway.</para>

</sect1>

<!-- ======================== SECTION ============================== -->
<sect1 id="publicity">
<title>Publicity</title>

<para>In free software, there is a fairly smooth continuum between
purely internal discussions and public relations statements.  This is
partly because the target audience is always ill-defined: given that
most or all posts are publicly accessible, the project doesn't have
full control over the impression the world gets.  Someone&mdash;say, a
<ulink url="http://slashdot.org/">slashdot.org</ulink>
editor&mdash;may draw millions of readers' attention to a post that no
one ever expected to be seen outside the project.  This is a fact of
life that all open source projects live with, but in practice, the
risk is usually small.  In general, the announcements that the project
most wants publicized are the ones that will be most publicized,
assuming you use the right mechanisms to indicate relative
newsworthiness to the outside world.</para>

<para>For major announcements, there tend to be four or five main
channels of distribution, on which announcements should be made as
nearly simultaneously as possible:</para>

<orderedlist>

  <listitem><para>Your project's front page is probably seen by more
            people than any other part of the project.  If you have a
            really major announcement, put a blurb there.  The blurb
            should be a very brief synopsis that links to the press
            release (see below) for more information.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>At the same time, you should also have a "News" or
            "Press Releases" area of the web site, where the
            announcement can be written up in detail.  Part of the
            purpose of a press release is to provide a single,
            canonical "announcement object" that other sites can link
            to, so make sure it is structured accordingly: either as
            one web page per release, as a discrete blog entry, or
            as some other kind of entity that can be linked to while
            still being kept distinct from other press releases in the
            same area.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>If your project has an RSS feed (see
            <xref linkend="rss"/>), make sure the announcement goes
            out there too.  This may happen automatically when you
            create the press release, depending on how things are set
            up at your site.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>If the announcement is about a new release of the
            software, then update your project's entry on
            <ulink url="http://freshmeat.net/"/> (see
            <xref linkend="announcing"/> about creating the entry
            in the first place).  Every time you update a Freshmeat
            entry, that entry goes onto the Freshmeat change list
            for the day.  The change list is updated not only on
            Freshmeat itself, but on various portal sites (including
            <ulink url="http://slashdot.org"/>) which are watched eagerly by
            hordes of people.  Freshmeat also offers the same data via
            RSS feed, so people who are not subscribed to your
            project's own RSS feed might still see the announcement
            via Freshmeat's.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>Send a mail to your project's announcement mailing
            list.  This list's name should actually be "announce",
            that is, <literal>announce@yourprojectdomain.org</literal>,
            because that's a fairly standard convention now, and the
            list's charter should make it clear that it is very
            low-traffic, reserved for major project announcements.
            Most of those announcements will be about new releases of
            the software, but occasionally other events, such as a
            fundraising drive, the discovery of a security
            vulnerability (see
            <xref linkend="security"/>)<phrase output="printed">
            later in this chapter</phrase>, or a
            major shift in project direction may be posted there as
            well.  Because it is low traffic and used only for
            important things, the <literal>announce</literal> list
            typically has the highest subscribership of any mailing
            list in the project (of course, this means you shouldn't
            abuse it&mdash;consider carefully before posting).  To
            avoid random people making announcements, or worse, spam
            getting through, the <literal>announce</literal> list must
            always be moderated.</para>
  </listitem>

</orderedlist>

<para>Try to make the announcements in all these places at the same
time, as nearly as possible.  People might get confused if they see an
announcement on the mailing list but then don't see it reflected on
the project's home page or in its press releases area.  If you get the
various changes (emails, web page edits, etc.) queued up and
then send them all in a row, you can keep the window of inconsistency
very small.</para>

<para>For a less important event, you can eliminate some or all of the
above outlets.  The event will still be noticed by the outside world
in direct proportion to its importance.  For example, while a new
release of the software is a major event, merely setting the date of
the next release, while still somewhat newsworthy, is not nearly as
important as the release itself.  Setting a date is worth an email to
the daily mailing lists (not the announce list), and an update of the
project's timeline or status web page, but no more.</para>

<para>However, you might still see that date appearing in discussions
elsewhere on the Internet, wherever there are people interested in the
project.  People who are lurkers on your mailing lists, just listening
and never saying anything, are not necessarily silent elsewhere.  Word
of mouth gives very broad distribution; you should count on it, and
construct even minor announcements in such a way as to encourage
accurate informal transmission.  Specifically, posts that you expect
to be quoted should have a clearly meant-to-be-quoted portion, just as
though you were writing a formal press release.  For example:</para>

  <blockquote>
     <para><emphasis>Just a progress update: we're planning to release
     version 2.0 of Scanley in mid-August 2005.  You can always check
     http://www.scanley.org/status.html for updates.  The major new
     feature will be regular-expression searches.</emphasis></para>

     <para><emphasis>Other new features include:&nbsp;... There will
     also be various bugfixes, including:&nbsp;...</emphasis></para>
  </blockquote>

<para>The first paragraph is short, gives the two most important
pieces of information (the release date and the major new feature),
and a URL to visit for further news.  If that paragraph is the only
thing that crosses someone's screen, you're still doing pretty well.
The rest of the mail could be lost without affecting the gist of the
content.  Of course, sometimes people will link to the entire mail
anyway, but just as often, they'll quote only a small part.  Given that
the latter is a possibility, you might as well make it easy for them,
and in the bargain get some influence over what gets quoted.</para>

<!-- ======================== subsection ============================== -->
<sect2 id="security">
<title>Announcing Security Vulnerabilities</title>

<para>Handling a security vulnerability is different from handling any
other kind of bug report.  In free software, doing things openly and
transparently is normally almost a religious credo.  Every step of the
standard bug-handling process is visible to all who care to watch: the
arrival of the initial report, the ensuing discussion, and the
eventual fix.</para>

<para>Security bugs are different.  They can compromise users' data,
and possibly users' entire computers.  To discuss such a problem
openly would be to advertise its existence to the entire
world&mdash;including to all the parties who might make malicious use
of the bug.  Even merely committing a fix effectively announces the
bug's existence (there are potential attackers who watch the commit
logs of public projects, systematically looking for changes that
indicate security problems in the pre-change code).  Most open source
projects have settled on approximately the same set of steps to handle
this conflict between openness and secrecy, based on the these basic
guidelines:</para>

<orderedlist>
  <listitem><para>Don't talk about the bug publicly until a fix is
            available; then supply the fix at exactly the same moment
            you announce the bug.</para> 
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para>Come up with that fix as fast as you
            can&mdash;especially if someone outside the project
            reported the bug, because then you know there's at least
            one person outside the project who is able to exploit the
            vulnerability.</para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>In practice, those principles lead to a fairly standardized
series of steps, which are described in the sections below.</para>

<sect3 id="security-receiving">
<title>Receive the report</title>

<para>Obviously, a project needs the ability to receive security bug
reports from anyone.  But the regular bug reporting address won't do,
because it can be watched by anyone too.  Therefore, have a separate
mailing list for receiving security bug reports.  That mailing list
must not have publicly readable archives, and its subscribership must
be strictly controlled&mdash;only long-time, trusted developers can be
on the list.  If you need a formal definition of "trusted", you can
use "anyone who has had commit access for two years or more" or
something like that, to avoid favoritism.  This is the group that will
handle security bugs.</para>

<para>Ideally, the security list should not be spam-protected or
moderated, since you don't want an important report to get filtered
out or delayed just because no moderators happened to be online that
weekend.  If you do use automated spam-protection software, try to
configure it with high-tolerance settings; it's better to let a few spams
through than to miss a report.  For the list to be effective, you must
advertise its address, of course; but given that it will be unmoderated
and, at most, lightly spam-protected, try to never to post its address
without some sort of address hiding transformation, as described in
<xref linkend="address-hiding"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="technical-infrastructure"/></phrase>.
Fortunately, address-hiding need not make the address illegible; see
<ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org/security.html"/>, and view
that page's HTML source, for an example.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="security-finding-a-fix">
<title>Develop the fix quietly</title>

<para>So what does the security list do when it receives a report?
The first task is to evaluate the problem's severity and
urgency:</para>

<orderedlist>
  <listitem><para>How serious is the vulnerability?  Does it allow a
            malicious attacker to take over the computer of someone
            who uses your software?  Or does it, say, merely leak
            information about the sizes of some of their files?</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para>How easy is it to exploit the vulnerability?  Can
            an attack be scripted, or does it require circumstantial
            knowledge, educated guessing, and luck?</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem><para><emphasis>Who</emphasis> reported the problem to
            you?  The answer to this question doesn't change the
            nature of the vulnerability, of course, but it does give
            you an idea of how many other people might know about it.
            If the report comes from one of the project's own
            developers, you can breathe a little easier (but only a
            little), because you can trust them not to have told
            anyone else about it.  On the other hand, if it came in an
            email from <literal>anonymous14@globalhackerz.net</literal>,
            then you'd better act as fast as you can.  The person did
            you a favor by informing you of the problem at all, but you
            have no idea how many other people she's told, or how long
            she'll wait before exploiting the vulnerability on live
            installations.</para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>

<para>Note that the difference we're talking about here is often just
a narrow range between <emphasis>urgent</emphasis>
and <emphasis>extremely&nbsp;urgent</emphasis>.  Even when the report
comes from a known, friendly source, there could be other people on
the Net who discovered the bug long ago and just haven't reported it.
The only time things aren't urgent is when the bug inherently does not
compromise security very severely.</para>

<para>The "<literal>anonymous14@globalhackerz.net</literal>" example
is not facetious, by the way.  You really may get bug reports from
identity-cloaked people who, by their words and behavior, never quite
clarify whether they're on your side or not.  It doesn't matter: if
they've reported the security hole to you, they'll feel they've done
you a good turn, and you should respond in kind.  Thank them for the
report, give them a date on or before which you plan to release a
public fix, and keep them in the loop.  Sometimes they may
give <emphasis>you</emphasis> a date&mdash;that is, an implicit threat
to publicize the bug on a certain date, whether you're ready or not.
This may feel like a bullying power play, but it's more likely a
pre&euml;mptive action resulting from past disappointment with
unresponsive software producers who didn't take security reports
seriously enough.  Either way, you can't afford to tick this person
off.  After all, if the bug is severe, he has knowledge that could
cause your users big problems.  Treat such reporters well, and hope
that they treat you well.</para>

<para>Another frequent reporter of security bugs is the security
professional, someone who audits code for a living and keeps up on the
latest news of software vulnerabilities.  These people usually have
experience on both sides of the fence&mdash;they've both received and
sent reports, probably more than most developers in your project have.
They too will usually give a deadline for fixing a vulnerability
before going public.  The deadline may be somewhat negotiable, but
that's up to the reporter; deadlines have become recognized among
security professionals as pretty much the only reliable way to get
organizations to address security problems promptly.  So don't treat
the deadline as rude; it's a time-honored tradition, and there are
good reasons for it.</para>

<para>Once you know the severity and urgency, you can start working on
a fix.  There is sometimes a tradeoff between doing a fix elegantly
and doing it speedily; this is why you must agree on the urgency
before you start.  Keep discussion of the fix restricted to the
security list members, of course, plus the original reporter (if she
wants to be involved) and any developers who need to be brought in for
technical reasons.</para>

<para>Do not commit the fix to the repository.  Keep it in patch form
until the go-public date.  If you were to commit it, even with an
innocent-looking log message, someone might notice and understand the
change.  You never know who is watching your repository and why they
might be interested.  Turning off commit emails wouldn't help; first
of all, the gap in the commit mail sequence would itself look
suspicious, and anyway, the data would still be in the repository.
Just do all development in a patch and keep the patch in some private
place, perhaps a separate, private repository known only to the people
already aware of the bug.  (If you use a decentralized version control
system like Arch or SVK, you can do the work under full version
control, and just keep that repository inaccessible to
outsiders.)</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="security-cve">
<title>CAN/CVE numbers</title>

<para>You may have seen a <firstterm>CAN number</firstterm> or
a <firstterm>CVE number</firstterm> associated with security problems.
These numbers usually look like "CAN-2004-0397" or
"CVE-2002-0092", for example.</para>

<para>Both kinds of numbers represent the same type of entity: an
entry in the list of "Common Vulnerabilities and Exposures" list
maintained at <ulink url="http://cve.mitre.org/"/>.  The purpose of
the list is to provide standardized names for all known security
problems, so that everyone has a unique, canonical name to use when
discussing one, and a central place to go to find out more
information.  The only difference between a "CAN" number and a "CVE"
number is that the former represents a candidate entry, not yet
approved for inclusion in the official list by the CVE Editorial
Board, and the latter represents an approved entry.  However, both
types of entries are visible to the public, and an entry's number does
not change when it is approved&mdash;the "CAN" prefix is simply
replaced with "CVE".</para>

<para>A CAN/CVE entry does not itself contain a full description of
the bug and how to protect against it.  Instead, it contains a brief
summary, and a list of references to external resources (such as
mailing list archives) where people can go to get more detailed
information.  The real purpose of <ulink url="http://cve.mitre.org/"/>
is to provide a well-organized space in which every vulnerability can
have a name and a clear route to more data.  See
<ulink url="http://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=2002-0092"/>
for an example of an entry.  Note that the references can be very
terse, with sources appearing as cryptic abbreviations.  A key to
those abbreviations is at
<ulink url="http://cve.mitre.org/data/refs/refkey.html"/>.</para>

<para>If your vulnerability meets the CVE criteria, you may wish to
acquire it a CAN number.  The process for doing so is deliberately
gated: basically, you have to know someone, or know someone who knows
someone.  This is not as crazy as it might sound.  In order for the
CVE Editorial Board to avoid being overwhelmed with spurious or
poorly written submissions, they take submissions only from sources
they already know and trust.  In order to get your vulnerability
listed, therefore, you need to find a path of acquaintance from your
project to the CVE Editorial Board.  Ask around among your developers;
one of them will probably know someone else who has either done the
CAN process before, or knows someone who has, etc.  The advantage of
doing it this way is also that somewhere along the chain, someone may
know enough to tell you that a) it wouldn't count as a vulnerability
or exposure according to MITRE's criteria, so there is no point
submitting it, or b) the vulnerability already
<emphasis>has</emphasis> a CAN or CVE number.  The latter can happen
if the bug has already been published on another security advisory
list, for example at <ulink url="http://www.cert.org/"/> or on the
BugTraq mailing list at <ulink url="http://www.securityfocus.com/"/>.
(If that happened without your project hearing about it, then you
should worry what else might be going on that you don't know
about.)</para>

<para>If you get a CAN/CVE number at all, you usually want to get it
in the early stages of your bug investigation, so that all further
communications can refer to that number.  CAN entries are embargoed
until the go-public date; the entry will exist as an empty placeholder
(so you don't lose the name), but it won't reveal any information
about the vulnerability until the date on which you will be announcing
the bug and the fix.</para>

<para>More information about the CAN/CVE process may be found at
<ulink url="http://cve.mitre.org/cve/identifiers/candidates_explained.html" />, and a
particularly clear exposition of one open source project's use of
CAN/CVE numbers is at
<ulink
url="http://www.debian.org/security/cve-compatibility"/>.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="security-prenotification">
<title>Pre-notification</title>

<para>Once your security response team (that is, those developers who
are on the security mailing list, or who have been brought in to deal
with a particular report) has a fix ready, you need to decide how to
distribute it.</para>

<para>If you simply commit the fix to your repository, or otherwise
announce it to the world, you effectively force everyone using your
software to upgrade immediately or risk being hacked.  It is sometimes
appropriate, therefore, to do <firstterm>pre-notification</firstterm>
for certain important users.  This is particularly true with
client/server software, where there may be well-known servers that are
tempting targets for attackers.  Those servers' administrators would
appreciate having an extra day or two to do the upgrade, so that they
are already protected by the time the exploit becomes public
knowledge.</para>

<para>Pre-notification simply means sending mails to those
administrators before the go-public date, telling them of the
vulnerability and how to fix it.  You should send pre-notification
only to people you trust to be discreet with the information.  That
is, the qualification for receiving pre-notification is twofold: the
recipient must run a large, important server where a compromise would
be a serious matter, <emphasis>and</emphasis> the recipient must be
known to be someone who won't blab about the security problem before
the go-public date.</para>

<para>Send each pre-notification mail individually (one at a time) to
each recipient.  Do <emphasis>not</emphasis> send to the entire list
of recipients at once, because then they would see each others'
names&mdash;meaning that you would essentially be alerting each
recipient to the fact that each <emphasis>other</emphasis> recipient
may have a security hole in her server.  Sending it to them all via
blind CC (BCC) isn't a good solution either, because some admins
protect their inboxes with spam filters that either block or reduce
the priority of BCC'd mail, since so much spam is sent via BCC these
days.</para>

<para>Here's a sample pre-notification mail:</para>

<screen>
From: Your Name Here
To: admin@large-famous-server.com
Reply-to: Your Name Here (not the security list's address)
Subject: Confidential Scanley vulnerability notification.


This email is a confidential pre-notification of a security alert
in the Scanley server.

Please *do not forward* any part of this mail to anyone.  The public
announcement is not until May 19th, and we'd like to keep the
information embargoed until then.

You are receiving this mail because (we think) you run a Scanley
server, and would want to have it patched before this security hole is
made public on May 19th.

References:
===========

   CAN-2004-1771: Scanley stack overflow in queries

Vulnerability:
==============

   The server can be made to run arbitrary commands if the server's
   locale is misconfigured and the client sends a malformed query.

Severity:
=========

   Very severe, can involve arbitrary code execution on the server.

Workarounds:
============

   Setting the 'natural-language-processing' option to 'off' in
   scanley.conf closes this vulnerability.

Patch:
======

   The patch below applies to Scanley 3.0, 3.1, and 3.2.

   A new public release (Scanley 3.2.1) will be made on or just before
   May 19th, so that it is available at the same time as this
   vulnerability is made public.  You can patch now, or just wait for
   the public release.  The only difference between 3.2 and 3.2.1 will
   be this patch.

[...patch goes here...]
</screen>

<para>If you have a CAN number, include it in the pre-notification (as
shown above), even though the information is still embargoed and
therefore the MITRE page will show nothing.  Including the CAN number
allows the recipient to know with certainty that the bug they were
pre-notified about is the same one they later hear about through
public channels, so they don't have to worry whether further action is
necessary or not, which is precisely the point of CAN/CVE
numbers.</para>

</sect3>

<sect3 id="security-announcing">
<title>Distribute the fix publicly</title>

<para>The last step in handling a security bug is to distribute the
fix publicly.  In a single, comprehensive announcement, you should
describe the problem, give the CAN/CVE number if any, describe how to
work around it, and how to permanently fix it.  Usually "fix" means
upgrading to a new version of the software, though sometimes it can
mean applying a patch, particularly if the software is normally run in
source form anyway.  If you do make a new release, it should differ
from some existing release by exactly the security patch.  That way,
conservative admins can upgrade without worrying about what else they
might be affecting; they also don't have to worry about future upgrades,
because the security fix will be in all future releases as a matter of
course.  (Details of release procedures are discussed in
<xref linkend="security-releases"/><phrase output="printed"> in
<xref linkend="development-cycle"/></phrase>.)</para>

<para>Whether or not the public fix involves a new release, do the
announcement with roughly the same priority as you would a new
release: send a mail to the project's <literal>announce</literal>
list, make a new press release, update the Freshmeat entry, etc.
While you should never try to play down the existence of a security
bug out of concern for the project's reputation, you may certainly set
the tone and prominence of a security announcement to match the actual
severity of the problem.  If the security hole is just a minor
information exposure, not an exploit that allows the user's entire
computer to be taken over, then it may not warrant a lot of fuss.  You
may even decide not to distract the <literal>announce</literal> list
with it.  After all, if the project cries wolf every time, users might
end up thinking the software is less secure than it actually is, and
also might not believe you when you have a really big problem to
announce.  See
<ulink url="http://cve.mitre.org/about/terminology.html"/> for a good
introduction to the problem of judging severity.</para>

<para>In general, if you're unsure how to treat a security problem,
find someone with experience and talk to them about it.  Assessing and
handling vulnerabilities is very much an acquired skill, and it's easy
to make missteps the first few times.</para>

</sect3>

</sect2>

</sect1>

</chapter>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "chapter")
end:
-->
